<topic id="xinclude">
    <title>XInclude Support</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q18"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db comes with partial support for the XInclude standard. By default, eXist-db's XML
        serializer will scan all XML fragments for XInclude tags. </p>
        <section id="introduction">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>The XInclude processor is implemented as a filter in between the serializer's output
            event stream and the receiver. If it finds an XInclude element, it will try to expand
            it. XInclude processing is therefore applied whenever eXist-db serializes an XML
            fragment,whether it's a document, the result of an XQuery or an XSLT stylesheet.</p>
        <p>eXist-db's does not support the full XInclude standard:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p> You cannot include raw text, only XML.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> XPointers are restricted to XPath. Additional features defined in the
                    XPointer spec (points and locations) are not supported. However, you can use
                    XPath functions to partly work around this and substitute XPointer's important
                    <ph>string-range()</ph> function. </p>
            </li>
            </ul>

        <p>eXist-db expands XIncludes at serialization, which means that the query engine will
            see the XInclude tags <i>before</i> they are expanded. You therefore
            cannot query across XIncludes, unless you create your own code (e.g. an XQuery function)
            for it.</p>
        <p>DTD entity declarations can be used for some of the things that XInclude can be used
            for. In general, however, XInclude is more powerful (with the exception that entity
            declarations are able include raw text). </p>

        <p>The XInclude namespace (in the examples below bound to the prefix <ph>xi:</ph>)
            is:</p>
        <pre>http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude</pre>
    </section>
        <section id="include-doc">
            <title>Including entire documents</title>
        

        <p>To include an entire document, simply specify its path in the <ph>href</ph>
            attribute of an <ph>xi:include</ph> element.</p>
        <p>For example, one can include a standard disclaimer, stored in the file
            <ph>short-disclaimer.xml</ph>, as follows: <ph>xi:include
            href="/db/apps/doc/data/disclaimer-short.xml"/</ph>
            </p>


        <p>If the URI in the <ph>href</ph> attribute specifies a known scheme (like
            <ph>http:</ph> or <ph>file:</ph>), eXist-db will try to load it as an external
            resource. For example: <ph>xi:include
            href="http://localhost:8080/exist/rest/db/apps/doc/data/disclaimer-short.xml"/</ph>
            </p>


        <p>If no scheme is specified, the XInclude processor will first try to load the
            referenced document from the database (relative to the current collection), and if that
            fails, from the file system.</p>
        <p>If the document that contains the XInclude has been constructed in an XQuery (see
            <xref href="#sect-xquery-results" scope="local"/>), relative file system paths will be resolved
            relative to the main XQuery module source file.</p>

    </section>
        <section id="select-part">
            <title>Selecting parts of a resource</title>
        

        <p>The <ph>xpointer</ph> attribute of the <ph>xi:include</ph> element can be
            used to identify which part of the resource to include.</p>

        

        <section id="select-ident">
                <title>Selection by identifier</title>
            

            <p>If the XPointer contains a simple value it is interpreted as an identifier. This
                will select the element in the target document that has a matching attribute of type
                identifier (<ph>ID</ph>) (usually <ph>xml:id</ph>).</p>
            <p> For example, assume an XInclude target document <ph>disclaimer.xml</ph> looks
                like this:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;disclaimer&gt;
  &lt;p xml:id="p1"&gt;
    First disclaimer ...
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p xml:id="p2"&gt;
    Second disclaimer ...
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/disclaimer&gt;</pre>
            <p>the following XInclude selects the element from <ph>disclaimer.xml</ph>
                with an <ph>identifier</ph> attribute with value <ph>p1</ph>:
                <ph>xi:include href="disclaimer.xml" xpointer="p1"/</ph>
                </p>
            <p>When there are multiple instances of the same identifier attribute, only the first
                instance will be used.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="select-xpath">
                <title>Selecting by XPath expression</title>
            

            <p>We can also use an XPath expression to select fragments. For this the
                <ph>xpointer</ph> attribute must contain an XPointer, which consists of so
                called "schemes". An XPath expression can be passed through the
                <ph>xpointer()</ph> XPointer scheme. </p>
            <p> The following expression includes the first stage direction in Shakespeare's
                Macbeth:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/demo/data/macbeth.xml" xpointer="xpointer(//PLAY/ACT[1]/SCENE[1]/STAGEDIR[1])"/&gt;
</pre>

        </section>

        

        <section id="select-search">
                <title>Selecting by a search expression</title>
            

            <p>XIncludes can also perform searches, for instance using a full-text search:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/demo/data/hamlet.xml" xpointer="xpointer(//SPEECH[ft:query(., '" slings="slings" and="and" arrows"')/LINE[1])"="arrows"')/LINE[1])""/&gt;
</pre>
            <p>The XPath expression will be applied to the entire collection if the path in
                <ph>href</ph> points to a collection and not a single document:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/demo/data" 
  xpointer="xpointer(//SPEECH[ft:query(., '"cursed spite"')]/LINE[1])"/&gt;
</pre>
            <p>In all cases, only the first hit is retrieved.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="ns-map">
                <title>Namespace mappings</title>
            

            <p>All namespace/prefix mappings declared in the source document are passed to the
                query context. If necessary you can declare additional namespace mappings using
                <ph>xmlns()</ph>, like this:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="disclaimer.xml" xpointer="xpointer(//comment:comment)
  xmlns(comment=http://test.org)"/&gt;
</pre>
        </section>

    </section>
        <section id="sect-xquery-results">
            <title>Including XQuery results</title>
        

        <p>It is possible to include the result of an XQuery script by XInclude. If the target of
            an XInclude reference points to an XQuery document stored in the database (binary
            resource with MIME type <ph>application/xquery</ph>), the XInclude processor will
            attempt to compile and execute this query and use its results. </p>
        <p>For example:<ph>xi:include href="display-collection.xq"/</ph>
            </p>
        <p>The XInclude processor declares two variables in the XQuery's static context:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>$xinclude:current-doc</ph> </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The name of the document which XInclude-s the query (without its
                        collection path)</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>$xinclude:current-collection</ph> </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>the collection in which the current document resides</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
        <p>You can also pass additional parameters to the XQuery script: <ph>xi:include
            href="testvars.xq?var1=Hello&amp;var2=World"/</ph>
            </p>
        <p>The parameters <ph>var1</ph> and <ph>var2</ph> will be available
            to the XQuery as an external global variable. The XQuery needs to declare them:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare variable $var1 external;
declare variable $var2 external;</pre>

    </section>
        <section id="errors">
            <title>Error Handling</title>
        

        <p>An error is raised if you try to XInclude a resource which does not exist. You can
            specify a fallback to avoid this. The result of the XInclude will be the content of the
            <ph>xi:fallback</ph> element:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="I-do-not exist.xml"&gt;
  &lt;xi:fallback&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;
      The included document was not found!
    &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/xi:fallback&gt;
  &lt;xi:include&gt;
</pre>

        <p>A fallback element itself cannot contain XInclude elements.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="xpointer">
            <title>Implementing XPointer <ph>string-range()</ph> </title>
        

        <p>One reason why the XPointer spec has hardly seen any implementation is that it
            operates with "points" and "locations" which have no equivalent in the XPath Data Model.
            However, a major use case for the XPointer specification is to allow pointing at a range
            of characters inside an element. Luckily, we can work around the absence of this using
            the XPath functions <ph>string-join()</ph> and <ph>substring()</ph>.</p>
        <p>In the following example, a range of characters in the text node of a <ph>LINE</ph>
            element is extracted, 20 characters long, starting at the 22nd character:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/demo/data" xpointer="xpointer(
      substring(string-join(//PLAY/ACT[3]/SCENE[1]/SPEECH[19]/LINE[1],''), 22, 20)
    )"/&gt;
</pre>
        <p>Since only string contents is involved, these ranges can also work on text nodes
            belonging to different elements. In the following example, parts of succeeding lines are
            extracted from the SPEECH element: </p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xi:include href="/db/apps/demo/data" xpointer="xpointer(
      substring(string-join(//PLAY/ACT[3]/SCENE[1]/SPEECH[19], ''), 202, 24)
    )"/&gt;
</pre>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>