<topic id="devguide_log4j">
    <title>Log4j Logging Guide</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q20"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="java-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article explains logging and eXist-db's use of <xref href="https://logging.apache.org/log4j/" scope="external">Log4j</xref>.</p>
        <section id="overview">
            <title>Overview</title>
        

        <p>Logging may seem like a less important part of an application. After all, it consumes
            resources: programmer time, increasing class file size, CPU cycles, etc. All while doing
            nothing to provide end-user functionality. However, logging is an important part of any
            substantial body of software and is absolutely critical in enterprise software. A big
            issue with the use of the logging system when troubleshooting is that it changes to the
            log configuration require a <i>restart</i>. Yet, users are often
            extremely reluctant to restart their production servers. <xref href="https://logging.apache.org/log4j/" scope="external">Log4j</xref> is the most powerful
            Java-based logging library available today. It provides a many features to address such
            concerns.</p>

        

        <section id="intro">
                <title>Introducing Log4j</title>
            

            <p>Log4j is based on the following core concepts:</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Each log event is issued by a hierarchically named <ph>logger</ph>,
                        e.g. <ph>xx.method.server.httpgw</ph> which can correspond to Java class
                        names.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>All log events have an associated severity level:</p>
                    <simpletable>
                            <sthead>
                                <stentry> Level </stentry>
                                <stentry> Usage </stentry>
                            </sthead>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Trace</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> Very low-level debugging “execution is here”
                                        debugging/troubleshooting messages. </stentry>
                            </strow>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Debug</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> Messages of interest to those debugging or
                                        troubleshooting (with greater importance than trace
                                        messages). Probably only meaningful to developers
                                    </stentry>
                            </strow>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Info</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> General informational messages. Understandable by
                                        and/or of interest to non-developers as well.
                                    </stentry>
                            </strow>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Warn</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> Warnings of potential problems </stentry>
                            </strow>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Error</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> Error conditions </stentry>
                            </strow>
                            <strow>
                                <stentry>  <ph>Fatal</ph>  </stentry>
                                <stentry> Fatal error conditions, For instance a shut down,
                                        a likely crash or something equally severe </stentry>
                            </strow>
                        </simpletable>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Logging is controlled either via a Log4j configuration file. Exist-db's
                        main log configuration file responsible for the <ph>exist.log</ph>
                        is located at <ph>exist/etc/log4j2.xml</ph>. To issue log events
                        programmatically you must acquire a logger by name and specify a log message
                        and its severity level (and optionally a <ph>Throwable</ph> where
                        applicable). </p>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>Based on these core concepts, Log4j provides a powerful set of
                functionalities:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Many “appender” choices</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Each log event may be output to zero or more “appenders”. These are
                            generalized output pipes, e.g. <ph>System.out/err</ph>,
                            <ph>JDBC</ph>, <ph>syslog</ph> etc. </p>
                        <p>When outputing to a file various options for log rolling are
                            available. For instance daily creation of new log files, segmenting when
                            a given file size is reached, and externally controlled log rotation.
                            These appenders can be run synchronously to the threads generating the
                            log events or as separate asynchronous queues.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Flexible layout options</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Each appender can specify a layout, for formatting the log message.
                            The administrator can choose from <ph>HTML</ph>,
                            <ph>XML</ph>, and <ph>text</ph> formats – including
                            the flexible <ph>PatternLayout</ph>, which allows selecting the data
                            to include (timestamps, originating thread, logger name, etc.).</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Hierarchical logger configuration</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Administrators can configure log event cutoff levels and appenders for
                            entire branches of the hierarchical logger tree.</p>
                        <p>For instance, by adding a <ph>console</ph> appender targeting
                            <ph>System.out</ph> to the root logger, all Log4j output will go to
                            <ph>System.out</ph>. One can configure the overall cutoff level as
                            <ph>error</ph> at the root logger level so that only error and fatal
                            messages are output, unless otherwise specified. One could then
                            configure the <ph>xx.method</ph> logger to have an <ph>info</ph>
                            level cutoff and an appender to capture all output to a specified file
                            (in addition to <ph>System.out</ph>). These <ph>xx.method</ph>
                            settings would then affect all loggers whose names begin with
                            <ph>xx.method</ph>. (e.g.
                            <ph>xx.method.server.httpgw</ph>).</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Log viewers</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Various free and commercial products provide specialized viewing
                            capabilities for Log4j logs. Apache provides a very useful Log4j log
                            viewer <xref href="https://logging.apache.org/chainsaw" scope="external">Chainsaw</xref>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>

            <p>For more information visit the <xref href="https://logging.apache.org/log4j/" scope="external">Log4j website</xref> website. </p>

            <note type="note">
                    <p>Java 1.4 and higher’s <ph>java.util.logging</ph> API is very similar to
                    Log4j’s. However Log4j is much more powerful in a number of critical areas. </p>
                    <p>In conjunction with our JMX MBeans for Log4j, one can also: </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>Dynamically examine and reconfigure the Log4j configuration for the
                            duration of the process via a JMX console.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Have all processes using a Log4j configuration file periodically check
                            its modification date and automatically re-load it upon any
                            change.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Force an immediate reload from a configuration file via a JMX
                            console.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
                </note>

        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="config">
            <title>Configuring Log4j</title>
        
        
        <note type="note">
                <p>A full listing of the default log configuration files and the contents of
                <ph>$EXIST_HOME/logs/</ph> is not yet included in this guide. Contributions
                are welcome.</p>
            </note>

        <p>The <ph>$EXIST_HOME/etc/log4j2.xml</ph> configuration file controls Log4j’s
            behavior. Log files are written <ph>$EXIST_HOME/logs/</ph>. The configuration file
            is used mainly to set a given level of log output for loggers. Without such
            configuration only ERROR and FATAL log events will show up. Therefore you have to change
            the configuration to see <ph>trace</ph>, <ph>debug</ph>, <ph>info</ph>, or
            <ph>warn</ph> log events in the Log4j output. </p>
        <p>To turn on a given logging level for all loggers, find the <ph>Log4j.root</ph>
            property and change its priority value to the desired level. For instance:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;root&gt;
  &lt;priority value="debug"/&gt;
  &lt;appender-ref ref="exist.core"/&gt;
&lt;/root&gt;</pre>
        <p>Change the priority level to <ph>info</ph> to see informational messages:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;root&gt;
  &lt;priority value="info"/&gt;
  &lt;appender-ref ref="exist.core"/&gt;
&lt;/root&gt;</pre>
        <p>This will result in a cacophony of log output, so you’ll generally want to adjust the
            logging level to a more specific level. For instance:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;category name="org.exist.security" additivity="false"&gt;
  &lt;priority value="info"/&gt;
  &lt;appender-ref ref="exist.security"/&gt;
&lt;/category&gt;</pre>
        <p>This sets the <ph>org.exist.security</ph> logger’s level to
            <ph>info</ph>.</p>
        <p>Note that doing this causes the default log level of all
            <ph>org.exist.security</ph> loggers to be set to <ph>info</ph>. For example, the
            level of the <ph>org.exist.security.xacml</ph> logger would also be set to
            <ph>info</ph>, unless of course the level for this logger is specified explicitly. </p>
        <p>Checking the Log4j configuration file is done periodically so changes may go unnoticed
            for a few minutes.</p>
        <p>To make temporary changes to the Log4j configuration without changing the
            configuration files, use JMX MBeans:</p>

        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Start <ph>jconsole</ph> </p>
                <p> <ph>jconsole</ph> is located in the Java SDK’s bin directory. You can
                    either double-click on it or run it from the command line.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Select the target JVM</p>
                <p> <ph>jconsole</ph> will list the Java processes running on your machine
                    under the current user, which have been configured to allow local JMX
                    connections.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Navigate to the Logging node in the MBean tree:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>Select the MBeans tab.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Expand the right folder.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>In the servlet engine expand the <ph>WebAppContext</ph> folder and
                            the folder named after your web app.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Select the <ph>Logging</ph> node (which should now be
                            visible).</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Perform desired operations and/or modifications:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>To change the configuration file check interval, change the
                            <ph>ConfigurationCheckInterval</ph> attribute to the desired number
                            of seconds. Note that this change will apply only for the duration of
                            the JVM process unless you select the Loader node and its save
                            operation.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>To force an immediate reload of the configuration file, press the
                            <ph>reconfigure</ph> button on the operations
                            tab.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>To examine other aspects of the configuration and make temporary
                            changes, press the <ph>registerLoggers</ph> button on
                            the operation tab. Expand the <ph>Logging</ph> tree
                            node and examine/operate upon its children.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
        <section id="use">
            <title>Using Log4j in Java</title>
        

        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Acquire a logger: </p>
                <pre outputclass="java">import org.apache.logging.log4j.LogManager; import org.apache.logging.log4j.Logger; … private Logger logger = LogManager.getLogger("xx.method.server.httpgw");
</pre>

                <p>Remarks:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>This is a somewhat time-consuming operation and should be done in
                            constructors of relatively long-lived objects or in static
                            initializers.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Many classes can separately acquire a logger using the same logger
                            name. They will all end up with their own reference to the same shared
                            logger object.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Use the logger: </p>
                <pre outputclass="java">logger.info( "Something I really wanted to say" );</pre>
                <p>Remarks:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>info()</ph> is just one of Logger’s methods for issuing Log4j
                            log events. It implicitly assigns the event a severity level of
                            <ph>info</ph> and does not specify a <ph>Throwable</ph>. Logger
                            methods for issuing log events include:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">public void trace(Object message); 
    public void trace(Object message, Throwable t); 
    public void debug(Object message); 
    public void debug (Object message, Throwable t); 
    public void info(Object message); 
    public void info(Object message, Throwable t); 
    public void warn(Object message); 
    public void warn(Object message, Throwable t); 
    public void error(Object message); 
    public void error(Object message, Throwable t); 
    public void fatal(Object message); 
    public void fatal(Object message, Throwable t);</pre>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Note that in each case the message is an Object, not a
                            <ph>String</ph>. If (and only if) Log4j decides to output the given
                            log event (based on the configuration), it will render this object as a
                            <ph>String</ph> (essentially via <ph>toString()</ph>).</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p> You emit log events with appropriate log levels to appropriately named loggers. The
            Log4j configuration determines which appenders (if any) should output/record the event
            and how this should be done. </p>
        <section id="converting">
                <title>Converting existing logging code to Log4j</title>
            

            <p>Conversion of existing logging code to Log4j can be as simple as replacing
                <ph>System.out.println()</ph> calls, etc, with use of the Log4j API. There are a
                few special considerations worth noting.</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Dealing with Legacy Properties</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>You'll have to check the functionality of existing logging properties: </p>
                        <ul>
                                <li>
                                <p> For instance, properties specifying output files can be
                                    removed, as customers can now siphon Log4j output to specific
                                    files via Log4j’s configuration files. </p>
                                <p/>
                            </li>
                                <li>
                                <p>To preserve well-known logging properties regardless, given
                                    the following example code:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="java">private static final boolean VERBOSE_SERVER;
   static
   {
     XXProperties properties = XXProperties.getLocalProperties();
     VERBOSE_SERVER = properties.getProperty("xx.method.verboseServer", false);
   }
   …
   if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
     System.out.println( "some message" );</pre>
                                <p>The static portions above can be left as is and the remainder
                                    changed to:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="java">import org.apache.log4j.Level;
   import org.apache.log4j.Logger;

   // place VERBOSE_SERVER declaration and static block from above here
   private static final Logger  serverLogger =
                                     Logger.getLogger( "xx.method.server" );
   static
   {
     if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
       serverLogger.setLevel( Level.ALL );
   }
   …
   serverLogger.debug( "some message" );</pre>
                                <p>This example assumes that output from the given Log4j logger
                                    should be completely enabled when the existing property is
                                    set.</p>
                                <p>One can also use this:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="java">if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )
     if ( !serverLogger.isDebugEnabled() )
       serverLogger.setLevel( Level.DEBUG );</pre>
                                <p>This causes the existing property to enable output from the
                                    given Log4j logger up through the severity level,
                                    <ph>debug</ph>. </p>
                                <p>This approach to preserving existing “enabling” properties a
                                    partal fix. The intended minimum log verbosity is ensured upon
                                    initialization but cannot be reset via the property without a
                                    restart. The ability to change the log-level on the fly or make
                                    fine grained log-level adjustments is only available through the
                                    Log4j configuration. </p>
                            </li>
                            </ul>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Conditional Computation of Data for Logging</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>When log messages are constructed conditionallys:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">if ( VERBOSE_SERVER )  // static final boolean
   {
     // various computations and assignment
   }</pre>
                        <p>The <ph>if</ph> block may include
                            <ph>System.out.println()</ph>’s or the results of the block may be
                            used in later <ph>System.out.println()</ph>’s. The code is intended
                            to avoid computations and assignments unless their results are
                            used.</p>
                        <p>You can now use one of Log4j’s <ph>is*Enabled()</ph> methods for
                            this. For example: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">if ( serverLogger.isDebugEnabled() )
   {
     // various computations and assignment that will only be used
     // if serverLogger.debug() calls
   }</pre>
                        <p>The Log4j Logger class provides a set of methods for this:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">public boolean isTraceEnabled();
   public boolean isDebugEnabled();
   public boolean isInfoEnabled();
   public Boolean isEnabledFor(Level);</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="tips">
            <title>Tips and Tricks</title>
        
        <p>This section contains useful hints based on our user's experiences.</p>
        <section id="general">
                <title>General</title>
            

            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Carefully select appropriate logger names</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Logger names should be meaningful and facilitate hierarchical
                            configuration by administrators. Use a namespace prefix, either
                            <ph>xx</ph> or <ph>com.xxx</ph> to avoid collision with logger
                            names from 3rd-party libraries and customizations. </p>
                        <p>For instance, one might have <ph>xx.method.server</ph> for general
                            logging related to various low-level aspects of the method server and
                            <ph>xx.method.server.timing</ph> for logging specifically related to
                            the method timing. Use Java class and package names where these make
                            sense. </p>
                        <p/>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Document your logger if appropriate</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>If appropriate, document your logger in
                            <ph>/xxx/src_web/loggers.html</ph>. For instance when the output is
                            of interest to your customer. The logger should be documented (by name)
                            in <ph>/xxx/src_web/loggers.html</ph> (which ends up in xxx’s
                            codebase in an installation).</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Select appropriate levels for log events</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p> See the table above for an outline of levels and their intended
                            usage. <xref href="#loglevel" scope="local"/>
                            </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Don’t go overboard with the Log4j configuration files</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Log4j provides a great deal of ease and flexibility in its
                            configuration. Its log viewers also make it easy to merge log data from
                            multiple Log4j logs or filter out the data of interest from a general
                            purpose log. Given this it makes little sense to provide a complex Log4j
                            configuration file. The customer can change the configuration to have
                            more or less specific log outputs as dictated by their needs and
                            desires. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Adjust log levels in Log4j configuration files where appropriate</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>By default only <ph>error</ph> and <ph>fatal</ph> log messages
                            are created. This generates relatively "quiet" logs that only alert
                            administrators to issues. There are however sometimes log messages
                            classified as <ph>informational</ph> that should be output at this
                            log level as well. Such as periodic information about process health
                            summaries. Simply enable info level debig ouput in the for the logger in
                            question. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Don’t include redundant data in log messages</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Log4j includes current time, thread name, logger name, evernt level,
                            etc information in a standard fashion so it is easily interpreted by log
                            viewers. Inclusion of any of these pieces of information in the log
                            message itself is therefore redundant. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>make use of <ph>AttributeListWrapper</ph> where appropriate</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>For some particularly significant logs it is important to have even
                            more control, including: </p>
                        <ul>
                                <li>
                                <p>To select which attributes should be included in a given log
                                    message</p>
                            </li>
                                <li>
                                <p>To specify the order of these attributes</p>
                            </li>
                                <li>
                                <p>To specify the formatting of these attributes (e.g. comma
                                    delimited, with or without attribute names, etc)</p>
                            </li>
                            </ul>
                        <p>Examples of such cases include request access and periodic statistics
                            logging. </p>
                        <p>There is a re-usable utility for just this purpose,
                            <ph>xx.jmx.core.AttributeListWrapper</ph>. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>

        

        <section id="performance">
                <title>Performance</title>
            

            <p>The operation of Log4j’s Logger class’s logging methods for issuing log events can
                be summed up as: </p>
            <pre outputclass="java">public void  log( Level level, Object message )
{
  if ( isEnabledFor( level ) )
  {
    String  string = render( messasge );
    for ( Appender appender : myAppenders )
      appender.output( string );
  }
}</pre>

            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p> <ph>render()</ph> is simply a <ph>toString()</ph> call, except
                        when <ph>message</ph> is an instance of a class for which a specialized
                        render has been registered.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p> <ph>trace()</ph>, <ph>debug()</ph>, <ph>info()</ph>,
                        <ph>warn()</ph>, <ph>error()</ph>, etc, call <ph>log()</ph> with
                        the appropriate level.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>

            <p>Note that Log4j's documentation claims that <ph>isEnabledFor()</ph>, and the
                <ph>Logger.is*Enabled()</ph> method are extremely fast. Therefore
                <ph>log()</ph> should take very little time as well (unless
                <ph>isEnabledFor()</ph> returns <ph>true</ph>). </p>
            <p>Given this, a few additional performance tips and tricks: </p>

            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Don’t reacquire a logger on each usage</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>The <ph>LogR.getLogger()</ph> (and underlying
                            <ph>Logger.getLogger()</ph>) calls are relatively expensive. One
                            should acquire these objects once per class (or once per instance of a
                            class) and re-use them in subsequent logging calls. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Don’t assume a log’s level cannot change</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>One of the big advantages of Log4j is that administrators can easily
                            change the level setting of any logger at any time. One can however
                            easily undo this by following conventions common in existing logging
                            code, e.g.: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">static boolean  LOG_ENABLED = logger.isInfoEnabled ();
…
public void someMethod()
{
  if ( LOG_ENABLED )
    logger.info( … );
}</pre>
                        <p> <ph>Logger</ph>’s <ph>isEnabledFor()</ph> and
                            <ph>is*Enabled()</ph> routines are fast enough to allow calling them
                            more frequently in order to obtain the benefits of dynamically
                            configurable logging levels. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Don’t check whether the log level is enabled before every log call</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Do not write code as: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">if ( logger.isDebugEnabled() )
  logger.debug( "Some constant string" );</pre>
                        <p>This results in essentially no savings when
                            <ph>isDebugEnabled()</ph> is <ph>true</ph>. It also makes the
                            code more verbose and harder to read. Instead do: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">logger.debug( "Some constant string" );</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Do avoid doing additional work for logging unless the logger is
                        enabled</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Assume the last example looked like: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">if ( logger.isDebugEnabled() )
  logger.debug( "Object " + object.getDisplayIdentity() + 
                " is being deleted" );</pre>
                        <p>Then the <ph>isDebugEnabled()</ph> check should be performed. In
                            this case, two string concatenations and a potentially (somewhat)
                            expensive method call can be saved when the logger is not debug enabled.
                            See the “Conditional Computation of Data for Logging” section above for
                            another example of this pattern. </p>
                        <p>On the other hand, this technique should not be used when you are all
                            but certain the given logger will be enabled. Usually this applies only
                            to log events being emitted with an <ph>error</ph> or
                            <ph>fatal</ph> level. In this case saving times for the few cases in
                            which someone has actually disabled this level of logging is not
                            worthwhile. </p>
                        <p>Another technique to avoid unnecessary work is to leverage the fact
                            that <ph>Logger</ph>’s take objects, not strings, as arguments. Thus
                            one might write: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">SomeClass  someObj = new SomeClass(…);
logger.info( someObj );</pre>
                        <p>Here one will pay for the construction of <ph>someObj</ph> in all
                            cases but will only pay for <ph>someObj.toString()</ph> when logging
                            is enabled for info-level log events. Thus if very little work is done
                            in the constructor and most is done in toString() this avoids doing work
                            except when necessary. <ph>AttributeListWrapper</ph> (see above) is
                            an example of this technique. </p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>Hoist log level checks outside of very tight loops</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>For cases where a given log level will usually not be enabled, for
                            instance for trace and debug log messages, one should avoid repeated
                            checks within a tight loop. For example: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="java">{
  final boolean  traceEnabled = logger.isTraceEnabled();
  for ( int ii = 0; ii &lt; n; ++ii )
  {
    // do some very quick stuff
    if ( traceEnabled )
      logger.trace( ... );
    // do a little more very quick stuff
  }
}</pre>
                        <p>Trace level logging is rarely enabled and so in this example checking
                            for this case ahead of time can save us from repeatedly verifying this
                            in a tight loop. This does, however, come at the cost of making it
                            impossible to dynamically enable trace logging for this logger in the
                            middle of this loop. Due to this, this technique should only be used for
                            tight loops where the duration of the execution represented by the loop
                            (and thus the time during which the logging behavior may lag the
                            intended setting) is small.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>

        </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>