<topic id="repo">
    <title>Package Repository</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>The eXist-db package repository is a central component of eXist-db. It makes it easy to
        manage and deploy external packages (<ph>.xar</ph> archives) which include everything
        they need to run third party XQuery libraries, full applications or other XML technology
        functionality. This article provides technical details on the packaging format.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>The package repository is based on and extends the <xref href="http://expath.org/modules/pkg/" scope="external">EXPath Packaging System</xref>. The core
            of the EXPath packaging specification has been designed to work across different XQuery
            implementations and is targeted at managing extension libraries (including XQuery, Java
            or XSLT code modules). eXist-db extends this core by adding a facility for the automatic
            deployment of entire applications into the database. </p>
        <p>eXist-db packages may fall into one of the following categories:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Applications</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p> Contain application code, HTML views, associated services, resources and
                        data. An application always has a web interface which can be displayed, if
                        for example the user clicks on the application icon in the Dashboard.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Resource packages</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p> Contain only data or resources used by other applications, e.g.
                        JavaScript libraries shared by several application packages. A resource
                        package has no web view, but needs to be deployed into the database.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Library packages</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p> Provide a set of XQuery library modules to be registered with eXist-db
                        and used by other packages. A library package may also contain Java
                        <ph>.jar</ph> archives to be loaded into the eXist-db classpath. It has
                        no web view and is not deployed into the database.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>

        <p>These categories are not exclusive. An application may include resources and XQuery
            libraries and is not required to move those into separate packages.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="expath-pkg">
            <title>EXPath Packaging Format</title>
        

        <p>An EXPath package is essentially an archive file in ZIP format. By convention, the
            file extension of the package is <ph>.xar</ph>. </p>
        <p>The archive <i>must</i> contain two XML descriptor files in the root
            directory: <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> and <ph>repo.xml</ph>:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                    <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph>
                </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>This is the standard EXPath descriptor as defined by the EXPath
                        specification. It specifies the unique name of the package, lists
                        dependencies and any library modules to register globally. See <xref href="#sect-expathpkg" scope="local"/>.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                    <ph>repo.xml</ph>
                </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The eXist-db specific deployment descriptor: it contains additional
                        metadata about the package and controls how it will be deployed into the
                        database. See <xref href="#sect-repoxml" scope="local"/>.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
        <p>For library packages <ph>repo.xml</ph> is optional. However, we recommend to
            always provide it for better tool integration.</p>
        <p>The following is not mentioned in the EXPath spec, but if an image resource with the
            filename <ph>icon.png</ph> or <ph>icon.svg</ph> is found in the root
            directory of an app, the eXist-db dashboard will display that user-supplied image
            instead of the default eXist-db blue dotted <ph>X</ph>.</p>

        

        <section id="sect-expathpkg">
                <title>
                    <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph>
                </title>
            

            <p>As an example, the EXPath descriptor for the documentation app is shown
                below:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;package xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/pkg" abbrev="exist-documentation" name="http://exist-db.org/apps/doc" spec="1.0" version="5.2.1-SNAPSHOT"&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;
    eXist-db Documentation
  &lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;home&gt;
    https://www.github.com/exist-db/documentation
  &lt;/home&gt;
  &lt;dependency processor="http://exist-db.org" semver-min="5.3.0-SNAPSHOT"/&gt;
  &lt;dependency package="http://exist-db.org/html-templating"/&gt;
&lt;/package&gt;</pre>
            <p>The schema of this file is documented in the specification. In short, the
                attributes are as follows:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>name</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>URI used as a unique identifier for the package. The URI does not need
                            to point to an existing web site. The package repository will use this
                            URI to identify a package within the system.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>abbrev</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Short abbreviation for the package. This will be used as part of the
                            file name for the <ph>.xar</ph>. We recommend to choose a
                            short, simple name, without spaces or punctuation characters.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>version</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Version of the package. This allows the Package Manager to determine
                            if newer versions of the same package are available.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>spec</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Version of the packaging specification the package conforms to. Always
                            <ph>1.0</ph> for the current specification.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>title</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Descriptive title to display to the user (in the Dashboard)</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>

            <section id="dependencies">
                    <title>Dependency Management</title>
                

                <p>A package may depend on one or more other packages. The Package Manager in the
                    Dashboard will resolve these dependencies before deployment. Dependant packages
                    will be installed automatically from the public repository. It is an error if a
                    dependency cannot be resolved.</p>
                <p>A dependency on another package is defined by using a reference to the unique
                    name of the other package: The name attribute (URI) of the
                    <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> descriptor. For eaxample:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;dependency package="http://exist-db.org/html-templating"/&gt;</pre>
                <p>It is also possible to create a dependency on a specific version, based on
                        <xref href="https://semver.org/" scope="external">Semantic
                        Versioning</xref>. This can be done by adding either of the attributes:
                    <ph>version</ph>, <ph>semver</ph>, <ph>semver-min</ph>,
                    <ph>semver-max</ph>: </p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>
                                <ph>version</ph>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>A simple version string which must exactly match the version
                                string of the package to install.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>
                                <ph>semver</ph>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>A "semantic" version string: the version number must follow the
                                scheme <ph>x.x.x</ph>. Selects the highest version in the range
                                of versions starting with <ph>semver</ph>. </p>
                            <p>For example, if semver is <ph>1.2</ph>, a package with version
                                <ph>1.2.3</ph> will be selected because it is in the
                                <ph>1.2</ph> release series. Likewise, if <ph>semver</ph> is
                                <ph>1</ph>, any package with a version starting with
                                <ph>1</ph> will be chosen.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>
                                <ph>semver-min</ph>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Defines a minimal required version according to the
                                <ph>semver</ph> scheme.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>
                                <ph>semver-max</ph>
                            </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Defines a maximum version according to the <ph>semver</ph>
                                scheme.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
                <p>These attributes are mutually exclusive, except for <ph>semver-min</ph>
                    and <ph>semver-max</ph>, which may appear together. We recommend using
                    <ph>semver</ph>, <ph>semver-min</ph> and <ph>semver-max</ph> where
                    possible.</p>
                <p>It is also possible to require a certain eXist-db version (for versions
                    greater than 2.2). The Dashboard will prevent installation of packages into
                    unsupported instances and display a warning to the user. To require such a
                    specific eXist-db version, include a processor dependency in your
                    descriptor:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;dependency processor="http://exist-db.org" semver-min="3.1.0" semver-max="4.5.0"/&gt;</pre>
            </section>

            

            <section id="library-modules">
                    <title>Library Modules</title>
                

                <p>A package may list one or more library modules to register with eXist-db. The
                    registered modules will become globally available within the eXist-db instance
                    and may be used by other packages without knowing where the module code is
                    stored. </p>
                <p>For example, the following descriptor registers the module
                        <ph>functx.xql</ph> using the given namespace: </p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;package xmlns="http://expath.org/ns/pkg" name="http://www.functx.com" abbrev="functx" version="1.0" spec="1.0"&gt;
  &lt;title&gt;
    FunctX library
  &lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;xquery&gt;
    &lt;namespace&gt;
      http://www.functx.com
    &lt;/namespace&gt;
    &lt;file&gt;
      functx.xql
    &lt;/file&gt;
  &lt;/xquery&gt;
&lt;/package&gt;</pre>
                <p>The namespace has to correspond to the namespace defined in the module
                    declaration of the XQuery module. The file should be placed into a subdirectory
                    of the .xar archive, named "content". The structure of the <ph>.xar</ph> for
                    the <ph>functx</ph> library would be as follows:</p>
                <pre>/expath-pkg.xml
/repo.xml
/content/functx.xql</pre>
                <p>Only XQuery files which are registered in <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> need to
                    go into this special directory. You are free to keep other XQuery files wherever
                    you want. Also, XQuery resources which are only used by a single application,
                    should <i>not</i> be registered (to avoid messing up the global
                    context). Registering a module only makes sense for libraries which will likely
                    be used by several applications.</p>
                <p>After installing the package, you should be able to use the registered XQuery
                    modules from anywhere within the database instance without knowing the exact
                    import path. Thus the following import statement will be sufficient to import
                    the <ph>functx</ph> module:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace functx="http://www.functx.com";

functx:capitalize-first('hello')</pre>
            </section>

            

            <section id="java-lib">
                    <title>Java Libraries</title>
                

                <p>eXist-db also supports XQuery extension modules written in Java. These require
                    a slightly different mechanism for integration into a <ph>.xar</ph>
                    package. This is an extension to the standard EXPath format and should goes into
                    a separate file, named <ph>exist.xml</ph>. </p>
                <p>As an example, the <ph>exist.xml</ph> descriptor of the cryptographic
                    extension module is shown below:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;package xmlns="http://exist-db.org/ns/expath-pkg"&gt;
  &lt;jar&gt;
    expath-crypto.jar
  &lt;/jar&gt;
  &lt;java&gt;
    &lt;namespace&gt;
      http://expath.org/ns/crypto
    &lt;/namespace&gt;
    &lt;class&gt;
      org.expath.exist.crypto.ExistExpathCryptoModule
    &lt;/class&gt;
  &lt;/java&gt;
&lt;/package&gt;</pre>
                <p>The descriptor may contain one or more <ph>jar</ph> elements, each pointing
                    to a Java <ph>.jar</ph> archive to be installed. Arbitrary
                    <ph>.jar</ph> files can be listed here: they do not need to be XQuery
                    extension modules. Again, the <ph>.jar</ph> files should be placed into the
                    "content" subdirectory of the <ph>.xar</ph> file.</p>
                <p>All <ph>.jar</ph> files will be dynamically added to eXist-db's class
                    loader and become immediately available after deploying a package. A restart of
                    eXist-db is not required.</p>
                <p>The <ph>java</ph> element registers an XQuery extension module written in
                    Java. This is similar to the <ph>xquery</ph> element for library modules,
                    except that the namespace is mapped to a Java class instead of an XQuery file.
                    The Java class should point to the <ph>Module</ph> class which defines
                    the module.</p>
            </section>

        </section>

        

        <section id="sect-repoxml">
                <title>
                    <ph>repo.xml</ph>
                </title>
            

            <p>The deployment descriptor contains additional metadata and defines how the package
                will be installed into an eXist-db database instance. For example:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;meta xmlns="http://exist-db.org/xquery/repo"&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;
    eXist-db Documentation
  &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;author&gt;
    eXist-db
  &lt;/author&gt;
  &lt;website&gt;
    https://www.github.com/exist-db/documentation
  &lt;/website&gt;
  &lt;status&gt;
    stable
  &lt;/status&gt;
  &lt;license&gt;
    GNU Lesser General Public License, version 2.1
  &lt;/license&gt;
  &lt;copyright&gt;
    true
  &lt;/copyright&gt;
  &lt;type&gt;
    application
  &lt;/type&gt;
  &lt;target&gt;
    doc
  &lt;/target&gt;
  &lt;prepare&gt;
    pre-install.xql
  &lt;/prepare&gt;
  &lt;deployed/&gt;
&lt;/meta&gt;</pre>
            <p>The two settings: <ph>type</ph> and <ph>target</ph> determine how a
                package is handled by the installer:</p>
            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>
                                Type of package
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                type
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                target
                            </stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>
                                Application package
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                <ph>application</ph>
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                specified
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>
                                Resource package
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                <ph>library</ph>
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                specified
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>
                                Library package
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                <ph>library</ph>
                            </stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                not specified
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>An application package has <ph>type</ph> set to <ph>application</ph> and
                specifies a <ph>target</ph> because it needs to be deployed into the database.
                Contrary to this, a library package only registers XQuery or other modules, but no
                resources need to be stored into the database, so <ph>target</ph> is empty.</p>

            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>type</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Should be set to either <ph>application</ph> or
                            <ph>library</ph>. We assume a library has no GUI. A library will
                            therefore not be shown on the main Dashboard page, which only lists
                            applications.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>target</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Specifies the collection where the contents of the package will be
                            stored. Top-level files in the package will end up in this collection,
                            resources in sub-directories will go into sub-collections. Please note
                            that the target collection can be changed by the package manager during
                            install: It is a recommendation, not a requirement.</p>
                        <p>The collection path should be relative to the repository root
                            collection defined in the configuration (usually
                            <ph>/db/apps</ph>).</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>permissions</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>You can define package specific permissions in the
                                <ph>repo.xml</ph> to use when uploading package contents
                            like this: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;permissions user="app-user" password="123" group="app-group" mode="rw-rw-r--"/&gt;</pre>
                        <p> All resources and collections will be owned by the specified user and
                            permissions will be changed to those given in <ph>mode</ph>.
                            If the user does not exist, the deploy function will try to create it,
                            using the password specified in the <ph>password</ph>
                            attribute.</p>
                        <p>Concerning permissions: the execute <ph>x</ph> flag will be set
                            automatically on all XQuery files, in addition to the default
                            permissions defined in the descriptor. For more control over
                            permissions, use a post-install XQuery script (see element
                                <ph>finish</ph> below).</p>
                        <p> It is generally recommended to specify users in this manner when a
                            package requires write privileges to the database, and to use a custom
                            user-group (i.e. not <ph>dba</ph>). To avoid conflicts with locally
                            defined user-names and group names, packages that do not require write
                            access can omit permissions in their <ph>repo.xml</ph>. These
                            packages will be assigned to the <ph>guest</ph> user group by
                            default.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>prepare</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Points to an XQuery script inside the root of the package archive,
                            which will be executed before any package data is uploaded to the
                            database. By convention the XQuery script is called
                                <ph>pre-install.xql</ph>, but this is not a
                            requirement.</p>
                        <p>If you create a package via eXide, it will generate a default
                                <ph>pre-install.xql</ph> which uploads the default
                            collection configuration to the system collection. This needs to be done
                            before deployment to guarantee that index definitions are applied when
                            data is uploaded to the db.</p>
                        <p>The target collection, the file system path to the current package
                            directory and eXist-db's home directory, are passed to the script as
                            external variables:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">(: file path pointing to the eXist-db installation directory :)
declare variable $home external;
(: path to the directory containing the unpacked .xar package :)
declare variable $dir external;
(: the target collection into which the app is deployed :)
declare variable $target external;</pre>
                        <p>The script can use these to read files contained in the
                            package.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>finish</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Like <ph>prepare</ph>, this element must point to an XQuery script.
                            This will be executed <i>after</i> all data has been
                            uploaded to the database. It receives the same external variables as the
                            prepare script. The convention is to name the script
                                <ph>post-install.xql</ph>.</p>
                        <p>Use the <ph>finish</ph> script to run additional tasks or move data
                            into different collections. For example, the XQuery function
                            documentation app runs an indexing task from the finish trigger to
                            extract documentation from all XQuery modules known to the database at
                            the time.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>deployed</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>This element is set automatically when the package is deployed into a
                            database instance. It is used by eXide to track changes and does not
                            need to be specified in the original <ph>repo.xml</ph>
                            descriptor.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>

    </section>
        <section id="considerations">
            <title>General considerations when writing a package</title>
        

        <p>Packages should be portable and should not make any assumptions about the collection
            path in which they will be installed. So best to use relative paths throughout XQuery
            modules, in particular for import statements. Just as a reminder: a relative path in an
            "import module namespace..." expression is always relative to the XQuery which contains
            the import.</p>
        <p>If an XQuery needs to access data provided by another package, it should locate the
            other package by its package name and not by using an absolute collection path which may
            change in the future. For example, if an application requires access to data stored in
            another package called "data-pkg", it could define a variable to point to the correct
            collection as follows:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare namespace expath = "http://expath.org/ns/pkg";

declare variable $local:data-pkg-collection :=
    let $descriptor :=
        collection(repo:get-root())//expath:package[@name = "http://foo.com/data-pkg"]
    return
        util:collection-name($descriptor)
;

(: Query data provided by data-pkg :)
collection($local:data-pkg-collection)//foo</pre>
    </section>
        <section id="config-root">
            <title>Configuring the repository root</title>
        

        <p>The root collection for deployed packages can be configured in
                <ph>conf.xml</ph>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;repository root="/db/apps"/&gt;</pre>
        <p>The install location specified in the <ph>target</ph> element of
                <ph>repo.xml</ph> will always be relative to this root collection.</p>
        <p>eXist-db's URL rewriting is by default configured to map any path starting with
            <ph>/apps</ph> to the repository root collection. Check
                <ph>etc/webapp/WEB-INF/controller-config.xml</ph> and the <xref href="urlrewrite" scope="external">URL rewriting documentation</xref>.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="programm-install">
            <title>Programmatically installing packages</title>
        

        <p>The <ph>repo</ph> XQuery module provides a number of functions to
            programmatically install, remove or inspect packages. The Dashboard Package Manager
            relies on the same functions.</p>
        <p>The module distinguishes between <i>installation</i> and
                <i>deployment</i> steps. The reason for this distinction is: while the
            installation process is standardized by the EXPath packaging specification, the
            deployment step is implementation defined and specific to eXist-db.
                <i>Installation</i> will register a package with the EXPath packaging
            system, but not copy anything into the database. <i>Deployment</i> will
            deploy the application into the database as specified by the <ph>repo.xml</ph>
            descriptor.</p>
        <p>The most convenient way to install a package are the
            <ph>repo:install-and-deploy</ph> and <ph>repo:install-and-deploy-from-db</ph>
            functions. <ph>repo:install-and-deploy</ph> downloads the specified package from a
            public repository. For example, one can install the eXist-db demo apps using the
            following call:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">repo:install-and-deploy("http://www.functx.com", "1.0", "https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/public-repo/find")</pre>
        <p>The first parameter denotes the unique name of the package to install. The second may
            contain a specific version or the empty sequence. The third parameter is the URI for the
            public repository. The function call will download, install and deploy the package as
            well as any dependencies it defines. If the installation succeeds, an element will be
            returned to indicate the target collection into which the package was deployed.</p>
        <p>The <ph>repo:install-and-deploy-from-db</ph> function works in a similar way, but
            reads the package data to install from a resource stored in the database.</p>
        <p>To uninstall a package, you should first call <ph>repo:undeploy</ph>, followed by
            <ph>repo:remove</ph>. For instance:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">repo:undeploy("http://exist-db.org/apps/demo"), repo:remove("http://exist-db.org/apps/demo")</pre>
        <p>To list all installed packages, call <ph>repo:list</ph>. This will return the
            unique name of every installed package. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="run-repo">
            <title>Running your own repository</title>
        

        <p>You can run your private repository and install packages from it, for instance to
            distribute applications to your customers. The eXist-db repository is implemented by the
            application package <ph>http://exist-db.org/apps/public-repo</ph>. The code can be
            downloaded from the <xref href="https://github.com/eXist-db/public-xar-repo" scope="external">eXist-db GitHub</xref>
            repo.</p>
        <p>Once you have built and installed the app, you can upload the package
            <ph>.xar</ph> files you wish to distribute into the collection
                <ph>public-repo/public</ph>. To make the uploaded <ph>.xar</ph> files
            available, run the query <ph>public-repo/modules/update.xql</ph> once as an
            <ph>admin</ph> user. This will create a document <ph>apps.xml</ph> in
                <ph>public-repo/public</ph>.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>