<topic id="oldrangeindex">
    <title>Legacy Range index</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="indexing"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article describes eXist-db's old range index. This has been replaced by a <xref href="newrangeindex" scope="external">redesigned range index</xref> (since eXist 2.2). The old index is
        still available for compatibility reasons. Its use is discouraged.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>Range indexes provide a shortcut for the database to directly select nodes based on
            their typed values. They are used when matching or comparing nodes by way of standard
            XPath operators and functions. Without a range index, comparison operators like
            <ph>=</ph>, <ph>&gt;</ph> or <ph>&lt;</ph> will default to a "brute-force"
            inspection of the DOM, which can be extremely slow if eXist-db has to search through
            maybe millions of nodes: each node has to be loaded and cast to the target type.</p>
        <p>To see how range indexes work, consider the following fragment:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;items&gt;
  &lt;item n="1"&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;
      Tall Bookcase
    &lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;
      299.99
    &lt;/price&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
  &lt;item n="2"&gt;
    &lt;name&gt;
      Low Bookcase
    &lt;/name&gt;
    &lt;price&gt;
      199.99
    &lt;/price&gt;
  &lt;/item&gt;
&lt;/items&gt;</pre>
        <p>With this short inventory, the text nodes of the <ph>price</ph> elements have dollar
            values expressed as a floating-point number, (e.g. "299.99"), which has an <xref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-0/" scope="external">XML Schema Definition</xref> (XSD) data
            type of <ph>xs:double</ph>. Using this built-in type to define a range index,
            we can improve the efficiency of searches for <ph>price</ph> values. During indexing,
            eXist-db will apply this data type selection by attempting to cast all <ph>price</ph>
            values as double floating point numbers and add appropriate values to the index. Values
            that cannot be cast as double are ignored. This range index will be used by any
            expression that compares <ph>price</ph> to an <ph>xs:double</ph> value. For
            instance:</p>
        <pre>//item[price &gt; 100.0]</pre>

        <p>For non-string data types, the range index provides the query engine with a more
            efficient method of data conversion. Instead of retrieving the value of each selected
            element and casting it as a <ph>xs:double</ph> type, the engine can evaluate
            the expression by using the range index as a form of lookup index. Without an index,
            eXist-db has to do a full scan over all price <ph>price</ph> elements, retrieve the
            string values of their text node and cast them to a double number. This is a
            time-consuming process which also scales very badly with growing data sets. With a
            proper index, eXist-db needs just a single index lookup to evaluate <ph>price =
            100.0</ph>. The range expression <ph>price &gt; 100.0</ph> is processed
            with an index scan starting at 100. </p>
        <p>For string data, the index will also be used by the standard functions
            <ph>fn:contains()</ph>, <ph>fn:starts-with()</ph>,
            <ph>fn:ends-with()</ph> and <ph>fn:matches()</ph>.</p>
        <p>To illustrate this functionality, let's return to the previous example. If you define
            a range index of type <ph>xs:string</ph> for element <ph>name</ph>, a query
            on this element to select tall bookcases using <ph>fn:matches()</ph> will be
            supported by the following index:</p>
        <pre>//item[fn:matches(name, '[Tt]all\s[Bb]')]</pre>
        <p>Note that <ph>fn:matches</ph> will by default try to match the regular
            expression <i>anywhere</i> in the string. We can thus speed up the query
            dramatically by using "^" to restrict the match to the start of the string: </p>
        <pre>//item[fn:matches(name, '^[Tt]all\s[Bb]')]</pre>

        <note type="note">
                <p>If you really need to search for an exact substring in a longer text sequence, it
                is often better to use the NGram index instead of the range index, i.e. use
                <ph>ngram:contains()</ph> instead of <ph>fn:contains()</ph>.
                Unfortunately, there's no equivalent NGram function for
                <ph>fn:matches()</ph>.</p>
            </note>

        <p>In general, three conditions must be met in order to optimize a search using a range
            index:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p> <i>The range index must be defined on all items in the input
                    sequence.</i> </p>
                <p>For example, suppose you have two collections in the database: C1 and C2. If
                    you have a range index defined for collection C1, but your query happens to
                    operate on both C1 and C2, then the range index would <i>not</i>
                    be used. The query optimizer selects an optimization strategy based on the
                    entire input sequence of the query. Since, in this example, since only nodes in
                    C1 have a range index, no range index optimization would be applied.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i>The index data type (first argument type) must match the test data
                    type (second argument type).</i> </p>
                <p>In other words, with range indexes, there is no promotion of data types (i.e.
                    no data type precedes or replaces another data type). For example, if you
                    defined an index of type <ph>xs:double</ph> on <ph>price</ph>, a
                    query that compares this element's value with a string literal would not use a
                    range index, for instance:</p>
                <pre>//item[price = '1000.0']</pre>
                <p>In order to apply the range index, you would need to cast the value as a type
                    <ph>xs:double</ph>, i.e.:</p>
                <pre>//item[price = xs:double($price)] (where $price is any test value)</pre>
                <p>Similarly, when we compare <ph>xs:double</ph> values with
                    <ph>xs:integer</ph> values, as in, for instance:</p>
                <pre>//item[price = 1000]</pre>
                <p>the range index would again not be used since the <ph>price</ph> data type
                    differs from the test value type, although this conflict might not seem as
                    obvious as it is with string values.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i>The right-hand argument has no dependencies on the current context
                    item.</i> </p>
                <p>That is, the test or conditional value must not depend on the value against
                    which it is being tested. For example, range indexes will not be applied given
                    the following expression:</p>
                <pre>//item[price = self]</pre>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>Concerning range indexes on strings there's another restriction to be considered: up
            to version 1.3, range indexes on strings can only be used with the default Unicode
            collation. Also, string indexes will always be case sensitive (while n-gram and full
            text indexes are not). It is not (yet) possible to define a string index on a different
            collation (e.g. for German or French) or to make it case-insensitive. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="range-idx">
            <title>Range index configuration</title>
        

        <p>Range index configuration is done in <ph>collection.xconf</ph> documents (see
            <xref href="indexing" scope="external">indexing</xref>):</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;!-- Range indexes --&gt;
&lt;create qname="title" type="xs:string"/&gt;
&lt;create qname="author" type="xs:string"/&gt;
&lt;create qname="year" type="xs:integer"/&gt;
&lt;!-- "old" context-dependant configuration using the path attribute: --&gt;
&lt;create path="//booktitle" type="xs:string"/&gt;</pre>
        <p>A range index is configured by adding a <ph>create</ph> element directly below the
            root <ph>index</ph> element. As explained above, the node to be indexed is either
            specified through a <ph>path</ph> or a <ph>qname</ph>
            attribute.</p>

        <note type="note">
                <p>Unlike the <xref href="newrangeindex" scope="external">new range index</xref>, the
                <ph>create</ph> elements of the old range index are <i>not</i>
                wrapped inside a <ph>range</ph> tag.</p>
            </note>

        <p>As range indexes are type specific, the <ph>type</ph> attribute is always
            required. The type should be one of the atomic XML schema types, currently including
            <ph>xs:string</ph>, <ph>xs:integer</ph> and its derived types
            <ph>xs:double</ph> and <ph>xs:float</ph>,
            <ph>xs:boolean</ph> and <ph>xs:dateTime</ph>. If the name of the
            type is unknown, the index configuration will be ignored and you will get a warning
            written into the logs.</p>
        <p>Please note that the index configuration will only apply to the node specified via the
            <ph>path</ph> or <ph>qname</ph> attribute, not to descendants of
            that node. Consider a mixed content element like:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;mixed&gt;
  &lt;s&gt;
    un
  &lt;/s&gt;
  &lt;s&gt;
    even
  &lt;/s&gt;
&lt;/mixed&gt;</pre>
        <p>If an index is defined on <ph>mixed</ph>, the key for the index is built from the
            concatenated text nodes of element <ph>mixed</ph> and all its descendants, so
            <ph>uneven</ph> in this case. The created index will only be used to evaluate
            queries on <ph>mixed</ph>, but not for queries on <ph>s</ph>. However, you can
            create an additional index on <ph>s</ph> without getting into conflict with the
            existing index on <ph>mixed</ph>.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="pathvsqname">
            <title>Configuration by path vs. configuration by qname</title>
        

        <p>It is important to note the difference between the <ph>path</ph> and
            <ph>qname</ph> attributes used in above examples. Both attributes are used to
            define the elements or attributes to which the index should apply. However, the
            <ph>path</ph> attribute creates <i>context-dependant</i>
            indexes, while the <ph>qname</ph> attribute does not. </p>
        <p>The <ph>path</ph> attribute takes a simple path expression: <ph>create path="//book/title" type="xs:string"/</ph>
            </p>
        <p>The <ph>path</ph> expression looks like XPath, but it's not. Index path syntax
            uses the following components to construct paths:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>Elements are specified by their <i>qname</i> </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Attributes are specified by <ph>@attributeName</ph>, so if the
                    attribute is called <ph>attrib1</ph>, one uses <ph>@attrib1</ph>
                    in the index specification.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Child nodes are selected using the forward-slash (<ph>/</ph>)</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>All descendant nodes in a tree are selected using the double forward-slash
                    (<ph>//</ph>)</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
        <p>The example above creates a range index of type string on all <ph>title</ph>
            elements which are children of <ph>book</ph> elements, which may occur at an arbitrary
            position in the document tree. All other <ph>title</ph> elements, e.g. those being
            children of <ph>section</ph> nodes, are not indexed. The path expression thus defines
            a <i>selective</i> index, which is also
            <i>context-dependant</i>: we always need look at the context of each
            <ph>title</ph> node before we can determine if this particular title is to be indexed
            or not.</p>
        <p>This kind of context-dependant index definition helps to keep the index small, but
            unfortunately it makes it hard for the query optimizer to properly rewrite the
            expression tree without missing some nodes. The optimizer needs to make an optimization
            decision at compile time, where the context of an expression is unknown or at least not
            exactly known (read the <xref href="http://atomic.exist-db.org/blogs/eXist/NewIndexing" scope="external">blog article</xref> to
            get the whole picture). This means that some of the optimization techniques can not be
            applied to context-dependant indexes!</p>
        <p>We therefore had to introduce an alternative configuration method which is not
            context-dependant. To keep things simple, we decided to define the index on the
            <i>qname</i> of the element or attribute alone and to ignore the context
            altogether: <ph>create qname="title" type="xs:string"/</ph>
            </p>
        <p>This results in an index being created on every <ph>title</ph> element found in the
            document node tree. Section titles will be indexed as well as chapter or book titles. </p>
        <p>Indexes on attributes are defined as above by prepending "@" to the attribute's
            name: <ph>create qname="@type" type="xs:string"/</ph>
            </p>
        <p>This defines an index on all attributes named "type", but not on elements with the
            same name.</p>
        <p>Defining indexes on qnames may result in a considerably larger index, but it allows
            the query engine to apply all available optimization techniques, which can improve query
            times by an order of magnitude. As always, there's a trade-off here between performance
            and storage space. In many cases, the performance win can be dramatic enough to justify
            the increase in index size.</p>
        <note type="notice">
                <p>To be on the safe side, and to benefit from current and future improvements in the
                query engine, you should prefer <ph>qname</ph> over
                <ph>path</ph>, unless you really need to exclude certain nodes from
                indexing.</p>
            </note>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>