<topic id="newrangeindex">
    <title>Range Index</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="4Q20"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="indexing"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db includes a super fast modularized range index based on
        Apache Lucene. This article describes eXist-db's range index.</p>
        <section id="newrangeidx">
            <title>Overview</title>
        

        <p>Range indexes are extremely important in eXist-db. Without a proper index, evaluating
            a general comparison in an XPath filter expression (like <ph>//foo[baz =
            "xyz"]</ph>) requires eXist to do a full scan over the context node set, checking the
            value of every node against the argument. This is not only slow, it also limits
            concurrency due to necessary locking and consumes memory for loading each of the nodes.
            With a well-defined index, queries will usually complete in a few milliseconds instead
            of seconds. The index allows the optimizer to rewrite the expression and process the
            index lookup in advance, assuming that the number of <ph>baz</ph> elements with
            content <ph>xyz</ph> is much smaller than the total number of elements.</p>

    </section>
        <section id="conf-idx">
            <title>Index Configuration</title>
        


        <p>To use the new range index, wrap the range index definitions into a range
            element:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"&gt;
    &lt;!-- Range indexes --&gt;
    &lt;range&gt;
      &lt;create qname="mods:namePart" type="xs:string" case="no"/&gt;
      &lt;create qname="mods:dateIssued" type="xs:string"/&gt;
      &lt;create qname="@ID" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;/range&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>

        <p>Store this definition and do a re-index. Index files are created in the
            <ph>$EXIST_HOME/data/range directory</ph> (or wherever you configured your
            data directory to be). </p>
        <p>The indexes will be used automatically for general or value comparisons, as well as
            string functions like <ph>fn:contains</ph>, <ph>fn:starts-with</ph>,
            <ph>fn:ends-with</ph>. </p>
        <note type="note">
                <p>
                    <ph>fn:matches</ph> is currently not supported due to limitations in Lucene's
                regular expression handling. Alternatives include the new <ph>range:matches</ph>
                function (which <i>is</i> supported with the new range index, although subject to
                <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/core/org/apache/lucene/util/automaton/RegExp.html" scope="external">Lucene 
                    limitations</xref>) and the <xref href="oldrangeindex" scope="external">old range index</xref> (which does not use Lucene).</p>
            </note>
        <p>Above configuration applies to documents using MODS, a standard for bibliographical
            metadata. The following XPath expressions use the created indexes: </p>

        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare namespace mods="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3";
//mods:mods[mods:name/mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"],
//mods:mods[mods:originInfo/mods:dateIssued = "1978"],
//mods:mods[mods:name/mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"][mods:originInfo/mods:dateIssued = "1978"]</pre>
    </section>
        <section id="conf-feature">
            <title>Configuration Features</title>
        
        <p>Some notes on how to configuration the index.</p>
        

        <section id="case-sensitive">
                <title>Case sensitive index</title>
            

            <p> Add <ph>case="no"</ph> to create a case insensitive index on a string. </p>
            <p>With a case insensitive index on <ph>mods:namePart</ph> a match will also be
                found if you query for "dennis ritchie" instead of "Dennis Ritchie". </p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="collation">
                <title>Collations</title>
            

            <p> A collation changes how strings are compared. For example, you can change the
                strength property of the collation to ignore diacritics, accents or case. So to
                compare strings ignoring accents or case, you can define your index as follows: </p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;create qname="mods:namePart" 
        type="xs:string" 
        collation="?lang=en-US&amp;amp;strength=primary"/&gt;</pre>
            <p> Please refer to the <xref href="http://userguide.icu-project.org/collation/concepts" scope="external">ICU
                documentation</xref> (which is used by eXist) for more information on collations,
                strength, etc. </p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="combined-idx">
                <title>Combined indexes</title>
            

            <p> If you know you will often use a certain combination of filters, you can combine
                the corresponding indexes into one to further reduce query times. For example, the
                <ph>mods:name</ph> element has an attribute type which qualifies the name as being
                "personal", "corporate" or another predefined value. </p>
            <p>Assume you want to speed up a query like this:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">//mods:name[@type = "personal"][mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"]</pre>
            <p>To do this you could create a combined index on <ph>mods:name</ph> as
                follows:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;range&gt;
  &lt;create qname="mods:name"&gt;
    &lt;field name="name-type" match="@type" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="name-part" match="mods:namePart" type="xs:string"/&gt;
  &lt;/create&gt;
&lt;/range&gt;</pre>

            <p>This index will be used whenever the context of the filter expression is a
                <ph>mods:name</ph>. It filters on either or both: <ph>@type</ph> and
                <ph>mods:namePart</ph>. Advantage: only one index lookup is required to evaluate
                such an expression, resulting in a huge performance boost, in particular if the
                combination of filters does only match a few names out of a large set!</p>
            <p>Note that all 3 attributes of the field element are required. The
                <ph>name</ph> you give to the field can be arbitrary, but it should be unique
                within the index configuration document. The <ph>match</ph> attribute specifies
                the nodes to include in the field. It should be a simple path relative to the
                context element. </p>
            <p> You can skip the match attribute if you want to index the content of the context
                node itself. In this case, an additional attribute: <ph>nested="yes|no"</ph> can
                be added to tell the indexer to skip the content of nested nodes to only index
                direct text children of the context node.</p>
            <p> The index is also used if you only query one of the defined fields, for instance: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">//mods:mods[mods:name[mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"]]</pre>
            <p> It is important that the filter expression matches the index definition though,
                so the following will <i>not</i> be sped up by the index: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">//mods:mods[mods:name/mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"]</pre>
            <p>This is because the context of the filter expression here is <ph>mods:mods</ph>,
                not <ph>mods:name</ph>. </p>
            <p>You can create as many combined indexes as you like, even if some of them refer to
                elements which are nested inside other elements having a different index. For
                example, to index a complete MODS record, we could create one nested index on the
                root element: <ph>mods:mods</ph>, and include all attributes or simple descendant
                elements we may want to query at the same time. <ph>mods:name</ph>, even though a
                child of <ph>mods:mods</ph>, is a complex element, so we want it to have a
                separate index as shown above. We therefore define both indexes: </p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;range&gt;
  &lt;create qname="mods:name"&gt;
    &lt;field name="name-type" match="@type" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="name-part" match="mods:namePart" type="xs:string"/&gt;
  &lt;/create&gt;
  &lt;create qname="mods:mods"&gt;
    &lt;field name="mods-dateIssued" match="mods:originInfo/mods:dateIssued" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="mods-id" match="@ID" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="mods-authority" match="@authority" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="mods-lang" match="@lang" type="xs:string"/&gt;
  &lt;/create&gt;
&lt;/range&gt;</pre>
            <p> This allows more complex queries to be optimized, for instance: </p>

            <pre outputclass="xquery">//mods:mods[mods:name[@type = "personal"][mods:namePart = "Dennis Ritchie"]] 
           [mods:originInfo/mods:dateIssued = "1979"]</pre>
            <p>In this case, the <ph>mods:dateIssued</ph> lookup will be done first, which
                presumably returns more hits than the name lookup. So, for maximum performance it
                may still be faster to split the expression into two parts and do the name check
                first.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="conditional">
                <title>Conditional combined indexes</title>
            

            <p>For combined indexes, you can specify conditions to restrict the values being
                indexed to those contained in elements that have an attribute meeting certain
                criteria: </p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;range&gt;
  &lt;create qname="tei:term"&gt;
    &lt;condition attribute="type" value="main"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="mainTerm" type="xs:string"/&gt;
  &lt;/create&gt;
&lt;/range&gt;</pre>
            <p>This will only index the value of the <ph>tei:term</ph> element if it has an
                attribute named <ph>type</ph> with the value <ph>main</ph>. Multiple
                conditions can be specified in an index definition, in which case all conditions
                need to match in order for the value to be indexed.</p>
            <p>In order to take advantage of query optimization for conditionally indexed fields,
                queries should be formulated like this:</p>
            <pre>//tei:term[@type = "main"][. = "xyz"]</pre>
            <p>This gets rewritten to a call to: </p>
            <pre>range:field(("mainTerm"), "eq", "xyz")</pre>
            <p>By default, condition matching is string-based and case-sensitive. </p>
            <p>The following optional attributes can be specified on a <ph>condition</ph>: </p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                        <ph>operator="eq|ne|lt|gt|le|ge|starts-with|ends-with|contains|matches"</ph>
                    </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Specifies the operator for the comparison. <ph>matches</ph>
                            supports Java regular expressions.</p>
                        <p>Default is <ph>eq</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                        <ph>case="yes|no"</ph>
                    </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Turns case sensitivity on or off for string comparisons. </p>
                        <p>Default is <ph>yes</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                        <ph>numeric="yes|no"</ph>
                    </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Turns numeric comparison on or off for equality and ordinal
                            comparisons (<ph>eq, ne, lt, gt, le, ge</ph>). When enabled, 01.0
                            will equal 1 and 2 will be less than 110 for example. The rewriter will
                            respect the type of the value (string, numeric) when matching a
                            condition to a predicate. </p>
                        <p>Default is <ph>off</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="idx-functions">
            <title>Using Index Functions</title>
        

        <p>Internally the query optimizer will rewrite range lookup expressions into optimized
            function calls into the <ph>range</ph> module (namespace
            <ph>http://exist-db.org/xquery/range</ph>). This happens transparently and you'll
            never see the function calls. However, for debugging and testing it is sometimes useful
            to use the corresponding functions directly. There are two sets of functions: one for
            simple range index lookups, and one for indexes on fields.</p>
        <p>For example, assume the following index configuration:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;range&gt;
  &lt;create qname="SPEAKER" type="xs:string"/&gt;
  &lt;create qname="SPEECH"&gt;
    &lt;field name="stagedir" type="xs:string" match="//STAGEDIR"/&gt;
    &lt;field name="line" type="xs:string" match="LINE" case="no"/&gt;
  &lt;/create&gt;
&lt;/range&gt;</pre>
        <p>And the following query:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//SPEECH[SPEAKER="HAMLET"]</pre>
        <p>This translates into:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//SPEECH[range:eq(SPEAKER, "HAMLET")]</pre>

        <p>If the index is defined on an element with fields, the entire sub-expression, the
            context path and all its filters, is rewritten into a single function call. For
            example:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">collection("/db/apps/demo/data")//SPEECH[.//STAGEDIR = "Aside"]</pre>
        <p>This is replaced with:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">collection("/db/apps/demo/data")/range:field-eq("stagedir", "Aside")</pre>
        <p>Because the index root is defined on <ph>SPEECH</ph>, the function will always
            return <ph>SPEECH</ph> elements.</p>

        <p>If multiple filters are used and each of them has a corresponding field definition,
            they are combined into one call:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">collection("/db/apps/demo/data")/range:field-eq(("stagedir", "line"), "Aside", "what do you read, my lord?")</pre>
        <p>Note that while the field names are specified in a sequence, we add one parameter for
            every value to look up. This way it is possible to specify more than one value for each
            parameter by passing in a sequence.</p>
        <p>Because different operators might be used inside the filters, the query engine will
            actually rewrite the expression to the following:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">collection("/db/apps/demo/data")/range:field(("stagedir", "line"), ("eq", "eq"), "Aside", "what do you read, my lord?")</pre>
        <p>This is not easy to read, but efficient. Users will normally not see this function
            call. However, it sometimes helps to know what the optimizer is supposed to do and try
            it out explicitly.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="comparison-range-index">
            <title>Comparison with the old range index</title>
        

        <p>eXist also has an older version of the range index on board (see <xref href="oldrangeindex" scope="external">old range index</xref>). Compared to this newer version it
            has three main issues:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p> Index entries were organized by collection, resulting in an unfortunate
                    dependency between collection size and update speed. In simple words: updating
                    or removing documents became slower as the collection grew. For a long time, the
                    general recommendation was to split large document sets into multiple, smaller
                    sub-collections if update speed was an issue. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> Queries on very frequent search strings were quite inefficient: for example,
                    a query </p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">//term[@type ="main"][. = "xyz"]</pre>
                <p> could be quite slow despite an index being defined if
                    <ph>@type="main"</ph> occurred very often. Unfortunately this is a common
                    use of attributes and to make it quick, you had to reformulate the query, e.g.
                    by moving the non-selective step to the back: </p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">//term[. = "xyz"][@type = "main"]</pre>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Range indexes were baked into the core of eXist-db, making maintenance and bug
                    fixing difficult. </p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>The rewritten range index addresses both issues. First, indexes are now organized by
            document/node, so collection size does no longer matter when updating an index entry.
            Concerning storage, the index is entirely based on Apache Lucene instead of the B+-tree
            which was previously used. Most range indexes tend to be strings, so why not leave the
            indexing to a technology like Lucene, which is known to scale well and does a highly
            efficient job on string processing? Since version 4, Lucene has added support for
            storing numeric data types and binary data into the index, so it seemed to be a perfect
            match for our requirements. Lucene is integrated into eXist on a rather low level with
            direct access to the indexes. </p>
        <p>To address the second issue, it is now possible to combine several fields to index
            into one index definition: </p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//term[@type = "main"] [. = "xyz"]</pre>
        <p>This can now be evaluated with a single index lookup. </p>
        <p>Finally, the new range index is implemented as a pluggable module: a separate
            component which is not required for the core of eXist-db to work properly. For eXist,
            the index is a black box: it does not need to know what the index does. If the index is
            there, it will automatically plug itself into the indexing pipeline as well as the query
            engine. If it is not, eXist will fall back to default (brute force) query
            processing.</p>
        <p>The old range index is still supported to allow existing applications to run
            unchanged.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>