<topic id="devguide_manifesto">
    <title>eXist-db Developer Manifesto</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q18"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="exist"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This document lays out guidelines for developers that are either committing directly to
        the eXist-db code base via the projects GitHub repository or developing externally, for
        later incorporation into eXist-db.</p>
        <section id="communication">
            <title>Communication</title>
        

        <p>Communication between developers and within Open Source projects can be a hard thing
            to achieve effectively, but to ensure the success of the project and contributions, we
            must all strive to improve on communicating our intentions.</p>
        <p>Public and open discussion of all new features and changes to existing features
            <i>must</i> always be undertaken. eXist-db is a community project and the
            community must be invited to provide input and feedback on development. Development
            discussions take place through the <xref href="http://sourceforge.net/mail/?group_id=17691" scope="external">eXist-db Development mailing
            list</xref>.</p>
        <p>If conflicts of interest occur during discussion, they must be resolved before code
            changes are made. If conflicts cannot be resolved by the community, usually one of the
            core maintainers acts as a moderator. Core maintainers are contributors who feel
            responsible for the project as a whole and have shown it in the past their commitment
            and support. Right now this includes: Pierrick Brihaye, Wolfgang Meier, Leif-Jöran
            Olsson, Adam Retter and Dannes Wessels. We name those people, so you know who to talk
            to, but the list is in no way exclusive and may change over time.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="maintainability">
            <title>Maintainability</title>
        

        <p>All code accepted must be maintainable. Otherwise there is the possibility that it
            will grow stale and, without maintainers, will be removed from the code base.</p>
        <p>To ensure a happy future for the code base, each contributor has a responsibility to
            ensure:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>New code and bug-fixes <i>must</i> be accompanied by
                    JUnit/XQuery/XSpec test cases. This helps us understand intention and avoid
                    regressions.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Code must be appropriately commented (including javadoc/xqdoc), so the
                    intention is understood. Industry standard code formatting rules must be
                    followed. This helps us read and understand contributions.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Code must be tagged with the developers name and email address. This helps us
                    contact contributors/maintainers should issues arrive.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Consider the maintainability of new features: will you maintain and support
                    them over years? If not, who will? How do you communicate what is
                    required?</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
    </section>
        <section id="developing">
            <title>Developing</title>
        

        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>Follow Industry Standard coding conventions.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>eXist-db is now developed atop Sun Java 8, so make use of Java 8 features for
                    cleaner, safer and more efficient code.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>New Features <i>must</i> be generic and applicable to an
                    audience of more than one or two. Consider whether the eXist-db community would
                    see this as a valuable feature (you should have already discussed this via the
                    eXist-db Development mailing list). If a feature is just for you and/or your
                    customer, it may have no place in eXist-db's main code base.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Major new features or risky changes must be developed in their own branch.
                    Once tested (this must include user testing) they may then be integrated back
                    into the main code base.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Follow a RISC like approach to developing new functions. It is better to have
                    a single function that is flexible than multiple function signatures for the
                    same function. Likewise, do not replace two functions by offering one new super
                    function. Functions should act like simple building blocks that can be combined
                    together.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>The use of Static Analysis tools is highly recommended. These tools reduce
                    risk, and are valuable even to the most highly skilled developers. Such tools
                    include <xref href="http://checkstyle.sourceforge.net" scope="external">Checkstyle</xref>,
                    <xref href="http://findbugs.sourceforge.net" scope="external">FindBugs</xref> and <xref href="http://pmd.sourceforge.net/" scope="external">PMD</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
    </section>
        <section id="before">
            <title>Before Committing</title>
        

        <ul>
                <li>
                <p> <i>TEST, TEST and TEST again!</i> See last section how to do
                    this.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Execute the JUnit test suite to ensure that there are no regressions. If there
                    are any regressions, do not commit!</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Execute the XQTS test suite to ensure that there are no regressions. If there
                    are any regressions, do not commit!</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>If you are working in an area of performance, there is a Benchmark test suite
                    that you should run.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>When effecting major changes, make sure all the demo applications which ship
                    with eXist-db are still working as expected. Testing of the main user
                    interfaces, including Java WebStart client and WebDAV, helps to avoid surprises
                    at release time.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Documentation, whilst often overlooked, is critical in getting users to accept
                    and test any new feature. If you add features without documentation they are
                    worthless to the community.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Have a look at the <xref href="devguide_codereview" scope="external">Code Review
                    Guide</xref> and take its recommendations at heart!</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Atomicity! Please consider how you group commits together. A feature should be
                    contributed as an atomic commit, this enables co-developers to easily follow and
                    test the feature. If you need to clean up existing code during development,
                    please commit this labelled 'cleaning up'. This makes your final commit much
                    more concise.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>If possible, without breaking existing functionality, it can be useful to
                    break very large commits into a few smaller atomic ones, spanning a couple of
                    days. This allows other users to test and help identify any parts of your code
                    which might introduce issues.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Commit tagging helps us to generate lists of what has changed between
                    releases. Please prefix your commit messages with an appropriate tag:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>[bugfix]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[lib-change]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[feature]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[ignore]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[format-change]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[documentation]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[documentation-fix]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[performance]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[testsuite]</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>[building]</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
                <p>The change log scripts will ignore any messages which do not start with one of
                    the tags above or whose tag is [ignore].</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
    </section>
        <section id="finally">
            <title>Finally</title>
        

        <p>Open Source projects are almost but quite not a democracy. Breaking, unknown and/or
            untested commits cause a lot of pain and lost hours to your fellow developers.</p>
        <p>Whilst we of course wish to encourage and nurture contributions to the project, these
            have to happen in a manner everyone involved in the project can cope with. However, as
            an absolute last measure, if developers frequently fail to adhere to the Manifesto then
            Commit access to the eXist-db repository shall be revoked by the core developers.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="test-all">
            <title>How to enable all and test</title>
        

        <p>It is essential that none of the existing code breaks because of your commit. Here is
            how to be sure all code can be built and tested:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Edit <ph>conf.xml</ph> (or actually the original file
                    <ph>conf.xml.tmpl</ph>)</p>
                <ol>
                        <li>
                        <p>Uncomment all (really, all) built-in modules under Xpath
                            <ph>/exist/xquery/builtin-modules</ph> </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Activate the spatial index by uncommenting the index-module
                            spatial-index under Xpath <ph>/exist/indexer/modules</ph> (the
                            corresponding function module is uncommented in the first step.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ol>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Edit <ph>local.build.properties</ph> and switch on all
                    modules</p>
                <ol>
                        <li>
                        <p>The Oracle module can be left switched off, the required jar is a bit
                            difficult to download</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Switch all modules on with the command </p>
                        <pre>cat build.properties | sed 's/false/true/g' &gt; local.build.properties</pre>
                    </li>
                    </ol>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>