<topic id="lucene">
    <title>Full Text Index</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="3Q21"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="indexing"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article provides information on configuring and using eXist-db's full text
        index.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>The full text index module is based on <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org" scope="external">Apache Lucene</xref>. </p>
        <p>The full-text index module is tightly integrated with eXist-db's <i>modularized
            indexing architecture</i>: the index behaves like a plug-in which adds itself to
            the database's index pipelines. Once configured, the index will be notified of relevant
            events, like adding/removing a document, removing a collection or updating single nodes.
            No manual re-indexing is required to keep the index up-to-date. </p>
        <p>The full-text index module also implements common interfaces which are shared with
            other indexes, for instance for highlighting matches (see <xref href="kwic" scope="external">KWIC</xref>). It is easy to switch between the Lucene index and, for instance, the
            ngram index without rewriting much XQuery code.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="config">
            <title>Configuring the Index</title>
        
        <p>The index has a single configuration parameter on the <ph>modules</ph>
            <ph>/</ph> <ph>module</ph> element called <ph>buffer</ph>. It defines the
            amount of memory (in megabytes) Lucene will use for buffering index entries before they
            are written to disk. See the <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/core/org/apache/lucene/index/IndexWriterConfig.html#setRAMBufferSizeMB(double)" scope="external">Lucene Javadocs</xref>.</p>

        <p>Like other indexes, you create a Lucene index by configuring it in a
            <ph>collection.xconf</ph> document as explained in <xref href="indexing#idxconf" scope="external">documentation</xref>. For example:</p>

        <section>
                <title>collection.xconf (for version 3.0 and above).</title>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:wiki="http://exist-db.org/xquery/wiki" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"&gt;
    &lt;!-- Lucene index is configured below --&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"/&gt;
      &lt;analyzer id="ws" class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.core.WhitespaceAnalyzer"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="TITLE" analyzer="ws"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="p"&gt;
        &lt;inline qname="em"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
      &lt;text match="//foo/*"/&gt;
      &lt;!-- "inline" and "ignore" can be specified globally or per-index as shown above --&gt;
      &lt;inline qname="b"/&gt;
      &lt;ignore qname="note"/&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            </section>

        <p>You can define a Lucene index on a single element or attribute
            (<ph>qname="..."</ph>) or a node path with wildcards (<ph>match="..."</ph>, see
            below). </p>

        <p>It is important make sure to <i>choose the right context</i> for an
            index, which has to be the same as in your query. To better understand this, let's have
            a look at how the index creation is handled by eXist-db and Lucene. For example:
            <ph>text qname="SPEECH"</ph> </p>
        <p>This creates an index on <ph>SPEECH</ph> only. What is passed to Lucene is the
            string value of <ph>SPEECH</ph>, which also includes the text of all its descendant
            text nodes (<i>except</i> those filtered out by an optional
            <ph>ignore</ph>). </p>
        <p>Consider the fragment:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;SPEECH&gt;
  &lt;SPEAKER&gt;
    Second Witch
  &lt;/SPEAKER&gt;
  &lt;LINE&gt;
    Fillet of a fenny snake,
  &lt;/LINE&gt;
  &lt;LINE&gt;
    In the cauldron boil and bake;
  &lt;/LINE&gt;
&lt;/SPEECH&gt;</pre>
        <p>If you have an index on <ph>SPEECH</ph>, Lucene will use the text <ph>"Second
            Witch Fillet of a fenny snake, In the cauldron boil and bake;"</ph> and index it.
            eXist-db internally links this Lucene document to the <ph>SPEECH</ph> node, but Lucene
            itself has no knowledge of that (it doesn't know anything about XML nodes).</p>

        <p>Given this, take the following query:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//SPEECH[ft:query(., 'cauldron')]</pre>
        <p>This searches the index and finds the text, which eXist-db can trace back to the
            <ph>SPEECH</ph> node in the XML document. </p>
        <p>However, it is required that you use the same context (<ph>SPEECH</ph>) for creating
            <i>and</i> querying the index. For instance:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//SPEECH[ft:query(LINE, 'cauldron')]</pre>
        <p>This will <i>not return anything</i>, even though <ph>LINE</ph> is a
            child of <ph>SPEECH</ph> and <ph>cauldron</ph> was indexed. This particular
            <ph>cauldron</ph> is linked to its ancestor <ph>SPEECH</ph> , not its parent
            <ph>LINE</ph>.</p>

        <p>However, you are free to give the user both options, i.e. use <ph>SPEECH</ph> and
            <ph>LINE</ph> as context at the same time. For this define a second index on
            <ph>LINE</ph>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text qname="SPEECH"/&gt;
&lt;text qname="LINE"/&gt;</pre>

        <p>Let's use a different example to illustrate this. Assume you have a document with
            encoded place names:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;p&gt;
  He loves
  &lt;placeName&gt;
    Paris
  &lt;/placeName&gt;
  .
&lt;/p&gt;</pre>
        <p>For a general query you probably want to search through all paragraphs. However, you
            may also want to provide an advanced search option, which allows the user to restrict
            his/her queries to place names. To make this possible, simply define an index on
            <ph>placeName</ph> <i>as well</i>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;lucene&gt;
  &lt;text qname="p"/&gt;
  &lt;text qname="placeName"/&gt;
&lt;/lucene&gt;</pre>
        <p>Based on this setup, you'll be able to query for the word 'Paris' anywhere in a
            paragraph:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//p[ft:query(., 'paris')]</pre>
        <p>And also on 'Paris' occurring within a <ph>placeName</ph>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//p[ft:query(placeName, 'paris')]</pre>

        

        <section id="match">
                <title>Using <ph>match="..."</ph> </title>
            

            <p>In addition to defining an index on a given qualified name, you can also specify a
                "path" with wildcards. <i>This feature might be subject to change</i>,
                so please be careful when using it.</p>
            <p>Assume you want to define an index on all the possible elements below
                <ph>SPEECH</ph>. You can do this by creating one index for every element:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text qname="LINE"/&gt;
&lt;text qname="SPEAKER"/&gt;</pre>
            <p>As a shortcut, you can use a <ph>match</ph> attribute with a
                wildcard:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text match="//SPEECH/*"/&gt;</pre>
            <p>This will create a separate index on each child element of SPEECH it encounters.
                Please note that the argument to match is a simple path pattern, not a full XPath
                expression. For the time being, it only allows:</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p> <ph>/</ph> and <ph>//</ph> to denote child or descendant
                        steps,</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p> <ph>*</ph> wildcard selector to match an arbitrary element,</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>matching a single attribute's value, e.g. <ph>foo[@bar = 'xyz']</ph>
                    </p>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>As explained above, you have to figure out which parts of your document will
                likely be interesting as context for a full text query. The full text index works
                best if the context isn't too narrow. For example, if you have a document structure
                with section <ph>div</ph>s, headings and paragraphs, you would probably want to
                create an index on the <ph>div</ph>s and maybe on the headings, so the user can
                differentiate between the two.</p>
            <p> In some cases, you could decide to put the index on the paragraph level. Then you
                don't need the index on the section, since you can always get from the paragraph
                back to the section.</p>
            <p>If you query a larger context, you can use the <xref href="kwic" scope="external">KWIC</xref>
                module to show the user text <i>surrounding</i> each match. Or you can
                ask eXist-db to <xref href="kwic#highlight" scope="external">highlight each match</xref> with
                an <ph>exist:match</ph> tag, which you can later use to locate the matches within
                the text.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="whitespace">
                <title>Whitespace Treatment and Ignored Content</title>
            
            <p>We'll go into more detail with two common requirements when using full-text indexes.</p>
            <section id="inline">
                    <title>Inlined elements</title>
                

                <p>By default, eXist-db's indexer assumes that element boundaries break on a word
                    or token. For example, if you have an element:</p>

                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;size&gt;
  &lt;width&gt;
    12
  &lt;/width&gt;
  &lt;height&gt;
    8
  &lt;/height&gt;
&lt;/size&gt;</pre>
                <p>You want <ph>12</ph> and <ph>8</ph> to be indexed as separate tokens,
                    even though there's no whitespace between the elements. eXist-db will pass the
                    content of the two elements to Lucene as separate strings and Lucene will see
                    two tokens (instead of just <ph>128</ph>).</p>
                <p>However, you usually <i>don't</i> want this behaviour for mixed
                    content nodes. For example:</p>

                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;p&gt;
  This is
  &lt;b&gt;
    un
  &lt;/b&gt;
  clear.
&lt;/p&gt;</pre>
                <p>In this case, you want <ph>unclear</ph> to be indexed as a single word.
                    This can be done by telling eXist-db which nodes are inline nodes. The example
                    configuration above uses:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;inline qname="b"/&gt;</pre>
                <p>The <ph>inline</ph> option can both be specified globally or
                    per-index:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text qname="p"&gt;
  &lt;inline qname="em"/&gt;
&lt;/text&gt;</pre>
            </section>

            <section id="ignore">
                    <title>Ignored elements</title>
                

                <p>It is sometimes necessary to skip the content of an inline element. Notes are
                    a good example:</p>

                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;p&gt;
  This is a paragraph
  &lt;note&gt;
    containing an inline note
  &lt;/note&gt;
  .
&lt;/p&gt;</pre>
                <p>Use an <ph>ignore</ph> element in the collection configuration to have
                    eXist-db ignore the note:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;ignore qname="note"/&gt;</pre>
                <p>Basically, <ph>ignore</ph> simply allows you to hide a chunk of text before
                    Lucene sees it.</p>
                <p>Like the <ph>inline</ph> tag, <ph>ignore</ph> may appear both globally or
                    within a single index definition.</p>
                <p>The <ph>ignore</ph> only applies to descendants of an indexed element. You
                    can still create another index on the ignored element itself. For example, you
                    can have index definitions for <ph>p</ph> <i>and</i>
                    <ph>note</ph>:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;lucene&gt;
  &lt;text qname="p"/&gt;
  &lt;text qname="note"/&gt;
  &lt;ignore qname="note"/&gt;
&lt;/lucene&gt;</pre>

                <p>If <ph>note</ph> appears within <ph>p</ph>, it will not be added to the
                    index on <ph>p</ph>, only to the index on <ph>note</ph>. For example:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">//p[ft:query(., "note")]</pre>
                <p>This may not return a hit if <ph>"note"</ph> occurs within a
                    <ph>note</ph>, while this finds a match:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">//p[ft:query(note, "note")]</pre>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="boost">
                <title>Boost</title>
            

            <p>A <i>boost</i> value can be assigned to an index to give it a higher
                score. The score for each match will be multiplied by the boost factor (default is:
                1.0). For example, you may want to rank matches in titles higher than other matches. </p>
            <p>Here's how to configure the documentation search indexes in eXist-db:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;lucene&gt;
  &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"/&gt;
  &lt;text qname="section"&gt;
    &lt;ignore qname="title"/&gt;
    &lt;ignore qname="programlisting"/&gt;
    &lt;ignore qname="screen"/&gt;
    &lt;ignore qname="synopsis"/&gt;
  &lt;/text&gt;
  &lt;text qname="para"/&gt;
  &lt;text qname="title" boost="2.0"/&gt;
  &lt;ignore qname="title"/&gt;
&lt;/lucene&gt;</pre>

            <p>The <ph>title</ph> index gets a boost of 2.0 to make sure that its matches get a
                higher score. Since the <ph>title</ph> element occurs within <ph>section</ph>,
                we add an ignore rule to the index definition on the section and create a separate
                index on title. We also ignore titles occurring inside paragraphs. Without this,
                title would be matched two times.</p>
            <p>Because the title is now indexed separately, we need to query it explicitly. For
                example, to search the section and the title at the same time, one could issue the
                following query:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">for $sect in /book//section[ft:query(., "ngram")] | /book//section[ft:query(title, "ngram")]
order by ft:score($sect) descending 
return $sect</pre>

            <section id="boost-attribute">
                    <title>Attribute boost</title>
                

                <p>Starting with eXist-db 3.0 a boost value can also be assigned to an index by
                    attribute. This can be used to weight your search results, even if you have flat
                    data structures with the same attribute value pairs in attributes throughout
                    your documents. Two flavours of dynamic weighting are available through the new
                    pairs <ph>match-sibling-attribute</ph>, <ph>has-sibling-attribute</ph> and
                    <ph>match-attribute</ph>, <ph>has-attribute</ph> child elements in the
                    full-text index configuration. </p>
                <p>If you have data in Lexical metadata framework (LMF) format you will recognize
                    these repeated structures of <ph>feat</ph> elements with <ph>att</ph> and
                    <ph>val</ph> attributes within <ph>LexicalEntry</ph> elements. For
                    instance <ph>feat att='writtenForm' val='LMF feature value'</ph>. The
                    attribute boosting allows you to weight the results based on the value of the
                    <ph>att</ph> attribute so that hits in definitions come before hits in
                    comments and examples. This behaviour is enabled by adding a child
                    <ph>has-sibling-attribute</ph> to a Lucene configuration <ph>text</ph> element.
                    An example index configuration for it looks like this:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text qname="@val"&gt;
  &lt;match-sibling-attribute boost="25" qname="att" value="writtenForm"/&gt;
&lt;/text&gt;</pre>
                <p>This means that the <ph>ft:score#1</ph> function will boost hits in
                    <ph>val</ph> attributes with a factor of 25 times for the
                    <ph>writtenForm</ph> value of the <ph>att</ph> attribute.</p>
                <p>In the same way <ph>match-attribute</ph> would be used for element qnames in the
                    <ph>text</ph> element.</p>
                <p>If you do not care about any value of the sibling attribute, use the
                    <ph>has-attribute</ph> index configuration variant. An example index
                    configuration with <ph>has-attribute</ph> looks like this:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;text qname="feat"&gt;
  &lt;has-attribute boost="0" qname="xml:lang"/&gt;
&lt;/text&gt;</pre>
                <p>This means that if your <ph>feat</ph> elements have an attribute
                    <ph>xml:lang</ph> it will score them nil and push them last of the pack, which
                    might be useful to demote hits in features in other languages than the main
                    entry language.</p>
                <p>In the same way <ph>has-sibling-attribute</ph> would be used for attributes in
                    the <ph>text</ph> element.</p>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="analyzer">
                <title>Analyzers</title>
            

            <p>One of the strengths of Lucene is that it allows the developer to determine nearly
                every aspect of text analysis. This is done through analyzer classes, which combine
                a tokenizer with a chain of filters to post-process the tokenized text. eXist-db's
                Lucene module already allows different analyzers to be used for different indexes.
                And starting from eXist version 5.3.0 - specifying a particular analyzer to be used
                for processing a particular query (see <ph>query-analyzer-id</ph> in
                <xref href="#parameters" scope="local">Additional parameters</xref>).
                </p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;lucene&gt;
  &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"/&gt;
  &lt;analyzer id="ws" class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.core.WhitespaceAnalyzer"/&gt;
  &lt;text match="//SPEECH//*"/&gt;
  &lt;text qname="TITLE" analyzer="ws"/&gt;
&lt;/lucene&gt;</pre>

            <p>In the example above, we define that Lucene's <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/analyzers-common/org/apache/lucene/analysis/standard/StandardAnalyzer.html" scope="external">StandardAnalyzer</xref> should be used by default (the <ph>analyzer</ph> element
                without <ph>id</ph> attribute). We provide an additional analyzer and
                assign it the id <ph>ws</ph>, by which the analyzer can be referenced in
                the actual index definitions and by queries specifying a particular analyzer that
                should be used to process them (see <ph>query-analyzer-id</ph> in
                <xref href="#parameters" scope="local">Additional parameters</xref>).</p>
            <p>The <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/analyzers-common/org/apache/lucene/analysis/core/WhitespaceAnalyzer.html" scope="external">whitespace analyzer</xref> is the most basic one. As the name implies, it tokenizes
                the text at white space characters, but treats all other characters - including
                punctuation - as part of the token. The tokens are not converted to lower case and
                there's no stopword filter applied.</p>
            <p>eXist-db provides a special analyzer for characters with diacritics based on the
                <ph>StandardAnalyzer</ph>. The
                <ph>NoDiacriticsStandardAnalyzer</ph> can be switched on and off by
                setting the <ph>diacritics</ph> attribute on the <ph>lucene</ph> element
                of your index configuration file.</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index&gt;
    &lt;!-- Lucene indexes --&gt;
    &lt;lucene diacritics="no"&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"/&gt;
      &lt;text match="//title[@xml:lang='Sa-Ltn']"/&gt;
      &lt;text match="/TEI/text"&gt;
        &lt;ignore qname="text"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            <p>Without diacritics <ph>ä</ph>, <ph>å</ph>, <ph>ā</ph>,
                etc will all be indexed as <ph>a</ph>. Alternatively, this analyzer can
                also be called by its full name. </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.exist.indexing.lucene.analyzers.NoDiacriticsStandardAnalyzer" id="nodiacritics"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="letter" analyzer="nodiacritics"&gt;
        &lt;field name="place" expression="place" analyzer="nodiacritics"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="from" expression="from" store="no"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="to" expression="to"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            <section id="conf">
                    <title>Configuring the Analyzer</title>
                

                <p>You can send configuration parameters to the instantiation of the Analyzer.
                    These parameters must match a <ph>Constructor</ph> signature on the
                    underlying Java class of the Analyzer, please review the Javadoc for the
                    Analyzer that you wish to configure.</p>
                <p>We currently support passing the following types:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.lang.String</ph> (default if no type is specified)</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.lang.String[]</ph> (since eXist-db 5.4.0)</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>char[]</ph> (since eXist-db 5.4.0)</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.io.FileReader</ph> or <ph>file</ph>
                        </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.lang.Boolean</ph> or <ph>boolean</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.lang.Integer</ph> or <ph>int</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>org.apache.lucene.analysis.util.CharArraySet</ph> or
                            <ph>set</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>java.lang.reflect.Field</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
                <p> The value <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/core/org/apache/lucene/util/Version.html#LUCENE_CURRENT" scope="external">Version#LUCENE_CURRENT</xref> is always added as first parameter for the
                    analyzer constructor (a fallback mechanism is present for older analyzers). The
                    previously valid values <ph>java.io.File</ph> and <ph>java.util.Set</ph>
                    can not be used since Lucene 4.</p>
                <p>For instance to add a stopword list, use one of the following
                    constructions:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;analyzer id="stdstops" class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"&gt;
  &lt;param name="stopwords" type="java.io.FileReader" value="/tmp/stop.txt"/&gt;
&lt;/analyzer&gt;</pre>

                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;analyzer id="stdstops" class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"&gt;
  &lt;param name="stopwords" type="org.apache.lucene.analysis.util.CharArraySet"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      the
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      this
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      and
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      that
    &lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/param&gt;
&lt;/analyzer&gt;</pre>
                
                <p>For instance to construct your custom analyzer you might use
                    something like:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;analyzer id="my-custom-analyzer" class="tld.org.CustomAnalyzer"&gt;
  &lt;param name="minimumTermLength" type="int" value="2"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="punctuationDictionary" type="char[]"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      '
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      -
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      ’
    &lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/param&gt;
&lt;/analyzer&gt;</pre>
                

                <note type="note">
                        <p>Using the Snowball analyzer requires you to add additional libraries to
                        <ph>lib/user</ph>.</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;analyzer id="sbstops" class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.snowball.SnowballAnalyzer"&gt;
  &lt;param name="name" value="English"/&gt;
  &lt;param name="stopwords" type="org.apache.lucene.analysis.util.CharArraySet"&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      the
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      this
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      and
    &lt;/value&gt;
    &lt;value&gt;
      that
    &lt;/value&gt;
  &lt;/param&gt;
&lt;/analyzer&gt;</pre>
                    </note>

            </section>
        </section>

        
        <section id="facets-and-fields">
                <title>Facets and Fields</title>
            
            <p>Starting with eXist 5.0, an index configuration may define additional facets and
                fields. Both can hold arbitrary content, which will be attached to the indexed
                parent node and can be used to further refine a query, sort results or display
                additional information to the user:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>facet</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>a facet defines a concept or information item by which the indexed
                            items can be grouped. Typical facets would be categories taken from some
                            pre-defined taxonomy, languages, dates, places or names occurring in a
                            text corpus. The goal is to enable users to "drill down" into a
                            potentially large result set by selecting from a list of facets
                            displayed to them. For example, if you shop for a laptop, you are often
                            presented with a list of facets with which you may restrict your result
                            by CPU type, memory or screen size etc. As you select facets, the result
                            set will become smaller and smaller.</p>
                        <p>Facets are always pre-defined at indexing time, so the drill down is
                            very fast. They are meant for refining other queries, the assumption
                            always is that the user selects one or more facets from a list of facet
                            values associated with the current query results.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>field</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>a field contains additional, searchable content attached to an indexed
                            parent node. In many cases fields will contain constructed content which
                            is not directly found in the indexed XML or requires costly computation.
                            For example, determining publication dates or author names for a set of
                            articles may require some pre-processing which may be too expensive at
                            query time. A field allows you to pre-compute those information items at
                            indexing time.</p>
                        <p>Fields can be queried in the same expression as the parent node,
                            resulting in fast response times. Their content can optionally be stored
                            to speed up display or sorting. Fields may also use a different analyzer
                            than the parent node, which allows e.g. multiple languages to be handled
                            separately.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
            <section id="facet-conf">
                    <title>Facet and Field Configuration</title>
                
                <p>Facets and fields are configured in a similar way. Both should appear nested
                    inside the parent index element they are attached to. Let's assume we have a
                    collection of articles written in docbook. Each article will have a top-level
                    <ph>info</ph> element describing the article. Each <ph>info</ph> element
                    contains a <ph>title</ph>, one or more <ph>author</ph>s and a list of
                    keywords in <ph>keywordset</ph>.</p>
                <p>Keywords are a perfect candidate for a facet, so let's start with it:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p>Every facet needs to have a <ph>dimension</ph> attribute, defining the
                    name of the facet dimension the items will be added to. The values associated
                    with this facet dimension are determined by the <ph>expression</ph>
                    attribute: it may contain an arbitrary XQuery expression rooted in the parent
                    node being indexed. In the example the parent will be a <ph>db:article</ph>
                    element, so the context item for the expression is set to this element.</p>
                <p>The expression is evaluated and for each result item, a facet value is added
                    to the dimension using the string value of the item. Therefore if the expression
                    returns multiple items, a facet for that dimension will also hold multiple
                    values. If the expression returns the empty sequence for the current parent
                    node, the corresponding facet will be empty as well.</p>
                <p>A facet can also be defined to be hierarchical. A typical example would be a
                    date, which consists of a year, month and day component. By indexing the single
                    components as separate parts of a hierarchical facet, we enable the user to
                    drill down by year first, then by month and finally by day. Let's assume each of
                    our docbook articles has a <ph>pubdate</ph> containing a date in
                    <ph>xs:date</ph> format:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="date" expression="tokenize(db:info/db:pubdate, '-')" hierarchical="yes"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p>Hierarchical facets may also hold multiple values, for example if we would
                    like to associate our documents with a subject classification on various levels
                    of granularity (say: <i>science</i> with <i>math</i>
                    and <i>physics</i> as subcategories or
                    <i>humanities</i> with <i>art</i>,
                    <i>sociology</i> and <i>history</i>). This way we
                    enable the user to drill down into broad <i>humanities</i> or
                    <i>science</i> subject first and choose particular topics
                    afterwards. If the result of the hierarchical facet <ph>expression</ph>
                    evaluates to an array, each of array members will be treated as a hierarchical
                    value for that facet. Such an array could look in XQuery similar to
                    <ph>[('science', 'math'), ('humanities', 'history')]</ph> and be a result of
                    evaluating a function like <ph>idx:subject-hierarchy</ph> below stored in
                    an imported module (see <xref href="#external-module" scope="local">below</xref>) </p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;module uri="http://exist-db.org/lucene/test/" prefix="idx" at="module.xql"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="date" expression="tokenize(db:info/db:pubdate, '-')" hierarchical="yes"/&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="subject" expression="idx:subject-hierarchy(db:info/db:subjectset/db:subject/db:subjectterm)" hierarchical="yes"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">declare function idx:subject-hierarchy($key as xs:string*) {
    array:for-each (array {$key}, function($k) {
        doc('/db/subjects/subjects.xml')//subject[@name=$k]/ancestor-or-self::subject/@name
    })
};</pre>
                <p>which assumes hierarchical subject structure stored in
                    <i>/db/subjects/subjects.xml</i> </p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;subject&gt;
  &lt;subject name="science"&gt;
    &lt;subject name="math"/&gt;
    &lt;subject name="physics"/&gt;
  &lt;/subject&gt;
  &lt;subject name="humanities"&gt;
    &lt;subject name="art"/&gt;
    &lt;subject name="sociology"/&gt;
    &lt;subject name="history"/&gt;
  &lt;/subject&gt;
&lt;/subject&gt;</pre>
                <p>Next, we may want to define fields for the authors and title of the article.
                    In docbook, <ph>author</ph> can be a complex element, consisting e.g. of a
                    <ph>personname</ph> with nested <ph>surname</ph> and <ph>firstname</ph>.
                    For display to the user and sorting we want to pre-compute a normalized string
                    out of those components:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="title" expression="db:info/db:title"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="author" expression="for $au in db:info/db:author string-join(($au/db:personname/db:firstname, $au/db:personname/db:surname), ' ')"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p>A field does not need to define an <ph>expression</ph> attribute though: if
                    no expression is given, the field's content will be taken from the parent
                    element. This makes sense e.g. if you would like to index a node twice, e.g.
                    using a different analyzer. Or you can specify <ph>index="no"</ph> on the
                    parent element and index its content with an explicit field.</p>
                <p>A field may use a different analyzer than the one used to index the parent
                    content. Analyzers are referenced through <ph>analyzer</ph> attribute as
                    described <xref href="#analyzer" scope="local">above</xref>.</p>
                <p> <b>Typed fields</b>: fields may also declare a
                    <ph>type</ph> attribute: supported values are atomic types like
                    <ph>xs:date</ph>, <ph>xs:dateTime</ph>, <ph>xs:time</ph>,
                    <ph>xs:integer</ph>, <ph>xs:decimal</ph> and their sub-types. Defining a
                    type is important with respect to sorting (see below), e.g. to get dates in the
                    correct order. Typed fields can also be retrieved into corresponding XQuery
                    atomic values, so no additional casting is necessary. However, typed fields
                    cannot be queried using Lucene's default query parser, only retrieved with
                    <ph>ft:field</ph>.</p>
                <p> <b>Storing fields</b>: by default the complete content of a field is stored in the Lucene index, allowing later
                    fast retrieval of the content using <ph>ft:field</ph>. You can disable storing the content by adding attribute
                    <ph>store="no"</ph>. The field will still be indexed and available for queries though.</p>
                <p>
                        <b>Binary fields</b>: a special type of field offering faster access times than a normal field. Binary fields
                    are stored into a fast lookup table alongside the main index. Their content can be retrieved, but not queried, and you can declare a type
                    (see <i>typed fields</i> above). The default type will be <ph>xs:string</ph>. Use a binary field if you frequently need to sort or
                    filter large node sets by a given field, e.g. when sorting by date:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;module uri="http://exist-db.org/lucene/test/" prefix="idx" at="module.xql"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="title" expression="db:info/db:title"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="date" expression="db:info/db:pubdate" type="xs:date" binary="yes"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="author" expression="idx:author(db:info/db:author)"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p> <b>Importing external
                    modules</b>: as can be seen in the field definition for "author" above,
                    expressions can easily become quite verbose, so writing them into an attribute
                    is not convenient. It is thus also possible to import one or more XQuery modules
                    into the index configuration and use the functions declared in the
                    module:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;module uri="http://exist-db.org/lucene/test/" prefix="idx" at="module.xql"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article"&gt;
        &lt;facet dimension="keyword" expression="db:info/db:keywordset/db:keyword"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="title" expression="db:info/db:title"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="author" expression="idx:author(db:info/db:author)"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p>In this example we extract the code for computing the author field into a
                    function <ph>idx:authors</ph> located in an XQuery module,
                    <ph>module.xql</ph>. Note that we're using a relative import path for
                    the module in the <ph>at</ph> attribute. The path will be resolved
                    relative to the collection to which the collection configuration applies (not
                    where the collection configuration itself is stored). It is also important that
                    the module and all dependencies it imports is stored <i>before</i>
                    the collection configuration is saved and indexing starts.</p>
                <p> <b>Conditions</b>: sometimes you may want to create
                    a field only if a certain condition is met. For this purpose, an additional
                    attribute <ph>if</ph> may be added, containing an XPath expression. If
                    the expression evaluates to an effective boolean value of
                    <ph>true</ph>, the field will be created. Otherwise it is
                    skipped.</p>
                <p>Conditions are useful to e.g. distinguish between different languages and
                    apply an appropriate analyzer to each. Let's assume our docbook articles may
                    have both, a German and English version. The language is indicated by the
                    <ph>@xml:lang</ph> attribute on the top-level <ph>section</ph> element. We
                    thus create a separate field for each language and connect it to the analyzer
                    appropriate for the language:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.de.GermanAnalyzer" id="german"/&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.en.EnglishAnalyzer" id="english"/&gt;
      &lt;text qname="db:article" index="no"&gt;
        &lt;field name="english" if="@xml:lang='en'" analyzer="english"/&gt;
        &lt;field name="german" if="@xml:lang='de'" analyzer="german"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
                <p>Note that we skip indexing the parent <ph>article</ph> element with
                    <ph>index="no"</ph> because we do not want a default index, but rather a
                    separate field for each language, so we can target them in queries
                    explicitely.</p>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="query">
            <title>Querying the Index</title>
        
        <p>Querying full text from XQuery is straightforward. For example:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">for $m in //SPEECH[ft:query(., "boil bubble")]
order by ft:score($m) descending
return $m</pre>
        <p>The query function takes a query string in Lucene's default <xref href="https://lucene.apache.org/core/4_10_4/queryparser/org/apache/lucene/queryparser/classic/package-summary.html#package_description" scope="external">query syntax</xref>. It returns a set of nodes which are relevant with respect to the
            query. Lucene assigns a relevance score or rank (a decimal number) to each match. This
            score is preserved by eXist-db and can be accessed through the score function.</p>
        <p>The higher the score, the more relevant the text. You can use Lucene's features to
            "boost" a certain term in the query: give it a higher or lower influence on the final
            rank.</p>
        <p>Please note that the score is computed relative to the root context of the index. If
            you created an index on <ph>SPEECH</ph>, all scores will be computed based on text in
            <ph>SPEECH</ph> nodes, even though your actual query may only return <ph>LINE</ph>
            children of <ph>SPEECH</ph>.</p>
        <p>The query string passed to <ph>ft:query</ph> may be empty. In this case all
            items from the context sequence are matched and returned. Using an empty query makes
            sense in combination with the options for retrieving facets and field values described
            below.</p>
        <p>The Lucene module is fully supported by eXist-db's query-rewriting optimizer. This
            means that the query engine can rewrite the XQuery expression to make best use of the
            available indexes. All the rules and hints given in the <xref href="tuning.xml" scope="external">tuning</xref> guide fully apply to the Lucene index.</p>
        <p>To present search results in a <i>Keywords in Context</i> format, you
            may want to have a look at eXist-db's <xref href="kwic.xml" scope="external">KWIC</xref>
            module.</p>
        <section id="query-fields">
                <title>Querying Fields</title>
            
            <p>Fields associated with the indexed parent node (see <xref href="#facets-and-fields" scope="local">above</xref>) can be queried with
                <ph>ft:query</ph> by prefixing parts of the query expression with the
                field name followed by a colon (':') as described in the documentation for Lucene's
                default query syntax. For example, the following expression searches for a docbook
                article containing the terms "xml" in the text and "xquery language" in the
                title:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">//db:article[ft:query(., "title:(xquery AND language) AND xml")]</pre>
            <p>Note how subexpressions can be grouped with parentheses to clearly state to which
                field they apply.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="retrieve-fields">
                <title>Retrieving Field Content</title>
            
            <p>You can retrieve the content of a field for display or sorting purposes using the <ph>ft:field</ph> function or alternatively the
                <ph>ft:binary-field</ph> function if you created a binary field. However, fields are always bound to the result of a full text query,
                so you cannot retrieve them without calling <ph>ft:query</ph> first.</p>
            <p>One of the most common uses for retrieving field contents will be for sorting the
                results of a query. The <ph>order by</ph> in the example below sorts results by
                title first and then by author.</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">for $article in collection("/db/articles")//db:article[ft:query(., "xquery")]
order by ft:field($article, "title"), ft:binary-field($article, "date", "xs:date")[1]
return
    $article</pre>
            <p>Note that even though fields are only available with the results of the ft:query,
                it is still possible to use them for sorting and displaying the whole available data
                set. For example, to view all articles in the collection you could pass in an empty
                sequence in place of the query string like this:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">//db:article[ft:query(., ())]</pre>
            <p> <b>Typed fields</b>: If you declared a different type than <ph>xs:string</ph> on a field, you should
                remember to use the 3-parameter variant of <ph>ft:field</ph> or <ph>ft:binary-field</ph> and pass in the name of the desired
                target type as 3rd parameter. Reason: lucene basically stores all non-text data types as numbers and eXist has no way to figure out the original
                type of the field. So if you defined a field (binary or not) with type <ph>xs:date</ph>, make sure to retrieve it with
                <ph>ft:binary-field($node, "date", "xs:date")</ph>, otherwise you'll either get an error or garbage returned.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="expand-fields">
                <title>Matches in fields</title>
            
            <p>When retrieving the content of a field for display, you may still need an indication
                of where matches were found. You cannot use <ph>util:expand</ph> for that 
                but need <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> instead. Effectively it provides 
                the same mechanism as <ph>util:expand</ph> for full text matches but works on fields.</p>

            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>util:expand</ph> operates on nodes which are part of an XML document</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>fields are attached to a node, but can contain arbitrary string content which may, but does 
                        not have to, be derived from the document</p>
                </li>
                </ul>

            <p>Thus <ph>util:expand</ph> and <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> behave differently 
                and produce slightly different output. <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> is also faster as it 
                does not need to traverse the XML tree like <ph>util:expand</ph>.</p>

            <p>
                <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> will return a field it
                received in its first parameter with <ph>exist:match</ph>
                tag wrapped around the matches. </p>            

            <p>For example, to display each matching article with its title, author and matched full
                text as KWIC, you could start with the code below. Please note that 
                <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> just returns
                <ph>exist:field</ph> with <ph>exist:match</ph> inside, so you'd need
                to further process the result for proper HTML output.</p>

            <pre outputclass="xquery">  
for $article in collection("/db/articles")//db:article[ft:query(., "lucene AND title:xquery AND author:wolfgang", map { "fields": ("title", "author") })]
    order by ft:field($article, "title")[1]
return
    &lt;result&gt;
      {ft:highlight-field-matches($article, 'title')}
      {ft:highlight-field-matches($article, 'author')}
      {kwic:summarize($article, &lt;config width="40"/&gt;)}
    &lt;/result&gt;</pre>
        </section>
        <section id="display-facets">
                <title>Displaying Facet Counts</title>
            
            <p>Facet counts for the query result can be retrieved if facets are associated with
                an indexed parent element. Facet counts for a particular dimension are available as
                a map containing an entry for each facet value occurring in one or more items of the
                query result. The map links the facet value given as a map key with a positive count
                corresponding to the number of times the value occurs in the result set. Facet
                values with zero count are never included.</p>
            <p>For example, we may use the following query to display the facet counts for the
                "keyword" dimension in our set of docbook articles:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $result := collection("/db/articles")//db:article[ft:query(., "xml")]
let $facets := ft:facets($result, "keyword", ())
return
    &lt;table&gt;
    {
        map:for-each($facets, function($label, $count) {
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;{$label}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;{$count}&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
        })
    }
    &lt;/table&gt;</pre>
            <p>Function <ph>ft:facets</ph> expects a sequence of nodes belonging to a
                result set obtained from one or more calls to <ph>ft:query</ph>. If the
                sequence was combined from multiple expressions calling <ph>ft:query</ph>,
                the facet counts will be merged. Second parameter of <ph>ft:facets</ph>
                specifies the dimension for which facet counts should be retrieved. The third
                parameter should be either empty sequence or a positive integer denoting the maximum
                number of facets to show. In the case it is smaller than the total number of facets,
                only those with the highest counts are returned. Passing an empty sequence means
                that all facet value counts should be shown. Please note that facets with a zero
                occurrence count (i.e. facets not appearing anywhere in the result) are never
                returned.</p>
            <p>For hierarchical facets only the top-most facet value in the hierarchy will be
                returned by default. For example, if you indexed a date facet with separate year,
                month and day component, a call to <ph>ft:facets($node, "date", ())</ph> will
                return facet counts for years only. To also get counts for months, you have to call
                <ph>ft:facets</ph> with a fourth parameter, passing in the year for which
                sub-facet counts should be retrieved. To get days, you also need to specify month
                and so on. <ph>ft:facets($node, "date", (), ("2018", "06"))</ph> will thus
                return facet counts for all days in June 2018.</p>
        </section>
        <section id="refine-facets">
                <title>Refining a Query with Facets</title>
            
            <p>The main purpose of facets is to quickly narrow down a query result, limiting it
                to only items which match a certain facet value. To drill down by a given facet
                dimension and value, pass a key "facets" in the options map given in the third
                parameter of <ph>ft:query</ph>:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $options := map { 
    "facets": map { 
        "keyword": ("indexing", "facets")
    }
}
return
    collection("/db/articles")//db:article[ft:query(., "xml", $options)]</pre>
            <p>If you specify multiple dimensions, these will be linked together with a logical
                <ph>and</ph>, limiting the result to elements matching both
                dimensions.</p>
            <p>Treatment of multiple values for one facet dimension depends on the type of facet.
                For non-hierarchical facets, as in example above, if you specify more than one value
                these will be linked together with a logical <ph>or</ph>, returning
                elements matching any of the alternative facet values for that dimension.</p>
            <p>In case of hierarchical facets, a sequence of items is interpreted as a
                hierarchical value/subvalue facet path, therefore expression like <ph>("2018",
                "06", "25")</ph> for the <i>date</i> dimension mentioned earlier
                will return nodes from the 25th of June 2018. Nested sequences are not allowed in
                XQuery, so the only way to pass in multiple hierarchical facet paths is by wrapping
                the whole structure in an array. Each array element then is logically linked with
                its other members with <ph>or</ph> expression. To query for elements from
                June <i>or</i> May 2018 we therefore need to specify date dimension
                values as <ph>[("2018", "06"), ("2018", "05")]</ph> </p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $options := map { 
    "facets": map { 
        "keyword": ("indexing", "facets"),
        "date": [("2018", "06"), ("2018", "05")]
    }
}
return
    collection("/db/articles")//db:article[ft:query(., "xml", $options)]</pre>
        </section>
        <section id="describe">
                <title>Describing Queries in XML</title>
            
            <p>Lucene's default query syntax does not provide access to all available features.
                However, eXist-db's <ph>ft:query</ph> function also accepts a description
                of the query in XML, as an alternative to passing a query string. The XML
                description closely mirrors Lucene's query API. It is transformed into an internal
                tree of query objects, which is directly passed to Lucene for execution. This has
                several advantages, for example you can specify if the order of terms should be
                relevant for a phrase query:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;near ordered="no"&gt;miserable nation&lt;/near&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return
    //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
            <p>Ranged queries using <ph>TO</ph> are also supported. Suppose you have
                marked dates and wish to return only results between 1600 and 1610.</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query := "date:[1600 TO 1610]"

return ft:search($col, $query)//exist:match
</pre>
            <p>The following elements may occur within a query description:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>term</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Defines a single term to be searched in the index. If the root query
                            element contains a sequence of term elements, wrap them in
                            <ph>bool/</ph> and they will be combined as in a boolean "or" query.
                            For example: </p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;bool&gt;&lt;term&gt;nation&lt;/term&gt;&lt;term&gt;miserable&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/bool&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return
//SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                        <p>This finds all <ph>SPEECH</ph> elements containing either
                            <ph>nation</ph> or <ph>miserable</ph> or both.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>wildcard</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>A string with a <ph>*</ph> wildcard in it. This will be matched
                            against the terms of a document. Can be used instead of a
                            <ph>term</ph> element. For example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;bool&gt;&lt;term&gt;nation&lt;/term&gt;&lt;wildcard&gt;miser*&lt;/wildcard&gt;&lt;/bool&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return
//SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>regex</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>A regular expression which will be matched against the terms of a
                            document. Can be used instead of a <ph>term</ph> element. For
                            example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;bool&gt;&lt;term&gt;nation&lt;/term&gt;&lt;regex&gt;miser.*&lt;/regex&gt;&lt;/bool&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return
//SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>bool</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Constructs a boolean query from its children. Each child element may
                            have an occurrence indicator, which could be either
                            <ph>must</ph>, <ph>should</ph> or
                            <ph>not</ph>:</p>
                        <dl>
                                <dlentry>
                                    <dt> <ph>must</ph> </dt>
                                    <dd>
                                    <p>this part of the query <i>must</i> be
                                        matched</p>
                                </dd>
                                </dlentry>
                                <dlentry>
                                    <dt> <ph>should</ph> </dt>
                                    <dd>
                                    <p>this part of the query <i>should</i> be
                                        matched, but doesn't need to</p>
                                </dd>
                                </dlentry>
                                <dlentry>
                                    <dt> <ph>not</ph> </dt>
                                    <dd>
                                    <p>this part of the query <i>must not</i> be
                                        matched</p>
                                </dd>
                                </dlentry>
                            </dl>
                        <p>For instance:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;bool&gt;&lt;term occur="must"&gt;boil&lt;/term&gt;&lt;term occur="should"&gt;bubble&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/bool&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(LINE, $query)]</pre>
                        <p>To optimize performance you can specify a minimum number of matches to
                            prevent needless disjunctive searches, using the <ph>min</ph>
                            attribute. If no occurrence indicator is provided the query will default
                            to <ph>should</ph>, as this is the only indicator that
                            supports <ph>min</ph>:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query := &lt;query&gt;&lt;bool min="3"&gt;&lt;term&gt;witch&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/bool&gt;&lt;/query&gt;

return
  //SPEECH[ft:query(LINE, $query)]        
</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>phrase</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Searches for a group of terms occurring in the correct order. The
                            element may either contain explicit <ph>term</ph> elements or text
                            content. Text will be automatically tokenized into a sequence of terms.
                            For example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;phrase&gt;cauldron boil&lt;/phrase&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                        <p>This has the same effect as:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;phrase&gt;&lt;term&gt;cauldron&lt;/term&gt;&lt;term&gt;boil&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/phrase&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                        <p>The attribute <ph>slop</ph> can be used for a proximity
                            search: Lucene will try to find terms which are within the specified
                            distance:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;phrase slop="10"&gt;&lt;term&gt;frog&lt;/term&gt;&lt;term&gt;dog&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/phrase&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>near</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p> <ph>near</ph> is a powerful alternative to <ph>phrase</ph> and
                            one of the features not available through the standard Lucene query
                            parser.</p>
                        <p>If the element has text content only, it will be tokenized into terms
                            and the expression behaves like <ph>phrase</ph>. Otherwise it may
                            contain any combination of <ph>term</ph>, <ph>first</ph> and nested
                            <ph>near</ph> elements. This makes it possible to search for two
                            sequences of terms which are within a specific distance. For
                            example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;near slop="20"&gt;&lt;term&gt;snake&lt;/term&gt;&lt;near slop="1"&gt;tongue dog&lt;/near&gt;&lt;/near&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                        <p>Element <ph>first</ph> matches a span against the start of the text
                            in the context node. It takes an optional attribute
                            <ph>end</ph> to specify the maximum distance from the start of
                            the text. For example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;near slop="50"&gt;&lt;first end="2"&gt;&lt;near&gt;second witch&lt;/near&gt;&lt;/first&gt;&lt;near
slop="1"&gt;tongue dog&lt;/near&gt;&lt;/near&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
    return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                        <p>As shown above, the content of <ph>first</ph> can again be text, a
                            <ph>term</ph> or <ph>near</ph>.</p>
                        <p>Contrary to <ph>phrase</ph>, <ph>near</ph> can be told to ignore
                            the order of its components. Use parameter
                            <ph>ordered="yes|no"</ph> to change near's behaviour. For
                            example:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query :=
    &lt;query&gt;
        &lt;near slop="100" ordered="no"&gt;&lt;term&gt;bubble&lt;/term&gt;&lt;term&gt;fillet&lt;/term&gt;&lt;/near&gt;
    &lt;/query&gt;
return //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query)]</pre>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
            <p>All elements in a query may have an optional <ph>boost</ph> parameter
                (float). The score of the nodes matching the corresponding query part will be
                multiplied by this factor.</p>
        </section>
        
        <section id="parameters">
                <title>Additional parameters</title>
            
            <p>The <ph>ft:query</ph> function allows a third parameter for passing additional
                settings to the query engine. This parameter must be an XML fragment which lists the
                configuration properties to be set as child elements:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $options :=
    &lt;options&gt;
        &lt;query-analyzer-id&gt;ws&lt;/query-analyzer-id&gt;
        &lt;default-operator&gt;and&lt;/default-operator&gt;
        &lt;phrase-slop&gt;1&lt;/phrase-slop&gt;
        &lt;leading-wildcard&gt;no&lt;/leading-wildcard&gt;
        &lt;filter-rewrite&gt;yes&lt;/filter-rewrite&gt;
        &lt;lowercase-expanded-terms&gt;yes&lt;/lowercase-expanded-terms&gt;
    &lt;/options&gt;
return
    //SPEECH[ft:query(., $query, $options)]</pre>
            <p>The meaning of those properties is as follows:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>query-analyzer-id</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Explicitly specifies the analyzer that should be used to process
                            that particular query. The value provided should match the
                            <ph>id</ph> attribute of an <ph>analyzer</ph> defined in
                            collection.xconf. If you don't specify that property, your query will
                            be processed using the same analyzer that was used to create the
                            index you're querying. While this works for most cases, there are tasks
                            that require this finer level of control. For example it is a feature of
                            some Lucene analyzers that the parameters used for indexing a field
                            are different from those used to query it. In such cases simply define
                            a distinct <ph>analyzer</ph> (dubbed 'query analyzer') and
                            explicitly refer to it with the <ph>query-analyzer-id</ph> parameter
                            in each respective query invocation.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>filter-rewrite</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Controls how terms are expanded for wildcard or regular expression
                            searches. If set to <ph>yes</ph>, Lucene will use a filter to
                            pre-process matching terms. If set to <ph>no</ph>, all matching
                            terms will be added to a single boolean query which is then executed.
                            This may generate a "too many clauses" exception when applied to large
                            data sets. Setting filter-rewrite to <ph>yes</ph> avoids those
                            issues.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>default-operator</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>The default operator with which multiple terms will be combined.
                            Allowed values: <ph>or</ph>, <ph>and</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>phrase-slop</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Sets the default slop for phrases. If <ph>0</ph>, then exact
                            phrase matches are required. Default value is <ph>0</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>leading-wildcard</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>When set to <ph>yes</ph>, <ph>*</ph> or <ph>?</ph> are
                            allowed as the first character of a PrefixQuery and WildcardQuery. Note
                            that this can produce very slow queries on big indexes.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt> <ph>lowercase-expanded-terms</ph> </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>An option used to set whether the terms in wildcard, prefix, fuzzy, or range queries should be
                        automatically lower-cased or left in their original case. 
                        When set to <ph>yes</ph>, query terms are lower-cased (i.e., as if <ph>fn:lower-case()</ph> were applied to the query string).
                        Default value is <ph>no</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="constructed-fields">
            <title>Adding Constructed Fields to a Document</title>
        

        <p>This feature allows to add arbitrary fields to a binary or XML document and have them
            indexed with Lucene. It was developed as part of the <xref href="contentextraction" scope="external">content extraction framework</xref>, to attach metadata
            extracted from for instance a PDF to the binary document. It works equally well for XML
            documents though and is an efficient method to attach computed fields to a document,
            containing information which does not exist in the XML as such.</p>
        <note type="note">
                <p>With the advent of <xref href="#facets-and-fields" scope="local"/>) functionality it is
                recommended to use these instead of constructed fields.</p>
            </note>
        <p>The field indexes are not configured via <ph>collection.xconf</ph>. Instead
            we add fields programmatically from an XQuery (which could be run via a trigger):</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">ft:index("/db/demo/test.xml", &lt;doc&gt;
    &lt;field name="title" store="yes"&gt;Indexing&lt;/field&gt;
    &lt;field name="author" store="yes"&gt;Me&lt;/field&gt;
    &lt;field name="date" store="yes"&gt;2013&lt;/field&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;)</pre>

        <p>The <ph>store</ph> attribute indicates that the fields content should be
            stored as a string. Without this attribute, the content will be indexed for search, but
            you won't be able to retrieve the contents. </p>
        <p>To get the contents of a field, use the <ph>ft:get-field</ph>
            function:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">ft:get-field("/db/demo/test.xml", "title")</pre>

        <p>To query this index, use the <ph>ft:search</ph> function:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">ft:search("/db/demo/test.xml", "title:indexing and author:me")</pre>

        <p>Custom field indexes are automatically deleted when their parent document is removed.
            If you want to update fields without removing the document, you need to delete the old
            fields first though. This can be done using the <ph>ft:remove-index</ph>
            function:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">ft:remove-index("/db/demo/test.xml")</pre>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>