<topic id="contentextraction">
    <title>Extracting Content from Binary Files</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>The Content Extraction module extends eXist-db's XML abilities to binary files. The module
        contains functions for extracting the content of the binary files, and returning the content
        as XML. In this form, the content can then be queried, indexed, and manipulated. It useful
        especially in conjunction with Lucene indexes.</p>
        <p>The Content Extraction is built on the <xref href="https://tika.apache.org/" scope="external">Apache
        Tika</xref> library. Tika understands a large variety of formats, ranging from PDF documents
        to spreadsheets and image metadata.</p>
        <section id="usage">
            <title>Usage</title>
        

        <p>To import the module use the following import statement:</p>
        <pre>import module namespace content="http://exist-db.org/xquery/contentextraction"
    at "java:org.exist.contentextraction.xquery.ContentExtractionModule";</pre>

        <p>The module provides three functions:</p>
        <pre>content:get-metadata($binary as xs:base64Binary) as document-node()
content:get-metadata-and-content($binary as xs:base64Binary) as document-node()
content:stream-content($binary as xs:base64Binary, $paths as xs:string*, $callback as function, $namespaces as element()?, $userData as item()*) as empty-sequence()</pre>

        <p>The first two functions need little explanation: <ph>get-metadata()</ph> just
            returns some metadata extracted from the resource, while
            <ph>get-metadata-and-content()</ph> will also provide the text body of the resource
            (if any). The third function is a streaming variant of the other two and is used to
            process larger resources whose content may not fit into memory.</p>
        <p>All functions produce XHTML. The metadata will be contained in the HTML head, the
            contents goes into the body. The structure of the body HTML varies depending on the
            media type of the binary file. For example, the HTML resulting from a PDF is a sequence
            of <ph>div</ph> elements, one per page. That of a word processing document is often a
            sequence of paragraphs.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="storage">
            <title>Storage and Indexing Strategies</title>
        

        <p>While you could decide to just store the HTML returned by the content extraction
            functions as an XML resource into the database, this may not be efficient. For example,
            a document search applications may not need to retain the extracted HTML.</p>
        <p>In such cases the <ph>ft:index()</ph> function from the full text indexing module
            can be useful. This function allows users to associate a full text index with any
            database resource, be it binary or XML. The index will be linked to the resource.</p>
        <p>To create an index, call the function with the following arguments: </p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>The path of the resource to which the index should be linked as a
                    string.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>An XML fragment describing the fields you want to add and the text content to
                    index.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>For example, to associate an index with the document <ph>test.txt</ph>, call
            <ph>ft:index()</ph> as follows: </p>
        <pre>ft:index("/db/apps/demo/test.txt", &lt;doc&gt;
    &lt;field name="title" store="yes"&gt;Indexing&lt;/field&gt;
    &lt;field name="para" store="yes"&gt;This is the first paragraph.&lt;/field&gt;
    &lt;field name="para" store="yes"&gt;And a second paragraph.&lt;/field&gt;
&lt;/doc&gt;)</pre>

        <p>This creates a Lucene index document, indexes the content using the configured
            analyzers, and links it to the eXist document with the given path. You may link more
            than one Lucene document to the same eXist resource. The field elements map to Lucene
            fields. You can use as many fields as you want or add multiple fields with the same
            name.</p>
        <p>The <ph>store="yes"</ph> attribute tells the indexer to also store the text
            string, so you can retrieve it later.</p>
        <p>To query the created index, use the <ph>ft:search()</ph> function: </p>
        <pre>ft:search("/db/apps/demo/test.txt", "para:paragraph and title:indexing")</pre>
        <p> The first parameter is the path to the resource or collection to query. Tthe second
            specifies a Lucene query string. Note how we prefix the query term by the name of the
            field.</p>
        <p>Executing this query returns:</p>
        <pre>&lt;results&gt;
    &lt;search uri="/db/apps/demo/test.txt" score="6.3111067"&gt;
        &lt;field name="para"&gt;This is the first
            &lt;exist:match&gt;paragraph&lt;/exist:match&gt;.&lt;/field&gt;
        &lt;field name="para"&gt;And a second
            &lt;exist:match&gt;paragraph&lt;/exist:match&gt;.&lt;/field&gt;
        &lt;field name="title"&gt;&lt;exist:match&gt;Indexing&lt;/exist:match&gt;&lt;/field&gt;
    &lt;/search&gt;
&lt;/results&gt;</pre>

        <p>Each matching resource is described by a search element. The score attribute expresses
            the relevance Lucene computed for the resource (the higher the better). Within the
            search element, every field which contributed to the query result is returned, but only
            if <ph>store="yes"</ph> was defined for this field at indexing time.</p>
        <p> Note how the matches in the text are enclosed in <ph>match</ph> elements, just as
            if you did a full text query on an XML document. This makes it easy to post-process the
            query result, for example to create a keywords in context display using eXist's standard
            KWIC module.</p>
        <p>The document the index is linked to does not need to be a binary resource. One can
            also create additional indexes on XML documents. This is a useful feature, because it
            allows us to index and query information which is not directly contained in the XML
            itself. For example, one could add metadata fields and retrieve them later using
            <ph>get-field</ph>. Or we could use fields to pre-process and normalize information
            already present in the XML to speed up later access.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>