<topic id="uploading-files">
    <title>Getting Data into eXist-db</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="getting-started"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db is a document oriented <i>database</i> and therefore stores <i>documents</i>. But how do you get them in?
    This article will handle several ways of doing that.</p>
        <section id="with-dashboard">
            <title>Uploading files using the Dashboard</title>
    

    <p> eXist-db's <xref href="{dashboard}" scope="external">Dashboard</xref>'s comes with a Collections pane. This
      lets you upload files from your filesystem into the database. Click on this icon to open it iIf you are not logged in, Dashboard will prompt you
      to log in first):</p>
    <fig>
                <title>The Collection pane's icon</title>
                <image href="assets/collections-app.png" width="20%"/>
            </fig>

    <p>A dialog will appear showing you the database collection hierarchy. After that perform the following steps:</p>
    <ol>
                <li>
        <p>Select the target collection for your files in the left pane. </p>
        <p>If you need to create a new collection for your files first, do so by selecting the <ph>New Collection</ph> button; it
          looks like a manila folder with a green plus.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Click on the <ph>Upload</ph> button (it looks like a gray cylinder with a green plus).</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Either drag and drop the files you want to upload or browse to select a file from your disk.</p>
      </li>
            </ol>
  </section>
        <section id="with-exide">
            <title>Uploading files with eXide</title>
    

    <p>eXide is eXist-db's built-in Integrated Development Environment (IDE). Among eXide's many functions is the ability to upload files from your
      filesystem into the database.</p>
    <p>To initiate an upload:</p>
    <ol>
                <li>
        <p>Open eXide from the Dashboard</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Choose <ph>File</ph>, <ph>Manage</ph> from the menu</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>click on the <ph>Upload</ph> button.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Either drag and drop the files you want to upload or browse to select a file from your disk.</p>
      </li>
            </ol>

  </section>
        <section id="with-webdav">
            <title>Uploading files with a WebDAV client</title>
    

    <p>A WebDAV client lets you manage eXist-db database collections and documents almost like directories and files in a filesystem. WebDAV
      clients, or applications with built-in WebDAV support, include Windows Explorer, macOS Finder, <xref href="http://www.webdav.org/cadaver" scope="external">cadaver</xref>, <xref href="https://www.konqueror.org/" scope="external">KDE Konqueror</xref>, <xref href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/" scope="external">oXygen XML Editor</xref>, <xref href="https://www.altova.com/" scope="external">XML Spy</xref>, <xref href="https://www.libreoffice.org/" scope="external">LibreOffice</xref>, <xref href="https://panic.com/transmit/" scope="external">Transmit</xref> (MacOS only),
      and many others.</p>

    <p>To connect a WebDAV client to eXist-db, you need the URL for eXist's WebDAV interface and an eXist-db username and password. eXist-db's
      default URL for its WebDAV interface is:</p>
    <pre>http://localhost:8080/exist/webdav/db/</pre>
    <p>The URL with HTTPS (SSL) encryption (some clients, among which Windows Explorer, require such a connection) is:</p>
    <pre>https://localhost:8443/exist/webdav/db/</pre>
    <p>The client may accept a URL or it may ask you to split up the URL into its component parts. Taking
        <ph>http://localhost:8080/exist/webdav/db/</ph> as an example, the server name is <ph>localhost</ph>, the port is <ph>8080</ph>,
      and the remote path is <ph>/exist/webdav/db</ph>.</p>
    <p>Dedicated WebDAV clients are an excellent way to upload and manage the contents of their database. For more information about using WebDAV
      connections with eXist-db (including client-specific instructions), see the <xref href="webdav" scope="external">WebDAV</xref> article.</p>
  </section>
        <section id="with-java-client">
            <title>Uploading files with the Java Admin Client</title>
    

    <p>The <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref> also lets you upload files into
      the database. This can be done using the GUI or the command line.</p>
    <p>For uploading files using the Java Admin Client's GUI:</p>
    <ol>
                <li>
        <p>Start the Java Admin Client, for instance by selecting the <ph>Open Java Admin Client</ph> command from eXist-db
          system tray application's menu.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Select <ph>File</ph>, <ph>Store files/directories</ph>, or click on the
            <ph>Store</ph> icon (which looks like a piece of paper with a plus icon).</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Select the file(s) you want to store in the database</p>
      </li>
            </ol>

    <p>To upload files with the command line:</p>
    <pre>bin/client.sh -m /db/path/in/database -p /path/on/file/system</pre>
    <p>The <ph>-m</ph> parameter specifies the target collection, the <ph>-p</ph> parameter the path on the filesystem to the files to
      upload. See also the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref>
      documentation.</p>
  </section>
        <section id="with-xquery">
            <title>Uploading files with XQuery</title>
    

    <p>Of course you can also programmaticly store documents in the database files using eXist-db's main programming language XQuery. For this use
      the <ph>xmldb:store()</ph> function. Fetching the documents (or data) to store can be done using the various HTTP Client modules, such as
      the EXPath HTTP Client <ph>http:request()</ph> function or the eXist-db specific <ph>httpclient:get()</ph> function. You can also fetch
      your data from the filesystem using <ph>xmldb:store-files-from-pattern()</ph>, which accepts wildcard patterns like
      <ph>*.xml</ph>.</p>
  </section>
        <section id="with-ant">
            <title>Uploading files with Ant</title>
    

    <p>Ant is a build tool for automating common tasks. eXist-db comes with some special Ant eXist-db actions to automate things like importing or
      exporting files, etc.</p>
    <p>The action for uploading files and storing them into your database is <ph>xdb:store</ph>. See <xref href="ant-tasks" scope="external">Ant Tasks</xref> for more information.</p>
  </section>
    </body>
</topic>