<topic id="webdav">
    <title>WebDAV</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q20"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="getting-started"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="interfaces"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db ships with a <xref href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WebDAV" scope="external">WebDAV</xref> interface.
    WebDAV makes it possible to manage database collections and documents just like directories and
    files in a file system. You can copy, move, delete, view or edit files with any application
    supporting the WebDAV protocol, including Windows Explorer, macOS Finder, <xref href="http://www.webdav.org/cadaver" scope="external">cadaver</xref>, <xref href="https://www.konqueror.org/" scope="external">KDE Konqueror</xref>, <xref href="https://www.oxygenxml.com/" scope="external">oXygen XML Editor</xref>, <xref href="https://www.altova.com/" scope="external">XML Spy</xref>, <xref href="https://www.libreoffice.org/" scope="external">LibreOffice</xref> and many others (see <xref href="#compatibility" scope="local"/>
    below). The interface has been implemented with excellent open-source <xref href="http://milton.io" scope="external">Milton</xref>  WebDAV API for Java.</p>
        <p>In the default configuration the WebDAV server can be accessed via the URLs <ph>http://localhost:8080/exist/webdav/db/</ph> and <ph>http://localhost:8443/exist/webdav/db/</ph>.</p>
        <section id="compatibility">
            <title>Compatibility</title>
    
    <ul>
                <li>
        <p>eXist's Milton based WebDAV interface does not support HTTP Digest Authentication.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>
          The size of an XML document is presented as a multiple of 4096 bytes, which is eXist's
          internal pagesize (see <xref href="configuration#conf.xml" scope="external">conf.xml</xref>). The actual size of an XML
          document stored in the database can not be determined because the size depends on many
          factors, e.g. the applied serialization parameters.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
                    <p>A webdav client / enabled application may or may not work with the webdav server of eXist-db, depending on the quality of the implementation of the client. The server fullfills all requirements of the webdav <xref href="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2518" scope="external">specification</xref>.</p>
                </li>
            </ul>
  </section>
        <section id="serialization">
            <title>Serialization</title>
    

    <p>When retrieving an XML document via the WebDAV interface, the default serialization
      settings as defined in <xref href="configuration#conf.xml" scope="external">conf.xml</xref> are effective. It is  possible to define custom serialization settings specific for the WebDAV interface. </p>
    <p>
      Copy the file <ph>extensions/webdav/src/main/resources/webdav.properties</ph>
      into <ph>$EXIST_HOME/etc</ph> directory and uncomment/modify the parameters. Changes
      in this file requires a restart of eXist-db. </p>

    <pre>## XML Serialization options for the WevDAV
## The file is read from $EXIST_HOME/etc
## Be carefull changing the default values !
indent=no
expand-xincludes=no
process-xsl-pi=no
encoding=UTF-8
omit-xml-declaration=no
</pre>
  </section>
        <section id="notes">
            <title>Notes</title>
    

    <p> From the <xref href="https://github.com/eXist-db/exist/issues/1442" scope="external">community</xref> we have received feedback that the WebDAV interface is not fully
      functional when it is accessed via a reverse proxy and a resource's path is altered (aliased)
      with it. </p>
  </section>
    </body>
</topic>