<topic id="datasync">
    <title>Synchronize directory to a collection</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="3Q20"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="synchronize"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="filesystem"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="collection"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article provides information on the synchronization of filesystem data to an exist-db collection.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>An editing workflow often operates on a filesystem directory that eventually may be published using exist-db.
            An <xref href="https://search.maven.org/search?q=a:exist-db-addons" scope="external">exist-db-addons</xref> library,
            available in maven central, enables automatic publication of a directory to a collection.
        </p>
        <p>Files in a directory specified by the parameter <b>datadir</b> will be synchronized to a collection specified by the parameter
                <b>collection</b> recursively. If the target collection
            does not exist it will be created. Files and collections that are new or newer than the
            one in the target collection will be written to that collection. Files and collections
            that are not present in the source directory will be removed from the collection, this
            can be turned off via a boolean parameter <b>removeNotInSource</b>. Owner and group of collections and documents can be
            provided in parameters <b>owner</b> and <b>group</b>, otherwise they will be the same as the owner and group of the
            parent collection of the provided collection parameter. After syncing cache is cleared
            to prevent problems, this can be turned off via boolean parameter <b>clearCache</b>. NOTE that the sync will partially succeed when during
            syncing an exception occurs, collections and files added or removed before the exception
            will remain added/removed. Meant to be used as a start-up task, DataSyncTaskCron is
            meant to be scheduled as a cronjob. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="usage">
            <title>usage</title>
        
        <p>Below a setup for exist-db for data synchronization.</p>
        <section id="classpath">
                <title>Include exist-db-addons</title>
            
            <p>For example in a Dockerfile:</p>
            <pre outputclass="Dockerfile">ARG EXISTADDONSERSION=2.3
COPY exist-db-addons-${EXISTADDONSERSION}.jar $EXIST_HOME/lib/
ENV CLASSPATH=$EXIST_HOME/lib/exist.uber.jar:$EXIST_HOME/lib/exist-db-addons-${EXISTADDONSERSION}.jar</pre>
            <p>Or include a dependency in exist-db's pom.xml:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;dependency&gt;
  &lt;groupId&gt;
    org.fryske-akademy
  &lt;/groupId&gt;
  &lt;artifactId&gt;
    exist-db-addons
  &lt;/artifactId&gt;
  &lt;version&gt;
    2.3
  &lt;/version&gt;
&lt;/dependency&gt;</pre>
        </section>
        <section id="conf.xml">
                <title>configure in conf.xml</title>
            
            <p>Sync at start-up, <xref href="../scheduler" scope="external">see scheduler</xref>
                </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;job class="org.fryske_akademy.exist.jobs.DataSyncTask" type="system" period="10" repeat="0"&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="collection" value="xmldb:exist:///db/apps/teidictjson/data"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="datadir" value="/data"/&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;</pre>
            <p>Sync at 2am, <xref href="../scheduler" scope="external">see scheduler</xref>
                </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;job class="org.fryske_akademy.exist.jobs.DataSyncTaskCron" type="system" cron-trigger="0 0 2 ? * *"&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="collection" value="xmldb:exist:///db/apps/teidictjson/data"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="datadir" value="/data"/&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;</pre>
        </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>