<topic id="xmldb">
    <title>The xmldb module</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>The xmldb module (<ph>http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb</ph> function namespace)
    contains functions for manipulating database contents. The full list of functions and their
    documentation can be found in the <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb" scope="external">Function Documentation Library</xref>. This article handles some of the highlights and main
    uses for this module.</p>
        <section id="manipulating-database-contents">
            <title>Manipulating Database Contents</title>
    

    <p>The xmldb functions can be used to create new database collections or documents. </p>
    <p>To illustrate this, suppose we have a large file containing several RDF metadata records,
      but, since our application expects each record to have its own document, we do not want to
      store the metadata records in a single file. SO we have to divide the document into smaller
      units. This can be done by the following XQuery:</p>
    <pre outputclass="xquery">xquery version "3.0";

declare namespace rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#";

import module namespace xmldb="http://exist-db.org/xquery/xmldb";

let $log-in := xmldb:login("/db", "admin", "")
let $create-collection := xmldb:create-collection("/db", "output")
for $record in doc('/db/records.rdf')/rdf:RDF/*
let $split-record := 
    &lt;rdf:RDF xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"&gt;
        {$record}
    &lt;/rdf:RDF&gt;
let $about := $record/@rdf:about
let $filename := util:hash($record/@rdf:about/string(), "md5") || ".xml"
return
    xmldb:store("/db/output", $filename, $split-record)</pre>
    <p>Let's look at this example in some detail: </p>
    <ul>
                <li>
        <p>First, since we are using functions <ph>xmldb:create-collection()</ph> and
          <ph>xmldb:store()</ph>, which require the user to be logged in as a member of the
          <ph>dba</ph> group, we must log in using <ph>xmldb:login()</ph>. </p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Once logged in, we can create a new sub-collection <ph>output</ph> using
          <ph>xmldb:create-collection()</ph>.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>The <ph>for</ph>-loop iterates over all child elements of the top RDF
          element.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p> In each iteration, we use <ph>xmldb:store()</ph> to write the current child
          node to a new document. </p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <p>Since a unique document name is required, we need a way to generate unique names. The
          URI contained in the <ph>rdf:about</ph> attribute is unique, so we compute an
          MD5 key from it, append <ph>.xml</ph>, and use this as the document's name.</p>
      </li>
            </ul>

  </section>
        <section id="specifying-document-sets">
            <title>Specifying the Input Document Set</title>
    

    <p>A database can contain a virtually unlimited set of collections and documents. Four
      functions are available to restrict the input document set to a user-defined set of documents
      or collections: <ph>doc()</ph>, <ph>collection()</ph>,
      <ph>xmldb:document()</ph>, and <ph>xmldb:xcollection()</ph>. The first two
      are standard XPath functions, the others eXist-db specific extensions.</p>
    <p>The differences between the XPath and the eXist-db specific functions are:</p>
    <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                    <ph>doc()</ph> vs. <ph>xmldb:document()</ph>
                </dt>
                    <dd>
          <p>While <ph>doc()</ph> is restricted to a single document-URI argument,
            <ph>xmldb:document()</ph> accepts multiple document paths to be included into
            the input node set. </p>
          <p>Calling <ph>xmldb:document()</ph> without an argument includes
            <i>every</i> document in the database. </p>
          <p>Some examples:</p>
          <pre>doc("/db/apps/demo/data/hamlet.xml")//SPEAKER</pre>
          <pre>xmldb:document('/db/test/abc.xml', '/db/test/def.xml')//title</pre>
        </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                    <ph>collection()</ph> vs. <ph>xmldb:xcollection()</ph>
                </dt>
                    <dd>
          <p>The <ph>collection()</ph> function specifies the collection of documents
            to be included in the query evaluation. By default, documents found in sub-collections
            of the specified collection are also included.</p>
          <p>For example, suppose we have a collection <ph>/db/test</ph> that contains
            two sub-collections <ph>/db/test/abc</ph> and <ph>/db/test/def</ph>.
            In this case, the function call <ph>collection('/db/test')</ph> will include
            all of the resources found in <ph>/db/test</ph>,
            <ph>/db/test/abc</ph> and <ph>/db/test/def</ph>.</p>
          <p>The function <ph>xmldb:xcollection()</ph> does not include
            sub-collections. </p>
        </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>

    <p>Without an URI scheme in front (like <ph>file:</ph> or <ph>http:</ph>), eXist-db
      interprets the arguments to <ph>collection()</ph> and <ph>doc()</ph> as
      absolute or relative paths, leading to some collection or document within the database. For
      example:</p>
    <ul>
                <li>
        <pre>doc("/db/collection1/collection2/resource.xml")</pre>
        <p>This refers to a resource called <ph>resource.xml</ph> stored in
          <ph>/db/collection1/collection2</ph>.</p>
      </li>
                <li>
        <pre>doc("resource.xml")</pre>
        <p>This references a resource relative to the base URI property defined in the static
          XQuery context. This contains an XML:DB URI pointing to the <i>base
          collection</i> (see below) for the current query context, for instance
          <ph>xmldb:exist:///db</ph>.</p>
      </li>
            </ul>

    <p>The base collection depends on how the query context was initialized. If you call a query
      via the XML:DB API, the base collection is the collection from which the query service was
      obtained. All relative URLs will be resolved relative to that collection. If a stored query is
      executed via REST, the base collection is the collection in which the XQuery source resides.
      In most other cases, the base collection will point to the database root <ph>/db</ph>. </p>
    <note type="note">
                <p>As it might not always be clear what the base collection is, we recommend to always use
        absolute paths. This allows using the query with different interfaces.</p>
            </note>
    <p>You can also pass a full URI to the <ph>doc()</ph> function:</p>
    <pre>doc("http://localhost:8080/exist/servlet/db/test.xml")</pre>
    <p>The data on URI will be retrieved and stored in a temporary document in the
      database.</p>

  </section>
    </body>
</topic>