<topic id="templating">
    <title>HTML Templating Module</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="3Q25"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>The HTML templating framework makes creating XQuery applications that produce HTML pages
        more easy.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>The main goal of the HTML templating framework is a clean separation of concerns.
            Generating entire pages in XQuery is quick and dirty, but makes maintenance and code
            sharing difficult. Ideally, people should be able to look at the HTML view of an
            application and modify its look and feel without knowing XQuery. The application logic,
            written in XQuery, should be kept separate. Likewise, the XQuery developer should only
            have to deal with the minimal amount of HTML (generated dynamically).</p>
        <p>
            The templating module also handles most of the HTTP processing an application
            requires. It does so using sophisticated features like automatic parameter injection and
            type conversion. The goal was to remove repeating code like:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $query := request:get-parameter("query", ())
let $field := request:get-parameter("field", ())
...</pre>
        <p>In fact you should not see many calls to the HTTP request or session module inside a
            templating function. This is all handled by parameter injection. </p>
        <note type="note">
                <p>Working examples for the templating module can be found in the <xref href="{demo}/examples/templating/templates.html" scope="external">demo
                application</xref>.</p>
            </note>
    </section>
        <section id="write-html">
            <title>Writing the HTML</title>
        

        <p>
            The templating module is based mainly on conventions. Wherever possible it tries to
            make a best guess instead of requiring additional code or annotations. This works as
            long as the conventions used are sufficiently clear.
        </p>
        <p>
            The input for the templating framework is always a plain HTML file. The module scans
            the HTML view for elements with <ph>data-template</ph> attributes 
            following a simple convention and tries to translate them into XQuery
            function calls. By using <ph>data-*</ph> attributes, the HTML remains sufficiently clean and does
            not get messed up with application code. A web designer could take the HTML files and
            work on it without being bothered by the extra class names.
        </p>
        <p>
            To start with the usual "Hello world" example:
        </p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;div data-template="demo:hello" data-template-language="de"/&gt;</pre>

        <p>
            When the module encounters <ph>data-template="demo:hello"</ph>, it will try to find a function named
            <ph>demo:hello</ph> in all the modules known within the current XQuery context. If a function is found and its signature
            follows a certain convention, it will be called and the <ph>div</ph> will
            either be replaced or enhanced by whatever the function returns.</p>

        <p>
            The <ph>data-template</ph> attribute must follow the function naming pattern.
            It is also possible to pass static parameters to a template call.
            Additional parameters go into one or more attributes
            <ph>data-template-*</ph>, where the * should be replace by the name of the parameter, 
            e.g. <ph>data-template-path="menu.html"</ph>.
        </p>
        <section id="legacy-template-syntax">
                <title>Legacy Template Syntax</title>
            
            <p>
                You might encounter older templates that use the class attribute to call template functions.
                Like <ph>&lt;title class="app:title" /&gt;</ph>
            </p>
            <p>
                This is considered <i>legacy</i> syntax and should be re-written to use <ph>data-template</ph>
                attributes instead.
            </p>
            <p>
                In fact, version 1.1.0 introduced a configuration option <ph>$templates:CONFIG_USE_CLASS_SYNTAX</ph>.
                Setting it to <ph>false()</ph> will cause all class attributes to be ignored when reading
                template files. This is necessary in order to use colons in class names, which some CSS frameworks tend to do.
                This option will likely be <i>turned on by default</i> with the next major release of this library.
            </p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="templating">
            <title>Templating Functions</title>
        

        <p>
            A templating function is an ordinary XQuery function in a module. It <i>must</i> accept at least 
            two parameters, <ph>$node</ph> and <ph>$model</ph>.
            Additional parameters are allowed. If a function does not follow this convention it will be
            ignored by the framework.
        </p>
        <p>
            For example, our "Hello world!" function could be defined as follows:
        </p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare function demo:hello($node as node(), $model as map(*), $language as xs:string, $user as xs:string) as element(div) {
    &lt;div&gt;
    {
        switch($language)
            case "de" return
                "Hallo " || $user
            case "it" return
                "Ciao " || $user
            default return
                "Hello " || $user
    }
    &lt;/div&gt;
};</pre>
        <p>The two required parameters are <ph>$node</ph> and <ph>$model</ph>: </p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p> <ph>$node</ph> contains the HTML node currently being processed: in this
                    case, the <ph>div</ph> element. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>
                        <ph>$model</ph> is an XQuery map with application data. It will be empty
                    for now, but we'll see later why it is important.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>

    </section>
        <section id="parameter">
            <title>Parameter Injection and Type Conversion</title>
        

        <p>The additional parameters in the example above, <ph>$language</ph> and
            <ph>$user</ph>, will be injected automatically. The templating framework tries to
            make a best guess how to fill those parameters with values. It checks the following 3
            contexts for parameters with the same name (in the order below):</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>if the current <i>HTTP request</i> contains a (non-empty)
                    parameter with the same name as the parameter variable, this is used to set the
                    value of the variable</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>if the <i>HTTP session</i> contains an attribute with the same
                    name as the parameter variable, this is used to set the value of the
                    variable</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>if the <i>static parameters</i> passed to the template call
                    contain a parameter matching the variable name, it will be used</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>If neither 1 nor 2 lead to a non-empty value, the function signature will be checked
            for an annotation <ph>%templates:default("name", "value1", ..., "valueN")</ph>. See
            below.</p>
        <p>If "language" is passed as a parameter in the HTTP request, it will overwrite the
            static parameter we provided because the HTTP request is checked first. </p>
        <p>The templating framework will also attempt automatic type conversion for all
            parameters. If the parameter has a declared type of <ph>xs:integer</ph>, it will try
            to cast a parameter it finds into an integer. If the type is <ph>node()</ph>, the
            parameter value will be parsed into XML. These conversions may fail and this results in
            an error passing a parameter with the wrong type.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="annotations">
            <title>Additional Annotations</title>
        

        <p>Our "Hello world" example above does not preserve the div from which it was called,
            but replaces it with a new one which lacks the "grey-box" class. This is the default
            behavior. To preserve the enclosing div, we should add the XQuery annotation
            <ph>%templates:wrap</ph> to the function signature.</p>
        <p>Another annotation can be used to provide a default value for a parameter:
            <ph>%templates:default("parameter", "value1", "value2", ...)</ph>. The first
            parameter of the annotation must match the name of the parameter variable. All other
            parameters in the annotation are used as values for the variable. </p>
        <p>For example, set <ph>$language</ph> to <ph>en</ph> if the value cannot be
            determined otherwise:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare 
    %templates:wrap %templates:default("language", "en")
function demo:hello($node as node(), $model as map(*), $language as xs:string, $user as xs:string) as xs:string {
    switch($language)
        case "de" return
            "Hallo " || $user
        case "it" return
            "Ciao " || $user
        default return
            "Hello " || $user
};</pre>
        <p>Because of the <ph>%templates:wrap</ph> we can now remove the wrapping
            <ph>div</ph> in the function and just return a string now. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="model">
            <title>Using the Model to Keep Application Data</title>
        

        <p>In a more complex application, a view will have many templating functions which all
            access the same data. For example, take a typical search page: there might be one HTML
            element to display the number of hits, one to show the query, and another one for
            printing out the results. All those components need to access the search result. How to
            do this in a templating framework?</p>
        <p>This is where the <ph>$model</ph> parameter comes into play. It is passed to all
            template functions and they can add data to it. This is available to nested template
            calls. </p>
        <p>For example a search page:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;div data-template="demo:search"&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Found
    &lt;span data-template="demo:hit-count"/&gt;
    hits
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul data-template="demo:result-list"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</pre>
        <p> The <ph>demo:hit-count</ph> and <ph>demo:result-list</ph> occur inside the
            <ph>div</ph> calling <ph>demo:search</ph>. They are <i>nested</i>
            template calls. <ph>demo:search</ph> will perform the actual search operation, based
            on the parameters passed by the user. Instead of directly printing the search result in
            HTML, it delegates this to the nested templates.</p>
        <p> <ph>demo:search</ph> can be implemented as: </p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare
    %templates:wrap
function demo:search($node as node(), $model as map(*), $query as xs:string) as map(*) {
    let $result :=
        for $hit in collection($config:app-root)//SCENE[ft:query(., $query)]
        order by ft:score($hit) descending
        return $hit
    return
        map { "result": $result }
};
</pre>
        <p> <ph>demo:search</ph> differs from the functions we have seen so far in that it
            returns an XQuery map and not HTML or some atomic type. If a templating function returns
            a map, the templating framework will proceed as follows:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Add the returned map to the current <ph>$model</ph> map (adding it to the
                    map keeps entries produced by any ancestor templates)</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>resume processing the children of the current HTML node</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>The <ph>demo:hit-count</ph> can now access the query results in
            <ph>$model</ph>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">declare function demo:hit-count($node as node(), $model as map(*)) as xs:integer {
    count($model("result"))
};</pre>

        

        <section id="manual-processing">
                <title>Manual Processing Control</title>
            

            <p>Inside a templating function, you can also call <ph>templates:process($nodes as
                node()*, $model as map(*))</ph> to have the templating module process the given
                node sequence. </p>
            <note type="warning">
                    <p>You need to make sure you are not running into an endless loop by calling
                    <ph>templates:process</ph> on the currently processed node.</p>
                </note>
            <p> A common pattern is to trigger <ph>templates:process</ph> on the children of
                the current node:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">templates:process($node/node(), $model)</pre>
            <p>This is comparable to calling <ph>xsl:apply-templates</ph> in XSLT and will have
                the same effect as returning a map (see the section above), but with your templating
                function having full control.</p>
            <p>For example, it is sometimes necessary to first process all the descendant nodes
                of the current element, then apply some action to the processed tree. The
                documentation app has a function, <ph>config:expand-links</ph>, which scans the
                final document tree for links and expands them. The function is implemented as
                follows:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">declare %templates:wrap function config:expand-links($node as node(), $model as map(*), $base as xs:string?) {
    for $node in templates:process($node/node(), $model)
    return
        config:expand-links($node, $base)
};</pre>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="set-up">
            <title>Set-Up</title>
        
        
        <p>The templating module is entirely implemented in XQuery. It provides a single public
            function, <ph>templates:apply</ph>.</p>
        
        <section id="deprecation">
                <title>Important Note</title>
            
            <p>The old version of the templating module used to be part of the <i>deprecated</i>
                shared-resources package, while a <xref href="https://github.com/eXist-db/templating/" scope="external">new and improved version</xref> 
                is now available as its own expath library package. We recommend to update to the new package with the short name
                <i>templating</i>, available on the eXist-db dashboard. To update, follow the 3 steps below:</p>
            <ol>
                    <li>
                    <p>change any dependency on shared-resources in your expath-pkg.xml to point to this package:</p>
                    <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;dependency package="http://exist-db.org/html-templating"/&gt;</pre>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>update the module URI for any imports of the templating module:</p>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace templates="http://exist-db.org/xquery/html-templating";</pre>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                        New standard templating functions will go into a separate module, so you may want to add the following import
                        in addition to the one above, which will give you access to the lib:parse-params template function (and others in the future):
                    </p>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace lib="http://exist-db.org/xquery/html-templating/lib";</pre>
                </li>
                </ol>
        </section>
        <section id="main-xquery">
                <title>Calling the Templating from a Main XQuery</title>
            
            <p>
                A complete main module which calls the templating framework to process an HTML file passed
                in the HTTP request body could look as follows:
            </p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">(:~
 : This is the main XQuery which will (by default) be called by controller.xq
 : to process any URI ending with ".html". It receives the HTML from
 : the controller and passes it to the templating framework.
 :)
xquery version "3.0";

declare namespace output="http://www.w3.org/2010/xslt-xquery-serialization";

import module namespace templates="http://exist-db.org/xquery/html-templating";

(: 
 : The following modules provide functions which will be called by the 
 : templating framework.
 :)
import module namespace app="http://my.domain/myapp" at "app.xql";

declare option output:method "html";
declare option output:html-version "5.0";
declare option output:media-type "text/html";

(:
 : We have to provide a lookup function to templates:apply to help it
 : find functions in the imported application modules. The templates
 : module cannot see the application modules, but the inline function
 : below does see them.
 :)
declare variable $lookup := function($functionName as xs:string, $arity as xs:integer) as function(*)? {
    function-lookup(xs:QName($functionName), $arity)
}

(:
 : The HTML is passed in the request from the controller.
 : Run it through the templating framework and return the result.
 :)
templates:apply(
    request:get-data(),
    $lookup,
    () (: the third parameter is the initial model :)
)
</pre>
            <p>This module can now be called from the URL rewriting controller. For example, we can
                add a rule to <ph>controller.xq</ph> to pass any .html resource to the above
                main query (saved to <ph>modules/view.xq</ph>):</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">(: Pass all requests to HTML files through view.xq, which handles HTML templating :)
if (ends-with($exist:resource, ".html")) then (
    &lt;dispatch xmlns="http://exist.sourceforge.net/NS/exist"&gt;
        &lt;view&gt;
        &lt;forward url="{$exist:controller}/modules/view.xq"&gt;
                &lt;set-attribute name="$exist:prefix" value="{$exist:prefix}"/&gt;
                &lt;set-attribute name="$exist:controller" value="{$exist:controller}"/&gt;
            &lt;/forward&gt;
        &lt;/view&gt;
        &lt;error-handler&gt;
            &lt;forward url="{$exist:controller}/error-page.html" method="get"/&gt;
            &lt;forward url="{$exist:controller}/modules/view.xq"/&gt;
        &lt;/error-handler&gt;
    &lt;/dispatch&gt;
) else (
    (: do something with all other requests :)
)
</pre>
            <p>
                The only part of the main module code which might look a bit unusual is the inline
                lookup function: the templating module uses dynamic function calls to execute template
                functions in application modules. But unfortunately, XQuery modules can only "see"
                functions in their own context. There is therefore no way for the templating module to
                determine what functions are defined in application modules which are outside its
                context. So it needs to be "helped" by providing a callback function to resolve function
                references. The lookup function is defined in the main context and can access all the
                modules imported into the main module.
            </p>
            <p>
                Normally you can just copy and paste the main module code as given above. To adapt it
                to your own application, just import your application modules and you're done.
            </p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="pre-defined-commands">
            <title>Pre-defined Template Commands</title>
        

        <p>The templating module defines a number of general-purpose templating functions which
            are described below. Functions marked as <i>deprecated</i> should not be used
            anymore. Those labelled with <i>removed</i> did exist in the old templating
            module (which was shipped in the shared-resources package) and has been removed from the newer
            templating package.</p>
        <p>Functions marked as <i>new</i> have been added in the new templating package
            and are not available in the older module.</p>

        

        <section id="include">
                <title>templates:include (deprecated)</title>
            

            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>path</stentry>
                        <stentry>path to the resources</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Includes the content of the resource given by parameter <ph>path</ph> into the current
                element. <ph>path</ph> is always interpreted relative to the current application
                directory or collection.</p>
        </section>
        
        
        
        <section id="lib_include">
                <title>lib:include (new)</title>
            
            
            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>path</stentry>
                        <stentry>path to the resources</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Includes the content of the resource given by <ph>path</ph> into the current
                element. <ph>path</ph> is always interpreted relative to the current application
                directory or collection.</p>
            <p>The children (if any) of the including element (i.e. the one triggering the lib:include function)
                are merged into the included content. To define where a child element should be
                inserted, you must use a @data-target attribute referencing an HTML id which must exist
                within the included fragment. If @data-target is missing, the element will be discarded.</p> 
            <p>This is a mechanism to inject content from the including element into the included content. For example, if the same menu
                or toolbar is included into every page of an application, but some pages should have
                additional options, you can use lib:include with lib:block to define the additional HTML
                to be inserted in a specific place.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="each">
                <title>templates:each</title>
            

            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>from</stentry>
                        <stentry>references a property in the model map which should be used as the source sequence to iterate</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>to</stentry>
                        <stentry>the name of the property to be added to the model map. This will contain the current iteration item.</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Retrieve the sequence identified by the map key <ph>from</ph> in the
                <ph>$model</ph> map. If it exists, iterate over the items in its value (as a
                sequence) and process any nested content once. During each iteration, the current
                item is added to the <ph>$model</ph> map using the key
                <ph>to</ph>.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="if-set">
                <title>templates:if-parameter-set</title>
            

            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>name</stentry>
                        <stentry>name of the parameter to check</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Conditionally includes content only if the given request parameter is set and not
                empty.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="if-unset">
                <title>templates:if-parameter-unset</title>
            

            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>param</stentry>
                        <stentry>name of the parameter to check</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Conditionally includes content only if the given request parameter is
                <i>not</i> set or empty.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="surround">
                <title>templates:surround (deprecated)</title>
            

            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Parameter</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>with</stentry>
                        <stentry>path to the resource which should be used as surrounding container</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>at</stentry>
                        <stentry>id of the HTML element which should be surrounded</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>using</stentry>
                        <stentry>(optional) id of an HTML element in the resource specified by with. If specified,
                            only this element will be used as surrounding container - not the entire document.</stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
            <p>Surrounds its content with the contents of the XML resource specified in
                <ph>with</ph>. The <ph>at</ph> parameter determines where the content is
                inserted into the surrounding XML. It should match an existing HTML <ph>id</ph>
                in the template.</p>
            <p>The <ph>using</ph> parameter is optional and specifies the <ph>id</ph> of
                an element in the <ph>with</ph> resource. The current content will be surrounded
                by this element. If this parameter is missing, the entire document given in
                <ph>with</ph> will be used.</p>
            <p>The surround template instruction is used by all pages of the <xref href="{demo}/index.html" scope="external">Demo</xref> application. The header, basic page
                structure and menus are the same for all pages. Each page only contains a simple
                <ph>div</ph> with a template instruction:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">templates:surround?with=templates/page.html&amp;at=content</pre>
            <p>The instruction takes the content of the current element and injects it into the
                template page.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="form-control">
                <title>templates:form-control</title>
            

            <pre outputclass="xquery">templates:form-control</pre>
            <p>Use on <ph>input</ph> and <ph>select</ph> elements: checks the HTTP request
                for a parameter matching the name of the form control and fills it into the value of
                an input or selects the corresponding option of a select.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="load-source">
                <title>templates:load-source (removed)</title>
            

            <pre outputclass="xquery">templates:load-source</pre>
            <p>Commonly used with an <ph>a</ph> element: opens the document referenced in the
                <ph>href</ph> attribute in eXide.</p>
        </section>
        
        
        
        <section id="parse-params">
                <title>lib:parse-params (new)</title>
            
            
            <p>Recursively expand template expressions appearing in attributes or text content,
                trying to expand them from request/session parameters or the current model.</p>
                
            <p>Template expressions should have the form <ph>${paramName:default text}</ph>.
                Specifying a default is optional. If there is no default and the parameter
                cannot be expanded, the empty string is output.</p>

            <p>To support navigating the map hierarchy of the model, paramName may be a sequence 
                of map keys separated by ?, i.e. <ph>${address?street}</ph> would first retrieve the map
                property called "address" and then look up the property "street" on it.</p>
                
            <p>The templating function should fail gracefully if a parameter or map lookup cannot
                be resolved, a lookup resolves to multiple items, a map or an array.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>