<topic id="indexing">
    <title>Configuring Database Indexes</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q21"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>In this article we discuss the types of database indexes used by eXist-db and how they are
        created, configured and maintained. It assumes readers have a basic understanding of XML and
        XQuery.</p>
        <section id="overview">
            <title>Overview</title>
        


        <p>Database indexes are used extensively by eXist-db to facilitate efficient querying of
            the database. This is accomplished both by system-generated and user-configured database
            indexes. The current (3.x) version of eXist-db by default includes the following types
            of indexes:</p>
        <note type="note">
                <p>Properly configured indexes have a huge impact on database performance! Some
                expressions might run a hundred times faster with an index. This particulary applies
                to the range index: without a range index, eXist has to do a full scan over the
                context nodes to look up an element value, which severly limits performance and
                scalability.</p>
            </note>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="#structuralidx" scope="external">Structural Indexes</xref>
                    </i>: This index keeps track of the elements, attributes, and the nodal
                    structure of all XML documents in a collection. It is created and maintained
                    automatically. No configuration required.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> xml:id Index </i>: An index of all <ph>xml:id</ph>
                    attribute values is automatically created. These values can be queried by
                    <ph>fn:id()</ph>. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="newrangeindex" scope="external">New Range Indexes</xref>
                    </i>: A (rewritten) range index which provides superior performance on
                    large data sets.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="lucene" scope="external">Full Text Indexes</xref>
                    </i>: This full text indexing module features faster and customizable
                    full text indexing by transparently integrating Lucene into the XQuery engine.
                </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="ngram" scope="external">NGram Indexes</xref> </i>:
                    These map specific text nodes and attributes of the documents in a collection to
                    splitted tokens of n-characters (where n = 3 by default). This is very efficient
                    for exact substring searches and for queries on scripts (mostly non-European
                    ones) which can not be easily split into whitespace separated tokens and are
                    therefore a bad match for the Lucene full text index. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="oldrangeindex" scope="external">Legacy Range Indexes</xref>
                    </i>: These map specific text nodes and attributes of documents in a
                    collection to typed values.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <i> <xref href="devguide_indexes#spatial" scope="external">Spatial
                    Indexes</xref> (Experimental)</i>: A working proof-of-concept index,
                    which listens for spatial geometries described through the Geography Markup
                    Language (GML). A detailed description of the implementation can be found in the
                    <xref href="devguide_indexes#spatial" scope="external">Developer's Guide to Modularized
                    Indexes</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>eXist-db features a modularized indexing architecture. Most types of indexes have been
            moved out of the database core and are maintained as pluggable extensions. The full
            text, the ngram, the spatial and the new range indexes fall under this category. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="idxconf">
            <title>Configuring Indexes</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db has no "create index" command. Instead, indexes are configured in
            collection-specific configuration files. These files are stored as standard XML
            documents in the system collection <ph>/db/system/config</ph>, which can be
            accessed like any other document (e.g. using the Admin interface or <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Client</xref>). In addition to defining settings for
            indexing collections, the configuration document specifies other collection-specific
            settings such as triggers or default permissions.</p>
        <p>The contents of the system collection (<ph>/db/system/config</ph>) should
            mirror the hierarchical structure of the main collection. Configurations are shared by
            descendants in the hierarchy unless they have their own configuration: the configuration
            settings for the child collection override those set for the parent. If no
            collection-specific configuration file is created for any document, the global settings
            in the main configuration file <ph>conf.xml</ph> will apply by default. The
            <ph>conf.xml</ph> file should only define the default global <i>index
            creation policy</i>.</p>
        <p> To configure a given collection, for instance <ph>/db/foo</ph>, create a
            file <ph>collection.xconf</ph> and store it as
            <ph>/db/system/config/db/foo/collection.xconf</ph>. Note the replication of
            the <ph>/db/foo</ph> hierarchy inside <ph>/db/system/config/</ph>.
            Sub-collections which do not have a <ph>collection.xconf</ph> file of their
            own will be governed by the configuration policy specified for the closest ancestor
            collection which does have such a file, so you are not required to specify a
            configuration for every collection. </p>
        <note type="notice">
                <p>Configuration settings <i>do not cascade</i>: a sub-collection with
                a <ph>collection.xconf</ph> will <i>not</i> inherit any
                settings from any ancestor collection that has a
                <ph>collection.xconf</ph>. If you choose to deploy a
                <ph>collection.xconf</ph> file in a sub-collection, you must specify in
                that file <i>all</i> the configuration options you wish to have
                applied to that sub-collection (and any sub-collections without
                <ph>collection.xconf</ph> files of their own). </p>
            </note>

        

        <section id="maintaining">
                <title>Maintaining Indexes and Re-indexing</title>
            

            <p>The eXist-db index system automatically maintains and updates indexes defined by
                the user. You do not need to update an index when you update a database document or
                collection. eXist-db will even update indexes following partial document updates via
                <i>XUpdate</i> or <i>XQuery Update</i>
                expressions.</p>
            <p>The only exception to eXist-db's automatic update occurs when you <i>add a
                new index definition to an existing database collection</i>. In this case,
                the new index settings will <i>only</i> apply to new data added to
                this collection (or any of its sub-collections) and <i>not</i> to
                previously existing data. To apply the new settings to the entire collection, you
                need to trigger a "manual reindex" of the collection being updated.</p>
            <p>You can re-index collections using the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java
                Admin Client</xref>. From the Admin menu, select <ph>File, Reindex
                Collection</ph>. </p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/client4.png" width="50%"/>
                </fig>

            <p>You can also index by passing the following XQuery to eXist-db:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">xmldb:reindex('/db/foo')</pre>

        </section>

        

        <section id="general-config">
                <title>General Configuration Structure and Syntax</title>
            

            <p>Index configuration <ph>collection.xconf</ph> files are standard XML
                documents that have their elements and attributes defined by the eXist-db namespace
                <ph>http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0</ph>. The following example shows
                a configuration example:</p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index&gt;
    &lt;!-- Full text index based on Lucene --&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;text qname="SPEECH"&gt;
        &lt;ignore qname="SPEAKER"/&gt;
      &lt;/text&gt;
      &lt;text qname="TITLE"/&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
    &lt;!-- Range indexes --&gt;
    &lt;range&gt;
      &lt;create qname="title" type="xs:string"/&gt;
      &lt;create qname="author" type="xs:string"/&gt;
      &lt;create qname="year" type="xs:integer"/&gt;
    &lt;/range&gt;
    &lt;!-- N-gram indexes --&gt;
    &lt;ngram qname="author"/&gt;
    &lt;ngram qname="title"/&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            <p>All configuration documents have an <ph>index</ph> element directly below the
                root element. This encloses the index configuration. Only <i>one</i>
                <ph>index</ph> element is permitted in a document. Apart from the index
                configuration, the document may also contain settings not related to indexing (e.g.
                for triggers). These will not be covered here. </p>
            <p>In the <ph>index</ph> element are elements that define the various index types.
                Each index type adds its own configuration elements, which are directly forwarded to
                the corresponding index implementation. The example above configures three different
                types of indexes: full text, range and ngram.</p>

            <p>If the document to be indexed uses namespaces, you should add a
                <ph>xmlns</ph> declaration for each of the required namespaces:</p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;text qname="atom:title"/&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
    &lt;range&gt;
      &lt;create qname="atom:id" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;/range&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            <p>The example configuration above creates two indexes on a collection of atom
                documents. The two elements which should be indexed are both in the
                <ph>atom</ph> namespace and we therefore need to declare a mapping for
                this namespace. Here, the namespace mapping is placed on the <ph>index</ph> 
                element, but it can appear anywhere in the configuration document.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="check-usage">
            <title>Check Index Usage</title>
        

        <p>The quickest way to see if an index was used or not is to go to the
            <ph>Profiling</ph> menu item in the <xref href="{monex}" scope="external">Monex
            Monitoring and Profiling application</xref>.</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Click on <ph>Enable Tracing</ph> to enable usage statistics.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Run the query you would like to profile. The profiler will collect statistics
                    about any query running on the database instance, no matter how the query is
                    called.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Click <ph>Refresh</ph> and switch to the <ph>Index
                    Usage</ph> tab.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <fig>
                <image href="assets/IndexProfiling.png"/>
            </fig>
        <p>The table provides the following information:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Source</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The query containing the expression. The line/column of the expression is
                        given in brackets. For queries stored in the database, the file name will be
                        shown. Dynamically executed queries are displayed with the name
                        "String".</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Index</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Type of the index used: "range" for the old range index, "new-range" for
                        the new range index, "lucene" for the full text index.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Optimization</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <dl>
                            <dlentry>
                                <dt>Full</dt>
                                <dd>
                                <p>The expression was rewritten by the optimizer to make full use
                                    of the index. This is the best you can achieve.</p>
                            </dd>
                            </dlentry>
                            <dlentry>
                                <dt>Basic</dt>
                                <dd>
                                <p>The index was used, but the expression was not rewritten by
                                    the optimizer. This is better than "No index" but still several
                                    times slower than "Full". Most probably the context of the
                                    expression was too complex to rewrite it.</p>
                            </dd>
                            </dlentry>
                            <dlentry>
                                <dt>No index</dt>
                                <dd>
                                <p>No index defined. Expression is evaluated in "brute force"
                                    mode.</p>
                            </dd>
                            </dlentry>
                        </dl>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Calls</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The number of calls to the expression.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Elapsed time</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The time elapsed for all calls together. The time is measured for the
                        index lookup only. The absolute numbers are not reliable (due to measurement
                        errors), but they show a tendency: if a lookup takes relatively longer than
                        other expressions, it might be worth to optimize it with an index.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
    </section>
        <section id="moduleconf">
            <title>Enabling Index Modules</title>
        
        <p> To activate an index plug-in, it needs to be added to the <ph>modules</ph> section
            within the global configuration file <ph>conf.xml</ph>:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;modules&gt;
  &lt;module id="ngram-index" class="org.exist.indexing.ngram.NGramIndex" file="ngram.dbx" n="3"/&gt;
&lt;/modules&gt;</pre>

        <p>Every <ph>module</ph> element needs at least an <ph>id</ph> and
            <ph>class</ph> attribute. The class attribute contains the name of the plug-in
            class, which has to be an implementation of
            <ph>org.exist.indexing.Index</ph>.</p>
        <p>All other attributes or nested configuration elements below the <ph>module</ph>
            element are specific to the implementation and will differ between indexes. They should
            be documented by the index implementer.</p>
        <p>If an index implementation cannot be loaded from the specified class, the entry will
            simply be ignored. A warning will be written to the logs. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="structuralidx">
            <title>The Structural index</title>
        

        <p>This index keeps track of the elements (tags), attributes, and nodal structure for all
            XML documents in a collection. It is created and maintained automatically in eXist-db,
            and can neither be reconfigured nor disabled. The structural index is required for
            nearly all XPath and XQuery expressions in eXist-db (with the exception of wildcard-only
            expressions such as <ph>//*</ph>). This index is stored in the database file
            <ph>structure.dbx</ph>. </p>
        <p>Technically, the structural index maps every element and attribute
            <i>qname</i> (or <i>qualified name</i>) in a document
            collection to a list of <ph>documentId, nodeId</ph> pairs. This mapping is used by the
            query engine to resolve queries for a given XPath expression.</p>
        <p>For example:</p>
        <pre>//book/section</pre>
        <p>eXist-db uses two index lookups: the first for the <ph>book</ph> node, and the
            second for the <ph>section</ph> node. It then computes the <i>structural
            join</i> between these node sets to determine which <ph>section</ph> elements
            are in fact children of <ph>book</ph> elements.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>