<topic id="java-admin-client">
    <title>Java Admin Client</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db ships with the so-called "Java Admin Client". This application enables users to
        perform administrative tasks, such as user management, security settings, batch import of
        whole directories, and backup/restore of the database. It can be used either as a GUI or on
        the command line.</p>
        <section id="launching">
            <title>Launching the Client</title>
        

        <p>You can launch the Java Admin Client using one of the following methods:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>Windows and Linux users: Click the eXist-db icon in the taskbar and choose the
                    <ph>Open Java Admin Client</ph> menu entry.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Enter the following on your command line from the eXist installation directory
                    (with the <ph>JAVA_HOME</ph> environment variable set correctly):</p>
                <pre>bin\client.bat (DOS/Windows)</pre>
                <pre>bin/client.sh (Unix)</pre>
            </li>
            </ul>
    </section>
        <section id="gui">
            <title>Using the Graphical Client</title>
        

        <p>Once the Graphical Client is launched, you will see the "eXist Database Login"
            window.</p>
        <fig>
                <image href="assets/client1.png" width="75%"/>
            </fig>

        <p>The Java Admin Client can connect to a database in two ways:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>Most common is to connect to a "remote" server. The client talks with the
                    server using the XML RPC protocol.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>It can also launch an "enbedded database", that is, a database embedded in an
                    application which runs in the same process as the client. This embedded option
                    is useful for backup/restore or mass uploads of data; writing to an embedded
                    instance avoids the network overhead.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>



        <p>To connect to a remote server, enter your eXist-db username and password, select
            <ph>Remote</ph> from the <ph>Type</ph> dropdown
            menu, and in the URL field enter the database's URI. This by default set to
            <ph>xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</ph> (the URI for a database installed
            with all the default settings).</p>
        <p>After clicking <ph>OK</ph>, the main client window will open.</p>
        <fig>
                <image href="assets/client2.png"/>
            </fig>
        <p>This window is split into two panels. The top panel lists the database collections.
            The bottom panel acts like a shell and has a command prompt. This shell allows you to
            manually enter database commands.</p>
        <p>Using the Java Admin Client as a GUI is like using any other GUI application. That is
            why we do not explain it further.</p>

        <note type="warning">
                <p>If eXist-db is online, you expose it to exploitation if you use an empty admin
                password. If you did not specify an admin password during installation, you are
                strongly advised to set an admin password as soon as possible. You can do this in
                the Java Admin Client:</p>
                <ol>
                    <li>
                    <p>Open the <ph>Edit Users</ph> window by selecting the
                        <ph>Manage Users</ph> icon (image of a pair of keys) in
                        the toolbar</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>At the top, select the <ph>admin</ph> user in the table
                        of users</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Type in the new password into the password fields</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Click the <ph>Modify User</ph> button to apply the
                        changes</p>
                </li>
                </ol>
            </note>
    </section>
        <section id="command-line">
            <title>Using the Command-line Client</title>
        

        <p>It is sometimes faster or more convenient to use the Java Admin Client on the command
            line. The following sections provide a quick introduction to the most common command
            line parameters and their use. The client offers three modes of operation:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>If an action is specified on the command-line (when starting the client), it
                    will be processed in non-interactive mode and the client will terminate after
                    completion.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>If option <ph>-s</ph> or <ph>--no-gui</ph> is specified
                    without an action, the client switches to interactive shell-mode and prompts for
                    user input. No graphical interface is displayed.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Otherwise the client switches to interactive mode and displays the graphical
                    user interface.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>

        

        <section id="shell">
                <title>Interactive Shell Mode</title>
            

            <p>While this tutorial will not describe the interactive shell mode in detail, most
                commands work like their counterparts specified on the command line. On the shell,
                just type <ph>help</ph> to get a list of supported commands.</p>
            <p>The shell mode may support full command line history and command completion,
                depending on the OS</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p> On Unix systems, the client will try to load the GNU
                        <ph>readline</ph> library, which is part of most Unix installations.
                        This gives you access to all the nice things you probably know from Linux
                        shells. For example, pressing the tab-key will try to complete collection
                        and document names. However, for this to work, the native library
                        <ph>lib/core/libJavaReadline.so</ph> has to be found by the
                        system's loader. On Linux, just add <ph>lib/core</ph> to your
                        <ph>LD_LIBRARY_PATH</ph> (the client.sh script does this
                        automatically).</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>On Windows OS, you should at least be able to use the
                        cursor-up/cursor-down keys to browse through the command history.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>




            <p>To explain the shell-mode we provide a short example, showing how to store the
                sample files into the database.</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Typing <ph>mkcol shakespeare</ph> and pressing enter will create
                        a Shakespeare collection into which we will put some of the sample documents
                        provided with eXist-db.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>To check if the new collection is present, enter <ph>ls</ph> to
                        get a listing of the current collection contents. The listing below shows an
                        example session of how to add the sample documents:</p>
                    <pre>exist:/db&gt;mkcol shakespeare
created collection.
exist:/db&gt;cd shakespeare
exist:/db/shakespeare&gt;mkcol plays
created collection.
exist:/db/shakespeare&gt;cd plays
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays&gt;put samples/shakespeare/
storing document hamlet.xml (1 of 4) ...done.
storing document much_ado.xml (2 of 4) ...done.
storing document r_and_j.xml (3 of 4) ...done.
storing document shakes.xsl (4 of 4) ...done.
exist:/db/shakespeare/plays&gt; cd
exist:/db&gt;mkcol library
created collection.
exist:/db&gt;cd library
exist:/db/library&gt;put samples/biblio.rdf
storing document biblio.rdf (1 of 1) ...done.
exist:/db/library&gt;cd
exist:/db&gt;mkcol xinclude
created collection.
exist:/db&gt;cd xinclude
exist:/db/xinclude&gt;put samples/xinclude</pre>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Adding files to the database is done using <ph>put</ph>. This expects
                        either a single file, a file-pattern or a directory name as argument. If a
                        directory is specified, all XML and XSL files in that directory will be put
                        into the database. </p>
                    <p>To add the files in directory <ph>samples/shakespeare</ph> simply
                        enter <ph>put samples/shakespeare</ph>. </p>
                    <p> <ph>put</ph> also accepts file-patterns, i.e. a path with
                        wildcards <ph>?</ph> or <ph>*</ph>. <ph>**</ph> means: any
                        sub-directory. So the command <ph>put samples/**/*.xml</ph> will
                        parse any XML files found in the <ph>samples</ph> directory and
                        any of its sub-directories.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>To see if the files have actually been stored use <ph>ls</ph>
                        again.</p>
                    <p/>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>To view a document, use the get command, for instance <ph>get
                        hamlet.xml</ph> </p>
                </li>
                </ul>

            <note type="note">
                    <p>If you ever run into problems while experimenting with eXist-db and your
                    database files get corrupt: just remove the data files created by eXist-db and
                    everything should work again. The data files all end with
                        <ph>.dbx</ph>. You will find them in directory
                        <ph>$EXIST_HOME/data</ph>. It is ok to backup those data-files to
                    be able to restore them in case of a database corruption.</p>
                </note>
        </section>

        

        <section id="param">
                <title>Specifying Parameters</title>
            

            <p>The client uses the CLI library from Apache's Excalibur project to parse
                command-line parameters. This means that the same conventions apply as for most GNU
                tools. Most parameters have a short and a long form. </p>
            <p>For example, the user can be specified in short with <ph>-u user</ph> or
                in long with <ph>--user=user</ph>. You can combine argument-less
                parameters: for example, <ph>-ls</ph> is short for <ph>-l
                -s</ph>.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="conf">
                <title>General Configuration</title>
            

            <p>The client reads its default options from the properties file
                <ph>client.properties</ph>. Most of the properties can be overwritten by
                command-line parameters or by the <ph>set</ph> command in
                shell-mode.</p>
            <p>The client relies on the XML:DB API to communicate with the database. It will
                therefore work with remote as well as embedded database instances. The correct
                database instance is determined through the XML:DB base URI as specified in the
                properties file or through command-line options. The <xref href="deployment" scope="external">deployment</xref> article describes how different
                servers are addressed using the XML:DB URI.</p>
            <p>The XML:DB base URI used by the client for connections is defined by the
                <ph>uri=</ph> property. By default, this is set to
                <ph>uri=xmldb:exist://localhost:8080/exist/xmlrpc</ph>. With this, the
                client will try to connect to a database instance running inside the webserver at
                port 8080 of the local host. </p>
            <p>There are several ways to specify an alternate XML:DB base URI: </p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Change the <ph>uri=</ph> property in
                        <ph>client.properties</ph> </p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Use the <ph>-ouri</ph> parameter on the command-line</p>
                    <p>For instance, to access a server running inside the Jetty webserver at
                        port <ph>8080</ph> on a remote host, use</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -ouri=xmldb:exist://host:8080/exist/xmlrpc</pre>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>To start the client in <i>local</i> mode, use:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -ouri=xmldb:exist://</pre>
                    <p> Local mode means that an embedded database instance will be initialized
                        and started by the client. It will have direct access to the database
                        instance. Use this option if you want to batch-load a large document or a
                        huge collection of documents.</p>
                    <p>Since switching to local mode is required quite often, there's also a
                        shortcut: </p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -l</pre>
                    <p>This is equivalent to the <ph>-ouri=xmldb:exist://</ph> option
                        shown above.</p>
                    <p>When launching the client with option <ph>-l</ph> or
                            <ph>-ouri=xmldb:exist://</ph> the configuration for the
                        database instance is read from <ph>conf.xml</ph> located in
                            <ph>$EXIST_HOME/etc</ph>.</p>
                    <p>Use the <ph>-C</ph> parameter to specify an alternate database
                        location. For instance:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -C /home/exist/test/conf.xml</pre>
                    <p>This will temporarily launch a new database instance whose configuration
                        is read from the provided file. Option <ph>-C</ph> implies option
                        <ph>-l</ph>.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>

            <p>If you have set a password for the admin user you must to authenticate yourself to
                the database:</p>
            <pre>bin/client.sh -l -u username -P password</pre>
            <p>If the <ph>-P</ph> password option is missing, the client will prompt
                for the password.</p>
            <p>The graphical user interface will always prompt for username and password unless
                you specify both on the command-line.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="store">
                <title>Storing documents</title>
            

            <p>To store a set of documents, use the <ph>-m</ph> and
                <ph>-p</ph> parameters. For instance:</p>
            <pre>bin/client.sh -c /db/shakespeare/plays -m /db/shakespeare/plays -p /home/exist/xml/shakespeare</pre>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>The <ph>-m</ph> tells the client to implicitly create any
                        missing collection.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>The <ph>-p</ph> parameter means that all of the following
                        arguments should be interpreted as a list of paths to XML documents (you may
                        specify more than one document or directory).</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>If the passed path denotes a directory, the client will try to store all
                        documents in that directory into the database. However, it will
                        <i>not</i> recurse into subdirectories. For this, you have to
                        pass the <ph>-d</ph> option. For example:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -d -c /db/movies -m /db/movies -p /home/exist/xml/movies</pre>
                    <p>This will recurse into all directories below
                        <ph>/home/exist/xml/movies</ph>. For each subdirectory, a
                        collection will be created below the <ph>/db/movies</ph>
                        collection. Use this to recursively import an entire collection tree.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>

            <p> eXist-db can also store binary resources in addition to XML files. The client
                tries to determine if the current file is XML or not. The
                <ph>mime-types.xml</ph> lookup table (in the eXist root installation
                directory) is used for this. It associates: </p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>a MIME type</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>an eXist-db type ("xml" or "binary")</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>a file extension</p>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p> This mechanism is also used by the eXist-db servers . For example to specify that
                <ph>.xmap</ph> extension is used for XML files: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;mime-type name="application/xml" type="xml"&gt;
  &lt;description&gt;
    XML document
  &lt;/description&gt;
  &lt;extensions&gt;
    .xml,.xsl,.xsd,.mods,.xmi,.xconf,.xslt,.wsdl,.x3d,.rdf,.owl,.xmap
  &lt;/extensions&gt;
&lt;/mime-type&gt;</pre>

        </section>

        

        <section id="remove">
                <title>Removing Collections/Documents</title>
            

            <p>The <ph>-r</ph> and <ph>-R</ph> parameters are used to remove
                a document or collection. </p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p> <ph>-r</ph> removes a single document from the collection
                        specified in the <ph>-c</ph> parameter. For example:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -c /db/shakespeare/plays -r hamlet.xml</pre>
                    <p>This removes the document <ph>hamlet.xml</ph> from the
                        <ph>/db/shakespeare/plays</ph> collection.</p>

                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>To remove the entire <ph>plays</ph> collection use the
                        <ph>-R</ph> parameter:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -c /db/shakespeare -R plays</pre>
                </li>
                </ul>

        </section>

        

        <section id="execute">
                <title>Executing Queries</title>
            
            <p>Executing queries can be done as follows:</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Use the <ph>-x</ph> parameter. This parameter accepts an
                        optional argument, which specifies the query to execute. However, passing
                        XQuery on the command-line is a problem on many operating systems, because
                        the command shell usually interprets whitespace characters as command
                        separators. Therefore if no argument is passed to <ph>-x</ph>, the
                        client will try to read the query from standard input.</p>
                    <p>For example, on Unix you may do the follwong:</p>
                    <pre>echo "//SPEECH[contains(LINE, 'love')]" | bin/client.sh -x</pre>
                    <p>Remember to type Ctrl-d when working without pipe:</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -x ENTER
      //SPEECH[contains(LINE, 'love')] ENTER Ctrl-d</pre>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Queries can also be read from a file using the <ph>-F</ph> parameter.
                        For example,</p>
                    <pre>bin/client.sh -F samples/xquery/fibo.xq</pre>
                    <p>This executes the XQuery contained in <ph>fibo.xq</ph>.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>As an addition use <ph>-n</ph> to specify the number of hits
                        that should be printed to the standard output.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>

        </section>

        

        <section id="xupdate">
                <title>XUpdate</title>
            

            <p>You can update a stored document or multiple documents by passing an XUpdate file
                on the command-line. For example: </p>
            <pre>bin/client.sh -c /db/test -f address.xml -X samples/xupdate/xupdate.xml</pre>
            <p>This will apply the modifications described in
                <ph>samples/xupdate/xupdate.xml</ph> to the document
                <ph>address.xml</ph> in collection <ph>/db/test</ph>.</p>
            <p>If you don't specify the <ph>-f</ph> option, the modifications will be
                applied to all documents in the collection.</p>
        </section>

    </section>
    </body>
</topic>