<topic id="configuration">
    <title>Application Server Configuration</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q21"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This section deals with the configuration of the eXist-db Application Server in eXist-db's
        main configuration file <ph>conf.xml</ph>.</p>
        <section id="conf.xml">
            <title>Main configuration file</title>
        

        <p>The main configuration file for <ph>eXist-db</ph> is called
            <ph>conf.xml</ph>, which is loaded the root directory of the
            distribution (as specified by the system property <ph>exist.home</ph>).</p>

        <p>The configuration file <ph>conf.xml</ph> is divided into twelve
            sections:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>db-connection</ph>: Configures the storage back-end.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>lock-manager</ph>: Configures the Lock Manager.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>repository</ph>: Settings for the package repository.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>binary-manager</ph>: Settings for the Binary Manager.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>indexer</ph>: Controls the indexing process.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>scheduler</ph>: Job scheduler for system or user jobs such as backups.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>parser</ph>: Default settings for parsing structured documents.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>serializer</ph>: Default settings for the serializer (external data representation).</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>transformer</ph>: Default settings for the XSLT Transformer.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>validation</ph>: Settings for XML validation.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>xquery</ph>: Enable and configure extension modules that contain XQuery
                    functions.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>xupdate</ph>: Configuration options related to XUpdate processing.</p>
          </li>
                <li>
            <p>
                        <ph>rpc-server</ph>: Configuration options related to RPC result pooling.</p>
          </li>
            </ol>
        <p>The following sections describe the most commonly modified of the above elements,
            including how to change the default behavior of eXist-db's handling of whitespace
            characters.</p>

        
        <section id="db-connection">
                <title> <ph>db-connection</ph> element</title>
            

            <p>This element contains basic default storage settings for eXist-db, including
                memory and system limits. Only one <ph>db-connection</ph> should be specified. An
                example configuration for the native back-end is shown below:</p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;db-connection cacheSize="48M" collectionCache="24M" database="native" files="../data" pageSize="4096" nodesBuffer="-1"&gt;
  &lt;pool min="1" max="15" sync-period="240000" wait-before-shutdown="60000"/&gt;
  &lt;!-- default-permissions collection="0775" resource="0775" / --&gt;
  &lt;recovery enabled="yes" sync-on-commit="no" group-commit="no" size="100M" journal-dir="../data"/&gt;
  &lt;watchdog query-timeout="-1" output-size-limit="10000"/&gt;
  &lt;default-permissions collection="0775" resource="0775"/&gt;
&lt;/db-connection&gt;</pre>

            <section id="db-att">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>database</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute selects a database system type. Since relational
                                database back-ends are no longer supported by the current release of
                                eXist, only <ph>native</ph> is available.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>files</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute specifies the directory where the native back-end
                                will keep its database files, and so it is necessary that this
                                directory exists. If a relative path is specified, it will be based
                                on the root directory as defined in the
                                <ph>exist.home</ph> system property. If this data
                                directory does not have write permissions (see <xref href="security" scope="external">User Authentication and Access
                                Control</xref>), eXist will internally switch to <i>read-only
                                mode</i> such that any attempt to change the database will
                                throw an exception.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>cacheSize</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute sets the maximum amount of main memory used by all
                                page buffers (i.e. assuming all page buffers are at full capacity).
                                The database uses this parameter to calculate the maximum size of
                                each internal cache. You can increase this value if your system
                                allows for greater memory use.</p>
                            <p>While indexing documents, eXist will reserve the amount of memory
                                specified in cacheSize - even if not all caches are filled - and
                                will not use it for temporary data.</p>
                            <p>The cacheSize should not be more than half of the size of the JVM
                                heap size (set by the JVM <ph>-Xmx</ph> parameter). If the JVM
                                heap is less than 512 megabyte, the cacheSize should even be
                                smaller, e.g. 1/3.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>collectionCache</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Determines the size of the collection cache, which is a separate
                                caching space. Usually this setting does not need to be changed
                                unless you really have more than a few thousand collections in the
                                db. Increase it carefully, maybe up to 128M.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>pageSize</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This specifies the number of bytes used for internal data and
                                B-tree pages. This should be equal to or a multiple of the page size
                                used by the filesystem (usually a multiple of 4096).</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>nodesBuffer</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Size of the temporary buffer used by eXist for caching index data
                                while indexing a document. If set to -1, eXist will use the entire
                                free memory to buffer index entries and will flush the cache once
                                the memory is full.</p>
                            <p>If set to a value &gt; 0, the buffer will be fixed to the given
                                size. The specified number corresponds to the number of nodes the
                                buffer can hold, in thousands. Usually, a good default could be
                                <ph>nodesBuffer="1000"</ph>.</p>
                            <p>The default setting, nodesBuffer="-1", can be problematic if you
                                frequently need to store large documents in a multi-user
                                environment. In this case, the index operation may consume most of
                                the memory resources, which means that concurrent threads will be
                                slowed down or even come to a halt.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>
            <section id="db-pool">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph>/<ph>pool</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>These settings control the internal database connection pool.</p>
                <dl>
                        <p>
                            <b> pool Attributes</b>
                        </p>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>min</ph> | <ph>max</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>These options specify the minimum and maximum size of the
                                connection pool. This pool restricts the number of parallel (basic)
                                operations that can be executed by the database. Settings should be
                                somewhere between 1 and 20. </p>
                            <p>Please note that this has nothing to do with the HTTP and XMLRPC
                                server settings - these servers have their own connection
                                pools.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>sync-period</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This option defines how often the database will flush its internal
                                buffers to disk (in milliseconds). The sync-thread will interrupt
                                normal database operation after the specified time and write all
                                dirty pages to disk. It also writes a checkpoint to the transaction
                                log. In case of a database crash, only transactions which started
                                after the last checkpoint have to be redone or rolled back. The
                                sync-period should thus not be set too long.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>wait-before-shutdown</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This option specifies the maximum amount of time (in milliseconds)
                                that the database will allow for any running processes to complete
                                upon database shutdown. After that, eXist will try to kill the
                                remaining processes.</p>
                            <p>If wait-before-shutdown is set to a positive number, eXist will
                                stop the db after the specified timeout, even if there were still
                                running database operations. In this case, no checkpoint will be
                                written to the transaction log. If there were any open transactions,
                                eXist will trigger a recovery run after restart.</p>
                            <p>If wait-before-shutdown is set to -1, eXist will not shut down
                                before all active database operations returned. This is a safe
                                setting, but it may require a manual intervention to stop the
                                JVM.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="db-query-pool">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph>/<ph>query-pool</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>This element configures the global pool for compiled XQuery expressions. For
                    each XQuery, a maximum number of compiled expressions are kept in the pool, and
                    is removed if it hasn't been used for the defined timeout. The XQuery pool is
                    multi-threaded.</p>
                <p> <ph>query-pool</ph> Attributes:</p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>max-stack-size</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The maximum number of queries in the query-pool.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>size</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The number of copies of the same query kept in the query-pool.
                                Value <ph>"-1"</ph> effectively disables caching. Queries cannot
                                be shared by threads, each thread needs a private copy of a
                                query.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>timeout</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The amount of time that a query will be cached in the query-pool
                                in milliseconds.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>timeout-check-interval</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The time between checking for timed out queries. For value
                                <ph>"-1"</ph> the time out is switched off, resulting cached
                                queries to remain in the cache forever.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="db-recovery">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph>/<ph>recovery</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>This element configures the journalling and recovery of the database. With
                    recovery enabled, the database is able to recover from an unclean database
                    shutdown due to, for example, power failures, OS reboots, and hanging processes.
                    For this to work correctly, all database operations must be logged to a journal
                    file. The location, size and other parameters for this file can be set using the
                    <ph>recovery</ph> element.</p>
                <p> <ph>recovery</ph> Attributes:</p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enabled</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>If this attribute is set to <ph>yes</ph>, automatic
                                recovery is enabled.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>size</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attributes sets the maximum allowed size of the journal file.
                                Once the journal reaches this limit, a checkpoint will be triggered
                                and the journal will be cleaned. However, the database waits for
                                running transactions to return before processing this checkpoint. In
                                the event one of these transactions writes a lot of data to the
                                journal file, the file will grow until the transaction has
                                completed. Hence, the size limit is not enforced in all
                                cases.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>journal-dir</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute sets the directory where journal files are to be
                                written. If no directory is specified, the default path is to the
                                <ph>data</ph> directory.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>sync-on-commit</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute determines whether or not to protect the journal
                                during operating system failures. That is, it determines whether the
                                database forces a file-sync on the journal after every commit. If
                                this attribute is set to <ph>yes</ph>, the journal is
                                protected against operating system failures. However, this will slow
                                performance - especially on Windows systems. If set to
                                <ph>no</ph>, eXist will rely on the operating system to
                                flush out the journal contents to disk. In the worst case scenario,
                                in which there is a complete system failure, some committed
                                transactions might not have yet been written to the journal, and so
                                will be rolled back.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>group-commit</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>If set to <ph>yes</ph>, eXist will not sync the journal file
                                immediately after every transaction commit. Instead, it will wait
                                until the current file buffer (32kb) is really full. This can speed
                                up eXist on some systems where a file sync is an expensive operation
                                (mainly windows XP; not necessary on Linux).</p>
                            <p>However, <ph>group-comit="yes"</ph> will increase the
                                chance that an already committed operation is rolled back after a
                                database crash.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>force-restart</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Try to restart the db even if crash recovery failed. This is
                                dangerous because there might be corruptions inside the data files.
                                The transaction log will be cleared, all locks removed and the db
                                re-indexed.</p>
                            <p>Set this option to <ph>yes</ph> if you need to make sure that
                                the db is online, even after a fatal crash. Errors encountered
                                during recovery are written to the log files. Scan the log files to
                                see if any problems occurred.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>consistency-check</dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>If set to <ph>yes</ph>, a consistency check will be run on the
                                database if an error was detected during crash recovery. This option
                                requires force-restart to be set to <ph>yes</ph>, otherwise it
                                has no effect.</p>
                            <p>The consistency check outputs a report to the directory
                                {files}/sanity and if inconsistencies are found in the db, it writes
                                an emergency backup to the same directory.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="db-watchdog">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph>/<ph>watchdog</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>This is the global configuration for the <i>query watchdog</i>.
                    The watchdog monitors all query processes, and can terminate any long-running
                    queries if they exceed one of the predefined limits. These limits are as
                    follows:</p>

                <p> <ph>watchdog</ph> Attributes:</p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>query-timeout</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute sets the maximum amount of time (expressed in
                                milliseconds) that the query can take before it is killed. The
                                setting can be overwritten in an XQuery by specifying the option
                                <ph>exist:timeout</ph>:</p>
                            <pre outputclass="xquery">declare option exist:timeout "time-in-ms";</pre>
                            <p>Please check the documentation on <xref href="xquery" scope="external">XQuery
                                options</xref>.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>output-size-limit</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute limits the size of XML fragments constructed using
                                XQuery, and thus sets the maximum amount of main memory a query is
                                allowed to use. This limit is expressed as the maximum number of
                                nodes allowed for an in-memory DOM tree. The purpose of this option
                                is to avoid memory shortages on the server in cases where users are
                                allowed to run queries that produce very large output fragments. The
                                setting can be overwritten in an XQuery by specifying the option
                                <ph>exist:output-size-limit</ph>:</p>
                            <pre outputclass="xquery">declare option exist:output-size-limit "size-hint";</pre>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="db-perm">
                    <title> <ph>db-connection</ph>/<ph>default-permissions</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>Specifies the default permissions for all resources and collections in eXist
                    (see <xref href="security" scope="external">User Authentication and Access
                    Control</xref>). When this is not configured, the default <ph>mod</ph>
                    (similar to the Unix <ph>chmod</ph> command) is set to
                    <ph>0775</ph> in the <ph>resources</ph> and
                    <ph>collections</ph> attributes. A different default value may be set
                    for a database instance. Local overrides are also possible.</p>
            </section>
        </section>


        
        <section id="lock-manager">
                <title> <ph>lock-manager</ph> element</title>
            
            <p>This element contains settings for eXist-db's Lock Manager and Lock Table. The majority
                of these Lock Manager settings should not be modified unless otherwise suggested by eXist-db Core Development Team.</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>lock-table/@disabled</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Disables the database Lock Table which tracks database locks. The Lock Table is enabled by default
                            and allows reporting on database locking via JMX.</p>
                        <p>Tracking locks via the Lock Table imposes a small overhead per-Lock. Once users
                            have finished testing their system to ensure correct operation, they may wish to disable
                            this in production to ensure the absolute best performance.</p>
                        <note type="note">
                                <p>Unless nessecary, it is recommened to leave this enabled.</p>
                            </note>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>document/@use-path-locks</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>
                                <i>Experimental:</i> Causes path locks to be used for documents as well as collection locks.</p>
                        <p>This has a performance and concurrency impact, but will ensure that you cannot have deadlocks between Collections and Documents.</p>
                        <note type="note">
                                <p>Unless nessecary, it is recommened to leave this at its default value.</p>
                            </note>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
        </section>

        

        <section id="indexer">
                <title> <ph>indexer</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>This element sets parameters on how XML files are to be indexed by eXist. An
                example configuration is shown below:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;indexer caseSensitive="yes" index-depth="5" preserve-whitespace-mixed-content="no" suppress-whitespace="none"&gt;
  &lt;modules&gt;
    &lt;module id="ngram-index" file="ngram.dbx" n="3" class="org.exist.indexing.ngram.NGramIndex"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- &lt;module id="spatial-index" connectionTimeout="10000" flushAfter="300" class="org.exist.indexing.spatial.GMLHSQLIndex"/&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;module id="lucene-index" buffer="32" class="org.exist.indexing.lucene.LuceneIndex"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- The following index can be used to speed up 'order by' expressions by pre-ordering a node set. --&gt;
    &lt;module id="sort-index" class="org.exist.indexing.sort.SortIndex"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- New range index based on Apache Lucene. Replaces the old range index which is hard-wired into eXist core. --&gt;
    &lt;module id="range-index" class="org.exist.indexing.range.RangeIndex"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- The following module is not really an index (though it sits in the index pipeline). It gathers relevant statistics on the distribution of elements in the database, which can be used by the query optimizer for additional optimizations. --&gt;
    &lt;!-- &lt;module id="index-stats" file="stats.dbx" class="org.exist.storage.statistics.IndexStatistics" /&gt; --&gt;
  &lt;/modules&gt;
  &lt;!-- Default index settings. Default settings apply if there's no collection-specific configuration for a collection. --&gt;
  &lt;index&gt;
    &lt;!-- settings go here --&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/indexer&gt;</pre>

            <section id="indexer-att">
                    <title> <ph>indexer</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>caseSensitive</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Specifies whether string comparisons are to be case-sensitive.
                                This option applies to XPath equality tests (i.e. the
                                <ph>=</ph> operator), as well as functions such as
                                <ph>contains()</ph>, <ph>starts-with()</ph> and
                                <ph>ends-with()</ph>. </p>
                            <p>This setting does not apply to operators or functions of the
                                full-text index (e.g. <ph>&amp;=</ph>,
                                <ph>|=</ph>, <ph>near()</ph>) nor the n-gram
                                index, which are <i>never</i> case-sensitive</p>
                            <note type="warning">
                                    <p>Setting <ph>caseSensitive="no"</ph> violates the
                                    XQuery specs! The option should be regarded as a dirty
                                    workaround, which will be removed in the future. Please use the
                                    n-gram or full-text indexes for case-insensitive queries or - if
                                    that is impossible - specify a <xref href="xquery#collations" scope="external">collation</xref>.</p>
                                </note>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>suppress-whitespace</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Specifies how the <ph>indexer</ph> is to treat whitespace at the
                                start or end of a character sequence. This option
                                <i>only</i> applies to newly stored files, and
                                therefore changing it has no effect on previously stored documents.
                                Possible values for this attribute are:</p>
                            <ol>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>leading</ph> - Suppresses leading
                                        whitespace.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>trailing</ph> - Suppresses trailing
                                        whitespace.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>both</ph> - Suppresses leading and trailing
                                        whitespace.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>none</ph> - Preserves all
                                        whitespace.</p>
                                </li>
                                </ol>
                            <p>Note that suppressing whitespace at the start or end of character
                                sequences does effectively change the document!</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>preserve-whitespace-mixed-content</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>controls how ignorable whitespace is handled. If set to
                                <ph>no</ph>, ignorable whitespace, e.g. between the end
                                tag of an element and the start tag of another, will not be stored
                                into the persistent DOM. This leads to a smaller DOM and usually
                                increases the readability of the XML. Ignorable whitespace is not
                                considered as a part of the logical document model, so removing it
                                doesn't change the document.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>tokenizer</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute invokes the Java class used to tokenize a string
                                into a sequence of single words or tokens, which are stored to the
                                full-text index. Currently only <ph>SimpleTokenizer</ph>
                                is available.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>index-depth</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute specifies the depth of the DOM index, or the tree
                                level up to which elements will be added to the index. For example,
                                a value of <ph>2</ph> results in the document root node
                                and all its child elements being indexed; a value of
                                <ph>1</ph> only indexes the root node.</p>
                            <p>The DOM index maps unique node identifiers to the nodes' storage
                                locations in the DOM file. Generating this index is time- and
                                memory-consuming. It is furthermore primarily needed to access nodes
                                by their unique node identifier, for example, when serializing XML
                                data for query results or XUpdate - which are operations not
                                normally considered time-critical. Moreover, most XPath expressions
                                can do without this index since they use short-cuts to access the
                                node directly.</p>
                            <p>Normally only top-level elements are added to the DOM index,
                                whereas attributes and text nodes are always excluded. This results
                                in much smaller index sizes and, consequently, a smaller
                                <ph>dom.dbx</ph> file size. Usually, setting the
                                <ph>index-depth</ph> to a value of <ph>2</ph>
                                offers a reasonable compromise of index size and performance.</p>
                            <p>However, if your documents are
                                <i>deeply-structured</i>, you might consider
                                increasing this setting to a level of 3, 4 or 5. For example, if the
                                longest path from the document root to an element node has greater
                                than ten node levels, an <ph>index-depth</ph> setting of
                                <ph>4</ph> or <ph>5</ph> would probably help to
                                increase overall query performance for some types of queries.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>validation</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute defines the default setting for the validation of
                                documents by the XML parser. If it is set to <ph>no</ph>,
                                documents will never be validated against an existing DTD or schema.
                                A value of <ph>auto</ph> will leave document validation to
                                the SAX parser.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="indexer-modules">
                    <title> <ph>indexer</ph>/<ph>modules</ph> element </title>
                

                <p>This section configures optional indexing modules. Beginning with version 1.2,
                    eXist features a modularized indexing architecture, which allows new indexes to
                    be plugged into the indexing pipeline. The <ph>modules</ph> section lists and
                    configures the indexes that will be available to the database:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;modules&gt;
  &lt;module id="ngram-index" class="org.exist.indexing.ngram.NGramIndex" file="ngram.dbx" n="3"/&gt;
  &lt;!-- &lt;module id="spatial-index" class="org.exist.indexing.spatial.GMLHSQLIndex" connectionTimeout="10000" flushAfter="300" /&gt; --&gt;
&lt;/modules&gt;</pre>
                <p>The only common attributes for each <ph>module</ph> element are
                    <ph>class</ph> and <ph>id</ph>. The other attributes, as
                    well as any nested elements, are specific to the index implementation. Detailed
                    information is available in the article on <xref href="indexing#moduleconf" scope="external">Configuring Database Indexes</xref>.</p>
            </section>

            <section id="indexer-stopwords">
                    <title> <ph>indexer</ph>/<ph>stopwords</ph> element </title>
                

                <p>The <ph>file</ph> attribute for this element points to a file
                    containing a list of <i>stop-words</i>. Stop-words are not added
                    to the full-text index.</p>
            </section>

            <section id="indexer-index">
                    <title> <ph>indexer</ph>/<ph>index</ph> element </title>
                

                <p>This configuration element specifies the default index settings. These
                    settings are applied if neither the collection nor any of its ancestors provide
                    a collection configuration.</p>
                <p>Configuring indexes via the default settings is <i>not</i>
                    recommended. If you need a global collection configuration, store one for the
                    root collection <ph>/db</ph>. For more information, see <xref href="indexing" scope="external">Configuring Indexes</xref>.</p>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="scheduler">
                <title> <ph>scheduler</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>This section is used to configure asynchronous jobs with eXist's internal
                scheduler. Three types of jobs are supported:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>startup jobs</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>Startup jobs are executed once during database startup, but before the
                            database becomes available. These jobs are synchronous. The database is
                            blocked to outside requests and no other operations will run at the same
                            time.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>system jobs</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>System jobs require the database to be in a consistent state. The
                            scheduler will run them in an exclusive environment. Once the job is
                            triggered, the database will block all new requests and wait for running
                            operations to complete. It then executes the job. All other database
                            operations will be stopped until the job returns or throws an exception.
                            Any exception will be caught and a warning written to the log.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>user jobs</dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>User jobs may be scheduled at any time and may be mutually exclusive
                            or non-exclusive</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
            <p>Below is an example which configures a <xref href="backup" scope="external">BackupSystemTask</xref>: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;job type="system" name="databackup" class="org.exist.storage.DataBackup" period="120000"&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="output-dir" value="backup"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="suffix" value=".zip"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="prefix" value="backup-"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="collection" value="/db"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="user" value="admin"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="password"/&gt;
  &lt;parameter name="zip-files-max" value="28"/&gt;
&lt;/job&gt;</pre>
            <p>Each job is configured in a <ph>job</ph> element which accepts a number of
                standard attributes:</p>
            <section id="job-att">
                    <title> <ph>job</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>type</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The type of the job to schedule. Must be either
                                <ph>startup</ph>, <ph>system</ph> or
                                <ph>user</ph>.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>class</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>If the job is written in Java this should be the name of the class
                                that extends either</p>
                            <ul>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>org.exist.scheduler.StartupJob</ph> </p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>org.exist.storage.SystemTask</ph> </p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>org.exist.scheduler.UserJavaJob</ph> </p>
                                </li>
                                </ul>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>xquery</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>If the job is written in XQuery (not suitable for system jobs)
                                this should be a path to the XQuery stored in the database, e.g.
                                <ph>/db/myCollection/myJob.xql</ph>. XQuery job's will be
                                launched under the <ph>guest</ph> account initially. The running
                                XQuery may switch permissions through calls to
                                <ph>xmldb:login()</ph>.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>cron-trigger</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>To define a firing pattern for the Job using <ph>cron</ph>
                                style syntax. Not applicable to start-up jobs.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>unschedule-on-exception</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Either <ph>true</ph> (default) or <ph>false</ph>. If
                                <ph>true</ph> and an exception is encountered the job is
                                unscheduled for further execution until a restart. Otherwise, the
                                exception is ignored.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>period</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Can be used to define an explicit period for firing the job
                                instead of a <ph>cron</ph> style syntax. Expressed in
                                milliseconds. Not applicable to start-up jobs.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>delay</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Can be used for periodic jobs to delay the start of a job. If
                                unspecified jobs will start as soon as the database and scheduler
                                are initialised.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>repeat</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Can be used for periodic jobs to define how many periods a job
                                should be executed. If unspecified, jobs will repeat
                                indefinitely.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
                <p>Every job can take additional parameters, which are passed as name/value
                    pairs.</p>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="serializer">
                <title> <ph>serializer</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>The serializer is responsible for serializing XML documents or document fragments
                back into XML. This configuration element defines default settings for various
                parameters, which can also be specified programmatically. All settings can be
                overwritten by XQuery <xref href="xquery#serialization" scope="external">serialization
                options</xref>.</p>
            <section id="serializer-att">
                    <title> <ph>serializer</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enable-xinclude</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute determines whether <ph>xinclude</ph> tags are to
                                be expanded during serialization. Setting the value to
                                <ph>false</ph> will leave <ph>xinclude</ph> tags
                                unexpanded.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enable-xsl</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Setting this attribute to <ph>true</ph> tells the
                                serializer to pass its output to an XSL stylesheet when it
                                encounters an XSL processing-instruction at the start of the
                                document.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>add-exist-id</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute tells the serializer to add additional debug
                                attributes to each element. This information includes the internal
                                identifier of the node and source document. Values:</p>
                            <ol>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>all</ph> - Adds debug information to every
                                        node in the output.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>element</ph> - Adds debug information to
                                        top-level elements only.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>none</ph> (default) - Disables debugging
                                        feature.</p>
                                </li>
                                </ol>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>indent</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The serializer defaults to pretty-print the resulting XML source
                                code. Setingt this option to <ph>no</ph> disables
                                pretty-printing.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>match-tagging-elements</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The database can highlight matches in the text content of a node
                                by tagging the matching text string with <ph>exist:match</ph>.
                                This only works for XPath expressions using the full-text index. Set
                                the parameter to <ph>yes</ph> to
                                <i>disable</i> this feature.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="transformer">
                <title> <ph>transformer</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>This section determines which XSLT processor will be used by eXist. By default,
                eXist relies on Saxon.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="validations">
                <title> <ph>validation</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>Defines the default validation settings active when parsing XML and links to
                catalog files. Catalog files are used to locate DTDs, schemas and resolve external
                entities in general.</p>
            <p>Please refer to the corresponding documentation on <xref href="validation" scope="external">XML Validation</xref>.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="xupdate">
                <title> <ph>xupdate</ph> element</title>
            

            <p>Inserting new nodes into a document can lead to fragmentation in the DOM storage
                file. eXist will thus trigger a de-fragmentation run if the fragmentation exceeds a
                certain limit. The frequency of such de-fragmentation runs can be configured in the
                <ph>xupdate</ph> section. The main parameter is called
                <ph>allowed-fragmentation</ph>:</p>

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xupdate allowed-fragmentation="20" enable-consistency-checks="no"/&gt;</pre>
            <section id="xupdate-att">
                    <title> <ph>xupdate</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>allowed-fragmentation</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute defines the maximum number of page splits allowed
                                within a document before a de-fragmentation run is triggered.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enable-consistency-checks</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>This attribute is for or debugging purposes only. If the parameter
                                is set to <ph>yes</ph>, a <i>consistency
                                check</i> will be run on modified documents after every
                                XUpdate request. This checks whether the persistent DOM is complete,
                                and all pointers in the structural index point to valid storage
                                addresses that contain valid nodes.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="xq-el">
                <title> <ph>xquery</ph> element</title>
            

            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;xquery enable-java-binding="no" enable-query-rewriting="no" enforce-index-use="always" disable-deprecated-functions="no" raise-error-on-failed-retrieval="no" backwardCompatible="no"&gt;
  &lt;builtin-modules&gt;
    &lt;!-- Default Modules --&gt;
    &lt;module class="org.exist.xquery.functions.util.UtilModule" uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/util"/&gt;
    &lt;!-- ... more modules ... --&gt;
  &lt;/builtin-modules&gt;
&lt;/xquery&gt;</pre>
            <p>The <ph>xquery</ph> section is used to enable/disable certain core features of
                the XQuery engine. It also lists the XQuery extension modules that will be known to
                the query engine by default.</p>

            <section id="xq-att">
                    <title> <ph>xquery</ph> attributes</title>
                

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enable-java-binding</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Set to <ph>yes</ph> to enable the <xref href="xquery" scope="external">java binding</xref>. Giving users full access to all Java classes
                                should be considered a security risk and the feature is thus
                                disabled by default.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>disable-deprecated-functions</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Set to <ph>yes</ph> to enable XQuery functions marked as
                                deprecated.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enforce-index-use</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>controls if available range indexes should be used if only some
                                collections in the context set define a matching index. Available
                                settings are: </p>
                            <ul>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>always</ph> to always use an index, even if it
                                        does not apply to the entire set of collections being
                                        queried.</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>strict</ph> to only use indexes if they are
                                        defined for the entire collection set.</p>
                                </li>
                                </ul>

                            <p> </p>
                            <p>For example, if you have two collections: <ph>/db/one</ph> and
                                <ph>/db/two</ph>, and you define a range index on a certain
                                element <ph>node</ph> in <ph>/db/one</ph>, but not in
                                <ph>/db/two</ph>, the query engine would not use the index with
                                setting <ph>strict</ph> if you query both collections. At
                                compile time, eXist doesn't know if <ph>node</ph> exists in both
                                collections and will not use the index if it determines that an
                                index definition does only apply to a part of the collection set
                                being queried. To use the index, you would need to start your XPath
                                expression with a call to <ph>collection()</ph>, selecting the
                                correct collection with the index defined.</p>
                            <p>If <ph>enforce-index-use</ph> is set to <ph>always</ph>,
                                the query engine only checks if one collection in the collection set
                                has a matching index defined on it. This may lead to an incomplete
                                query result if one forgets certain collections.</p>
                            <p>In other words, when <ph>enforce-index-use</ph> is set to
                                "always", it is the query writer's responsibility to make sure
                                indexes are defined properly. But experience has shown it is easier
                                for users to understand that a certain result is incomplete because
                                an index is missing, whereas they have problems to see that a
                                performance issue is caused by inconsistent indexing. </p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>raise-error-on-failed-retrieval</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Set to <ph>yes</ph> if a call to
                                <ph>doc()</ph>, <ph>xmldb:document()</ph>,
                                <ph>collection()</ph> or
                                <ph>xmldb:xcollection()</ph> should raise an error
                                (FODC0002) when an XML resource can not be retrieved.</p>
                            <p>Set to <ph>no</ph> if a call to
                                <ph>doc()</ph>, <ph>xmldb:document()</ph>,
                                <ph>collection()</ph> or
                                <ph>xmldb:xcollection()</ph> should return an empty
                                sequence when an XML resource can not be retrieved.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>enable-query-rewriting</ph>o</dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>the query engine can often achieve considerable performance
                                improvements by rewriting an XQuery expression into a more efficient
                                form (see the documentation about <xref href="indexing" scope="external">indexing</xref>). However, these features are relatively new. If
                                you have doubts about the correctness of a query result, you may
                                temporarily set <ph>enable-query-rewriting</ph> to
                                <ph>no</ph> and see if the result changes in any way. If
                                it does, you have hit a bug which should be reported. </p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>backwardCompatible</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>|Set to <ph>yes</ph> to enable XPath 1.0 backwards
                                compatibility. The setting mainly effects automatic type
                                conversions, which were less strict in XPath 1.0 than in later
                                versions.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="xq-builtin">
                    <title> <ph>xquery</ph>/<ph>builtin-modules</ph> element </title>
                

                <p>This section lists the XQuery extension modules which will be known to the
                    query engine. The modules in this list can be imported into a query without
                    specifying a location. For example:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;module class="org.exist.xquery.modules.file.FileModule" uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/file"/&gt;</pre>
                <p>This establishes a static mapping between the module URI for the file module
                    and the Java class which implements it. When using that module, it is sufficient
                    to provide the correct URI in the import. Specifying a location is not needed,
                    like in:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace file="http://exist-db.org/xquery/file";</pre>
                <p>Instead of providing a Java class, one can also specify a <ph>src</ph> URI
                    which must point to the XQuery source code of the module, for instance:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;module uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic" src="resource:org/exist/xquery/lib/kwic.xql"/&gt;</pre>
                <p>For the <ph>src</ph> attribute, eXist understands the <xref href="xquery#module-system" scope="external">same types of URIs</xref> as in an
                    ordinary XQuery import statement.</p>
            </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="rpc-server">
                <title> <ph>rpc-server</ph> element </title>
            

            <p>Defines the RPC server backend specific options used to process the requests and caching
                result values.</p>

            <section id="content-file">
                    <title> <ph>rpc-server</ph>/<ph>content-file</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>This element configures the maximum amount of data in bytes held in the heap space before
                    the data is moved to the temporary disk space. While using memory improves the performance
                    and not triggering eventually existing virus scanners it comes with the cost of heap size usage.
                    The location, size and other parameters for this file can be set using the
                    <ph>content-file</ph> element.</p>
                <p> <ph>content-file</ph> Attributes:</p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>max-in-memory-size</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Defines the maximum amount of data in bytes to hold in memory, before storing on
                                temporary disk space.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

            <section id="content-file-pool">
                    <title> <ph>rpc-server</ph>/<ph>content-file-pool</ph> element</title>
                

                <p>This element configures the pool used to hold the content file entries in order to reuse the once
                    initialized instances to further improve the performance and to limit the amount of used heap size.
                    To calculate the maximum size of used memory the maximum in memory size of a single content file has
                    to be multiplied by the size of the pool.
                    The location, size and other parameters for this file can be set using the
                    <ph>content-file-pool</ph> element.</p>
                <p> <ph>content-file</ph> Attributes:</p>
                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>size</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Specifies the maximum amount of content file objects that can be in use concurrently.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt> <ph>max-idle</ph> </dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Defines the maximum amount of idle pool entries that will not be removed for later reuse.</p>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>
            </section>

        </section>


    </section>
    </body>
</topic>