<topic id="beginners-guide-to-xrx-v4">
    <title>Creating CRUDS applications with XRX in eXist</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="getting-started"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This is a beginner's guide for creating a new XRX application with eXist-db (hereafter,
        eXist). XRX stands for <i>XForms, REST, XQuery</i>, the three technologies
        tied together to create applications.</p>
        <p>This guide intended for people who are new to eXist and are interested in building their
        first web applications. It demonstrates the minimal code necessary to create applications
        that perform CRUDS operations (Create, Read, Update, Delete, Search). Creating your first
        application can be somewhat tricky, since there are several structures that need to be
        "wired" together correctly. This example tries to use as little code as possible and yet
        still cover many of the key components of a fully functional XRX web application.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>Creating a new web application from scratch is a core skill that is necessary to
            understand the power of the XRX (XForms, REST, XQuery) web application architecture.
            Once users understand how XRX applications are constructed, they can quickly become
            productive building new web applications. They also have a much better understanding of
            the complex portions of the XRX application and why these portions are usually automated
            in XRX frameworks.</p>
        <p>This document is designed for new eXist users who would like to create their first XRX
            application. For this process we assume that you have a basic understanding of XML and
            understand concepts such as XML elements and XPath expressions. You should also be
            somewhat familiar with very basic HTML markup, including the structure of an XHTML file
            and use of HTML lists and HTML tables. We will also be describing how XQuery is used to
            create a listing of items and viewing an individual item, so please review the basic
            structure of an XQuery FLWOR expression (for, let, order by, where, and return) and
            basic XQuery syntax. Familiarity with the fundamentals of XForms is helpful, but this
            guide will explain each of the XForms elements used in the example.</p>
        <p>Please note that there are several easy-to-use drag-and-drop GUI tools available that
            can create XForms, and there are systems that can also automatically create a fully
            functional XRX application directly from an XML Schema. But using these tools and
            frameworks hide much of the inner workings of an XRX application. So this tutorial is
            for those that want to have a clear understanding of how XRX systems work.</p>

        

        <section id="getting-started">
                <title>Getting Started</title>
            

            <p>To use this guide you will need to have following tools in place: </p>
            <ol>
                    <li>
                    <p> <b>eXist</b>: You will need to have <xref href="https://exist-db.org" scope="external">eXist</xref> running on your local system.
                        By default eXist runs on port <ph>8080</ph> so that when you set your
                        web browser to <xref href="http://localhost:8080/exist/" scope="external">http://localhost:8080/exist/</xref> you should see the eXist homepage come
                        up.</p>
                    <p>You can also run this tutorial on a remote eXist server. If you are doing
                        this, you must replace the server name <ph>localhost</ph> with the name
                        of your remote server. Make sure that you take into account the port number:
                        it might not be <ph>8080</ph>. If there is no visible port number, then
                        the server is running on the default HTTP ports <ph>80</ph> or HTTPS
                        port <ph>443</ph>.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p> <b>XML and XQuery Editor</b>: You will need
                        some tool to edit XML and XQuery files. We encourage you to use the eXide
                        web application, which is included in the default eXist installation, or
                        oXygen XML Editor, since these tools have special additions to make editing
                        XML and XQuery files easy. Simple text editors such as Microsoft Notepad
                        will work but will not give you immediate feedback when there are syntax
                        errors in your files, nor do they perform syntax highlighting. </p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p> <b>File Uploader</b>: You will need some tool
                        to transfer your files directly to eXist. Tools like eXide or oXygen can
                        save directly to the eXist database. You can also use a WebDAV client to
                        copy the files. As a final option, you can also use eXist's <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref> to upload
                        files.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p> <b>XForms</b>: You will need some XForms client
                        libraries. This example will use the XSLTForms client which can be installed
                        using the <xref href="dashboard" scope="external">Dashboard</xref> package manager.
                        Please install the XSLTForms Files package.</p>
                </li>
                </ol>
        </section>

        

        <section id="concepts">
                <title>Terms and Concepts Used</title>
            

            <p>This example will use the following terms and concepts:</p>
            <p> <b>XRX</b> is the name of the web application
                architecture that we are introducing in this guide. The term XRX comes from the
                combination of XForms, REST, and XQuery. The term was <xref href="https://web.archive.org/web/20171224124316/http://archive.oreilly.com/pub/post/xrx_a_simple_elegant_disruptiv_1.html" scope="external">coined</xref> by Dan McCreary. XForms are used in the client (web browser), REST is
                the interface between the client and the server, and XQuery is the server language.
                Two of the most significant advantages of XRX over other architectures are: (1) it
                does not require users to translate data into Java or .Net objects, and (2) it does
                not require users to "shred" documents into rows of a relational database.</p>
            <p> <b>XForms</b> is a W3C standard to define the structure
                of a web form. XForms is much more advanced than traditional HTML forms, but can
                appear intimidating to the first time user. However, most simple forms need only a
                few control types, and these can be quickly learned. XForms binds user interface
                controls to each leaf element in an XML instance. XForms stores the data in a model
                element in the HTML HEAD tag and then binds the leaf elements in the model to web
                input controls. </p>
            <p> <b>XQuery</b> is a W3C standard query language for
                selecting and transforming XML structures. If you don't have programming experience,
                XQuery is not hard to pick up. If you do have programming experience, XQuery is a
                little different than other languages you may have used in the past. It is a
                "functional" programming language that makes it very easy to create robust
                server-side programs—without struggling with the managing the "side-effects" that
                many other languages introduce. XQuery is similar to the SQL language in some ways,
                but it is specifically designed for XML structures. Paired with an XML database like
                eXist, XQuery is an ideal language for creating web applications. eXist's highly
                efficient indexing makes full text searches and other queries very fast, even when
                working with gigabytes of XML data. </p>
            <note type="note">
                    <p> <b>Note for New XQuery Users with Programming Experience
                    in Other Languages</b>. There are some things that are very different in
                    XQuery that you should be aware of. In general, all XQuery variables are
                    <i>immutable</i>, meaning that they are designed to
                    be set once but never changed. So functions like <ph>let $x := $x + 1</ph>
                    within loops will not increment like in procedural languages. There are also
                    restrictions on what can be done inside FLWOR statements.</p>
                </note>
            <p> <b>REST</b> is at the heart of the architecture of the
                World Wide Web. We use the "RESTful" approach to passing information around in our
                XRX application by simply placing parameters at the end of a URL. For example, to
                pass a query keyword to a our XRX application search service, our form appends the
                parameter <ph>q=myword</ph> to the URL: <ph>search.xq?q=myword</ph>. If you
                have ever used a SOAP architecture, REST is a breath of fresh air. No complex SOAP
                interface testing tools are required. All you need to test your web services is a
                web browser. For example, the home page of the test application under the default
                configuration will be <xref href="http://localhost:8080/exist/apps/term/index.html" scope="external">http://localhost:8080/exist/apps/term/index.html</xref>.</p>
            <p>Several additional terms and concepts are helpful in understanding the XRX
                approach:</p>
            <p> <b>WebDAV</b> is a protocol for transferring files, and
                we use eXist's WebDAV interface to move files to and from eXist and to list files in
                eXist collections. If you want to add a folder to eXist you can do this through the
                WebDAV interface. When you use oXygen or other editors you will also use the WebDAV
                interface.</p>
            <p> <b>Model-View Bindings</b> is the term we use to
                describe how user interface elements (controls) within a form are associated with
                leaf-level elements within the XForms model. This is similar to the
                Model-View-Controller (MVC) architecture in other systems, but in the case of XForms
                event controls are part of the views. By using XPath statements in the
                <ph>ref</ph> attributes for user interface controls, the browser constructs a
                dependency graph to keep the model and views in sync. This makes forms development
                much easier since the form developer never needs to manually move data between the
                model and the views.</p>
            <p> <b>Convention over Configuration</b> is a common
                practice among modern web application frameworks like XRX of using conventions such
                as standardized collection and file names, to reduce the amount of configuration and
                thereby reduce the complexity and time required to prototype and complete
                applications. Of course, users have the ability to change these conventions, but
                they then take responsibility for maintaining their own adaptations or separate
                frameworks. </p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="conventions">
            <title>Collection and File Conventions</title>
        

        <p>The first convention of XRX applications involves the data collections and files that
            will structure our application. Although you do not have to use the collection
            conventions used in this example, you will find that frameworks that use this convention
            will be much easier to build and maintain. </p>
        <p>Here are the conventions we strongly recommend you use for your first
            application:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Apps</b>: XRX applications should be stored
                    within the <b>/db/apps</b> parent collection. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>App</b>: Each XRX application should be stored a
                    collection whose name reflects the function of the application. For example, our
                    business term application might be stored in the <ph>/db/apps/terms</ph>
                    collection. The convention is to use the plural ("terms" rather than "term") for
                    the primary kind of content being stored in the app.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Data</b>: Each XRX application should store its
                    data in a discrete data collection. For example, our term manager application
                    will store all the data in <ph>/db/apps/terms/data</ph>. In this example the
                    first term will be stored in the file <ph>1.xml</ph> and the second in the
                    file <ph>2.xml</ph>, etc. When the user saves new terms, we can increment a
                    counter to add a new term.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Views</b>: Each XRX application should store
                    read-only views of the data in a <ph>views</ph> collection. In our example,
                    the term manager will store read-only views of the data in the
                    <ph>/db/apps/terms/views</ph> collection. Note that views are all functions
                    that transform but do not alter the original XML data. Views collections are
                    usually visible to all users that have read access to data. Views do not need to
                    worry about locking records to prevent missing updates. Tools that do change or
                    edit the data can be stored in another collection such as <ph>edit</ph>.
                    This allows access control systems to limit who changes or deletes data.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Edit</b>: Each XRX application should store its
                    edit functions in a collection called edit. For our term manager application
                    this would be <ph>/db/apps/term/edit</ph>. Edit function include saving new
                    terms, updating terms and deleting terms. By grouping all edit functions
                    together it is easy to deny access to users that do not have permission to
                    change items and to create consistent logging functions for audit trails.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Search</b>: Each XRX application should store
                    its search functions in a collection called <ph>search</ph>. For our term
                    manager application this would be <ph>/db/apps/term/search</ph>. There are
                    two functions stored here. A simple HTML search form (<ph>search.html</ph>)
                    and a RESTful search (<ph>service.xq</ph>). Advanced applications sometimes
                    combine these functions into a single XQuery that generates HTML. </p>
                <p>In addition to these two search functions, an additional collection
                    configuration file, called <ph>collection.xconf</ph>, must be stored in the
                    <ph>/db/system/config/db/apps/terms/data</ph> collection that describes how
                    the files are indexed for search.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <b>Application metadata</b>: To facilitate
                    interchange of applications, the EXPath Community has created a specification
                    for application metadata, called EXPath Packaging System. eXist supports and
                    extends this module. This tutorial will not cover this file's structure, but you
                    can learn more about this by reading about the <xref href="repo" scope="external">Package
                        Repository</xref>. </p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>You are always free to change the names of the collection or the queries, but as
            mentioned above, you will have to take responsibility for your own frameworks and you
            may lose some of the benefits of using the common conventions. The reason for using a
            generic file name such as <ph>list-items.xq</ph> instead of a filename that reflects
            the data, such as <ph>list-terms.xq</ph>, may not be clear to you at first, but as
            you will see later, this more general file naming convention has it merits when many
            applications are being managed. </p>
    </section>
        <section id="ex-business">
            <title>Example Data: Business Terms</title>
        

        <p>In this example we will use a simple registry of business terms that might be used in
            a glossary of terms on a web site. Each term will have (1) a numeric ID, (2) a term
            name, (3) a definition, and (4) a publish-status code of "draft," "under-review," or
            "published."</p>
        <p>To illustrate this structure, the following is a sample XML file for one of our terms: </p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;term&gt;
  &lt;id&gt;
    1
  &lt;/id&gt;
  &lt;term-name&gt;
    Declarative Programming
  &lt;/term-name&gt;
  &lt;definition&gt;
    A style of programming that allows users to declare their requirements (what they want done) and leave out the details of how the function should be performed.
  &lt;/definition&gt;
  &lt;publish-status-code&gt;
    published
  &lt;/publish-status-code&gt;
&lt;/term&gt;</pre>
        <p> We will create an application that will allow users to edit these terms on a simple
            form that will use a simple input field for the name, a text area for the definition,
            and a selection list for the status codes.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="views">
            <title>Views</title>
        

        <p>We will create two XQuery services for our initial XRX application. The first is a
            simple XQuery that will list all the terms in our data collection that have the root
            element <ph>term</ph>. The second is an XQuery function that shows an individual term.
            The second requires a single parameter which is the ID of the term. We will allow the
            user to drill down to see an individual term by first viewing a list of all the term in
            a collection.</p>

        

        <section id="list-item">
                <title>Listing Items</title>
            

            <p>Our first task will be to create a simple XQuery program that will list all the
                terms in our collection in an HTML file. To do this we will us a simple XQuery FLWOR
                loop that gets each of the terms in the collection in succession and then converts
                the XML into a HTML list item using the <ph>li</ph> tags. The convention to use in
                this example is the file name <ph>list-items.xq</ph>.</p>

            <p>
                    <ph>/db/apps/terms/views/list-items.xq</ph>: </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Glossary of Terms&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;h1&gt;Terms&lt;/h1&gt;
        &lt;ol&gt;
            {
                for $term in collection('/db/apps/terms/data')/term
                let $term-name := $term/term-name/text()
                order by $term-name
                return
                    &lt;li&gt;{$term-name}&lt;/li&gt;
            }
        &lt;/ol&gt;
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</pre>

            <p>This produces the following output:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/list-items-no-links.png"/>
                </fig>
            <p>There are few points to note here. First, we use the <ph>collection</ph>
                function to specify the location of the data is being listed. We also return only
                items in the data collection that have <ph>term</ph> as their root element. This
                allows us to put other data types within the data collection without disrupting this
                report.</p>
            <p>Our next step is to change each of the items listed into HTML links so that we can
                view each individual item on a separate HTML page. To do this we change this:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">&lt;li&gt;{$term-name}&lt;/li&gt;
</pre>
                <p> to be the following code:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">&lt;li&gt;
  &lt;a href="view-item.xq?id={$term/id/text()}"&gt;{$term-name}&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
</pre>
            <p>This produces the following output:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/list-items-links.png"/>
                </fig>
            <p>This has the effect of taking each term's ID and using it as a RESTful parameter,
                so that when a user selects this link, the link to the <ph>view-item.xq</ph>
                query will include the ID, and the query will know which term to display. We will
                use the same technique many times. Note that this uses a relative path to the
                <ph>view-item.xq</ph> program. So it is important to keep both the list items
                and the view items in the same collection for this to work correctly.</p>
            <p>Note that this works fine as long as we have just a few hundred terms. But as your
                collections get longer (usually above a few hundred items) you will want to add
                pagination. This is not covered here.</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="view-item">
                <title>Viewing an Individual Item</title>
            

            <p>Now that we have a list of all the items in a collection, we are ready to drill
                down to a specific item and see all of the information about a single item. By
                convention this is done by an XQuery file called <ph>view-item.xq</ph>. The item
                viewer takes a single parameter that is the ID of the item. It has to perform a
                query on all the items in the data collection to find only the item you are looking
                for. This is done by adding a predicate or <ph>where</ph> clause to the query.
                In general we prefer predicates because they are faster for eXist to process. The
                predicate that selects our desired term appears in the square brackets in the
                following expression:</p>
            <pre>let $term := collection('/db/apps/terms/data')/term[id='5']</pre>
            <p>Note that the predicate <ph>[id='5']</ph> indicates to the system that only a
                term with an ID of 5 should be returned. (Also note the quotes surrounding
                <ph>'5'</ph>, which indicate that we are doing simple string comparison, and not
                treating the IDs as integers.)</p>
            <p>Our next step is to get the parameter from the URL to select the correct item.
                This is done by using the function <ph>request:get-parameter</ph>. We then
                display all the elements of the term using one element per line. Here is what the
                source of the <ph>list-item.xq</ph> file looks like: </p>
            <p>
                    <ph>/db/apps/terms/views/view-item.xq</ph>
                </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $id := request:get-parameter("id", "")
let $term := collection('/db/apps/terms/data')/term[id = $id]
return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Term {$term/id/text()}&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Term {$term/id/text()}&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;dl&gt;
                &lt;dt&gt;Term ID:&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;{$term/id/text()}&lt;/dd&gt;
                &lt;dt&gt;Term Name:&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;{$term/term-name/text()}&lt;/dd&gt;
                &lt;dt&gt;Term Definition:&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;{$term/definition/text()}&lt;/dd&gt;
                &lt;dt&gt;Term Status:&lt;/dt&gt; &lt;dd&gt;{$term/publish-status-code/text()}&lt;/dd&gt;
            &lt;/dl&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
            <p>This produces the following output:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/view-item.png"/>
                </fig>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="search-item">
            <title>Searching Items</title>
        

        <p>There are three items that we create to support search functions. These items are
            the:</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>An HTML search form</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>A RESTful search service</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>A configuration file for defining the indexes</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
        <p>There are two types of indexes we will create. Structural indexes are configured to
            work with specific XML structures such as IDs. Fulltext indexes are used by eXist to
            make keyword searches very fast. These both work by indexing new content and optimizing
            the indexes for fast retrieval. Queries can run quickly and efficiently against the
            indexes rather than iterating through all files in the collection. In addition to the
            three files above, we therefore also have a script that reindexes the collection of
            terms. </p>

        

        <section id="search-config">
                <title>Search Configuration File</title>
            

            <p>The following is a search configuration file that we store in the collection
                <ph>/db/system/config/db/apps/term/data</ph>.</p>
            <p>
                    <ph>/db/system/config/db/apps/term/data/collection.xconf</ph>
                </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;collection xmlns="http://exist-db.org/collection-config/1.0"&gt;
  &lt;index xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"&gt;
    &lt;!-- Lucene index configuration --&gt;
    &lt;lucene&gt;
      &lt;!-- Use the standard analyzer will ignore stopwords like 'the', 'and' --&gt;
      &lt;analyzer class="org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer"/&gt;
      &lt;!-- an index boost can be used to give matches in the name a higher score. This means a name match will have higher rank then an match in the definition. --&gt;
      &lt;text match="//term/term-name" boost="2"/&gt;
      &lt;text match="//term/definition"/&gt;
      &lt;text match="//term/publish-status-code"/&gt;
    &lt;/lucene&gt;
    &lt;!-- Range index configuration on the id attribute --&gt;
    &lt;!-- Most ids are integers but we will keep this general &lt;create qname="id" type="xs:int"/&gt; --&gt;
    &lt;range&gt;
      &lt;create qname="id" type="xs:string"/&gt;
    &lt;/range&gt;
  &lt;/index&gt;
&lt;/collection&gt;</pre>
            <p>This configuration file creates an index for the term ID for fast searching. It
                also creates a Lucene full text index for all words in the term name, term
                definition and term publish-status-code. (By using the repo.xml Deployment
                Descriptor's "prepare" field, you can automate the installation of this
                collection.xconf file into the target location; see <xref href="repo#D1.4.10" scope="external"/>.)</p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="re-index">
                <title>Re-indexing</title>
            

            <p>After you have created or modified your collection configuration file, you must
                re-index any data that you have. This can be done by executing the following two
                XQuery lines (supplying your eXist administrative user's password in place of
                <ph>myadminpassword</ph>, since reindexing requires administrative
                privileges):</p>

            <pre>xmldb:login('/db/apps/terms/data', 'admin', 'myadminpassword'),
xmldb:reindex('/db/apps/terms/data')</pre>
            <p>You can run this query directly in eXide, or you can also store the following
                XQuery script in the app's <ph>admin</ph> collection and call it via your
                browser. The script will login as the administrator and then run the
                <ph>xmldb:reindex</ph> function on the data collection. It also returns the time
                used to reindex the collection. For collections that are under 1,000 medium sized
                10K byte documents, this script usually runs in a few seconds. Tools are available
                for larger collections to schedule indexing during off hours with the eXist job
                scheduler.</p>
            <p>
                    <ph>/db/apps/terms/admin/reindex.xq</ph>
                </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'

let $login := xmldb:login($data-collection, 'admin', 'myadminpassword')
let $start-time := util:system-time()
let $reindex := xmldb:reindex($data-collection)
let $runtime-ms := ((util:system-time() - $start-time) div xs:dayTimeDuration('PT1S')) * 1000
return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Reindex&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Reindex&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;The index for {$data-collection} was updated in {$runtime-ms} milliseconds.&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;App Home&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
            <p>The result will be:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/reindex-result.png"/>
                </fig>
        </section>

        

        <section id="search-form">
                <title>The Search Form</title>
            

            <p>The search form is a simple HTML form with one text field input and one submit
                button. The action of this form will use the value in the input field and send the
                field in the <ph>q</ph> parameter to the search service.</p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/search/search-form.html</ph> </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;
      Search Terms
    &lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h2&gt;
      Search Terms
    &lt;/h2&gt;
    &lt;form method="GET" action="search.xq"&gt;
      &lt;label for="q"&gt;
        Search:
      &lt;/label&gt;
      &lt;input type="text" id="q" name="q" size="30"/&gt;
      &lt;input type="submit" value="Search"/&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</pre>
            <p>The following image shows a blank search screen form. To perform a search, the
                user simply enters one or more keywords into the search form and clicks the search
                button (or presses the enter key):</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/search.png"/>
                </fig>
            <p>If you put a keyword in the input field, your browser will request the following
                URL:</p>
            <pre>/db/apps/terms/search/search.xq?q=mykeyword</pre>
        </section>

        

        <section id="search-service">
                <title>The Search Service</title>
            

            <p>The search service is an XQuery script that calls the full-text search
                function.</p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/search/search.xq</ph>: </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'
let $q := request:get-parameter('q', "")
let $search-results := collection($data-collection)/term[ft:query(*, $q)]
let $count := count($search-results)
return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Term Search Results&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h3&gt;Term Search Results&lt;/h3&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Search results for:&lt;/b&gt; &amp;quot;{$q}&amp;quot;&lt;b&gt; in collection: &lt;/b&gt;{$data-collection}&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Terms Found:&lt;/b&gt; {$count}&lt;/p&gt;
            &lt;ol&gt;
                {
                    for $term in $search-results
                    let $id := $term/id
                    let $term-name := $term/term-name/text()
                    order by upper-case($term-name)
                    return
                        &lt;li&gt;
                            &lt;a href="../views/view-item.xq?id={$id}"&gt;{$term-name}&lt;/a&gt;
                        &lt;/li&gt;
                }
            &lt;/ol&gt;
            &lt;a href="search-form.html"&gt;New Search&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;a href="../index.html"&gt;App Home&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
        </section>

        

        <section id="search-results">
                <title>Search Results</title>
            

            <p>The form will then pass the search keyword(s) to the search service. The search
                service will return a series of search results, with one result per hit. Each result
                is also a link to the item-viewer service.</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/search-results.png"/>
                </fig>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="editing">
            <title>Editing</title>
        

        <p>Editing data is the most complex portion of building an XRX application. We will learn
            how to create a form for users to edit the data and corresponding queries that take the
            form data and write it to the database. Because of the complexity of creating these
            interfaces, some advanced XRX frameworks automate this process by generating all of the
            required files. However, this sample "business terms" app is simple enough that we can
            create these files from scratch.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="edit-query">
            <title>The Edit Query</title>
        

        <p>The Edit query is the most complex file in this application. It must perform saves for
            new items as well as update operations. The following source code should be studied
            carefully since many of the techniques used in the form will be used in more complex
            forms. </p>

        

        <section id="model-view">
                <title>Model-View-Binding</title>
            

            <p>To understand how the edit.xq script works it is first important to understand how
                the XForms standard uses Model-View-Binding to associate a user interface control
                with an XML instance inside the model. This is illustrated in the figure
                below:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/model-view-bindings.png"/>
                </fig>
            <p>In the form, the XML data that the form allows the user to modify is loaded into
                an <ph>xs:instance</ph> element within the <ph>xf:model</ph>. This is specified
                using the <ph>src</ph> attribute. Inside the body of the form, each of the user
                interface controls (an <ph>output</ph>, <ph>input</ph>,
                <ph>textarea</ph> and <ph>select1</ph> control) have a <ph>ref</ph>
                attribute. This attribute contains the XPath expression of the element it
                corresponds to within the model.</p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/edit.xq</ph>:</p>

            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/xml indent=yes process-xsl-pi=no";

let $new := request:get-parameter('new', '')
let $id := request:get-parameter('id', '')
let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'
let $file := 
    if ($new ne '') then
        'new-instance.xml'
    else
        concat('../data/', $id, '.xml')
let $form :=
    &lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
        xmlns:xf="http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms"
        xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema"
        xmlns:ev="http://www.w3.org/2001/xml-events"&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Edit Item&lt;/title&gt;
            &lt;style type="text/css"&gt;
                &lt;![CDATA[
                    @namespace xf url("http://www.w3.org/2002/xforms");
             
                    body {
                        font-family: Helvetica, Ariel, Verdana, sans-serif;
                    }
             
                    .term-name .xforms-value {width: 50ex;}
                    .definition .xforms-value {
                        height: 5em;
                        width: 600px;
                    }
                        
                    /* align the labels but not the save label */
                    xf|output xf|label, xf|input xf|label, xf|textarea xf|label, xf|select1 xf|label {
                        display: inline-block;
                        width: 14ex;
                        text-align: right;
                        vertical-align: top;
                        margin-right: 1ex;
                        font-weight: bold;
                    }
             
                    xf|input, xf|select1, xf|textarea, xf|ouptut {
                        display: block;
                        margin: 1ex;
                    }
                ]]&gt;
            &lt;/style&gt;
            &lt;xf:model&gt;
                &lt;xf:instance xmlns="" src="{$file}" id="save-data"/&gt;
                &lt;xf:submission id="save" method="post" action="{
                        if ($new eq 'true') then
                            'save-new.xq'
                        else
                            'update.xq'
                    }" instance="my-task" replace="all"/&gt;
            &lt;/xf:model&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Edit Term&lt;/h1&gt;
            {
                if ($id) then
                    &lt;xf:output ref="id" class="id"&gt;
                        &lt;xf:label&gt;ID:&lt;/xf:label&gt;
                    &lt;/xf:output&gt;
                else
                    ()
            }
            &lt;xf:input ref="term-name" class="term-name"&gt;
                &lt;xf:label&gt;Term Name:&lt;/xf:label&gt;
            &lt;/xf:input&gt;
            &lt;xf:textarea ref="definition" class="definition"&gt;
                &lt;xf:label&gt;Definition:&lt;/xf:label&gt;
            &lt;/xf:textarea&gt;
            &lt;xf:select1 ref="publish-status-code"&gt;
                &lt;xf:label&gt;Status:&lt;/xf:label&gt;
                &lt;xf:item&gt;
                    &lt;xf:label&gt;Draft&lt;/xf:label&gt;
                    &lt;xf:value&gt;draft&lt;/xf:value&gt;
                &lt;/xf:item&gt;
                &lt;xf:item&gt;
                    &lt;xf:label&gt;Under Review&lt;/xf:label&gt;
                    &lt;xf:value&gt;review&lt;/xf:value&gt;
                &lt;/xf:item&gt;
                &lt;xf:item&gt;
                    &lt;xf:label&gt;Published&lt;/xf:label&gt;
                    &lt;xf:value&gt;published&lt;/xf:value&gt;
                &lt;/xf:item&gt;
            &lt;/xf:select1&gt;
            &lt;xf:submit submission="save"&gt;
                &lt;xf:label&gt;Save&lt;/xf:label&gt;
            &lt;/xf:submit&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;
let $xslt-pi := processing-instruction xml-stylesheet {'type="text/xsl" href="/exist/apps/xsltforms/xsltforms.xsl"'}
return
    (
        (: Prevent betterFORM (still enabled by default) from intercepting the form, allowing XSLTForms to handle it :)
        request:set-attribute("betterform.filter.ignoreResponseBody", "true"),
        $xslt-pi, 
        $form
    )</pre>
            <p>Note that this form does "double duty" as both a form for new items and a form for
                updating existing items. The <ph>new=true</ph> parameter must always be passed
                to the form when creating a new item. (A more sophisticated production systems would
                check for these parameters and return error codes if one or the other is not passed
                to the form.) In order to create the new item, the form fetches a document
                containing blank fields to be used as a template for the form.</p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/new-instance.xml</ph>:</p>

            <pre>&lt;term&gt;
  &lt;id/&gt;
  &lt;term-name/&gt;
  &lt;definition/&gt;
  &lt;publish-status-code/&gt;
&lt;/term&gt;</pre>
            <p>All XForms hold the form data in the <ph>xf:model</ph> element. This form uses a
                single <ph>xf:instance</ph> element within the model to store the data that will
                saved when the user clicks the "Save" button. The Save button in XForms is called
                the <ph>xf:submit</ph> element. It has a single <ph>submission</ph> attribute
                that is associated with an <ph>xf:submission</ph> element within the model. In our
                example above the name of the submission element (its <ph>id</ph>) is
                <ph>save</ph>. The save submission element is responsible for sending the data
                from the XForms client to a specific service on the server. In the example above
                there are two slightly different XQuery services, one for saving new items and one
                for updating existing items. We will be covering the save-new and the update queries
                later in this tutorial.</p>
            <p>The query that is used is wrapped inside of the <ph>action</ph> attribute of
                the save submission. Here is the portion from <ph>edit.xq</ph> with this code: </p>
            <pre>action="{
    if ($new='true') then 
        'save-new.xq'
    else 
        'update.xq'
}"</pre>
            <p>You can see that if the user is creating a new item the data is sent via an HTTP
                POST request to the <ph>save-new.xq</ph> query. If the user does not have a new
                item the POST data is sent to the <ph>update.xq</ph> query.</p>
            <p>Although we could have used a single <ph>save.xq</ph> query, this structure
                allows you to trigger different behavior for different functions you may want. For
                example, <ph>save-new.xq</ph> might also trigger an e-mail notification when new
                records are saved for the first time, or a versioning routine might be triggered
                only when the file is updated. </p>
            <p>The next section of code to notice is that the ID element is only displayed using
                a read-only <ph>xf:output</ph> element if the form is in update mode.</p>
            <pre>if ($id) then
    &lt;xf:output ref="id" class="id"&gt;
        &lt;xf:label&gt;ID:&lt;/xf:label&gt;
    &lt;/xf:output&gt;
else 
    ()</pre>
            <p>This shows some of the power of combining XQuery and XForms. In this case we are
                using logic on the server to conditionally include portions of the form based on the
                context. Contextual indicators such as user, group, and role can be harnessed to
                dynamically create forms around the needs of your users. We can use both client and
                server logic to determine what features of the form are enabled. (XForms includes a
                useful function called <ph>xf:bind</ph> that uses XPath expressions to determine
                if certain fields should be displayed.)</p>
            <p>Note that there are four different user interface controls in this form. The first
                one is a read-only output. The second is the <ph>xf:input</ph> control that
                gathers input in a single line. The third is a <ph>xf:textarea</ph> control that
                allows users to enter multi-line descriptions for definitions of terms. The last
                control is the <ph>xf:select1</ph> control that allows the user to select one
                value from a list of values. (For a complete discussion of the XForms controls we
                suggest you use the XForms Wikibook at <xref href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XForms" scope="external">http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XForms</xref>. The Input Form Controls section goes
                through each of the controls in the XForms specification. In addition to the
                standard controls there are other controls that can also be integrated directly into
                XForms, such as rich-text editors.)</p>
            <p>Each of the input controls has a <ph>ref</ph> attribute that indicates which
                element in the instance it is bound to. If you have multiple instances and multiple
                models you may not be able to use all the default values as in this example. This
                ref attribute is how leaf elements the model get bound to each input control. In
                general, when you are building simple, flat forms there is a one-to-one
                correspondence between the form elements and the instances in the model. Complex
                forms also allow you to have repeating elements so you can add one-to-many
                structures in a form. This means that XForms are not restricted to managing a flat
                list of elements. They can contain multiple nested elements with elements. </p>
            <p>The final part of the form contains the instructions needed to place the XSLTForms
                processing instruction at the top of the file when it is rendered.</p>
            <pre>let $xslt-pi := processing-instruction xml-stylesheet {'type="text/xsl" href="/exist/apps/xsltforms/xsltforms.xsl"'}
return ($xslt-pi, $form)</pre>
            <p>You can also add a directive that will put the XSLTForms system into a debug mode
                by adding the following:</p>
            <pre>let $debug := processing-instruction xsltforms-options {'debug="yes"'}
return ($xslt-pi, $debug, $form)</pre>
        </section>

        

        <section id="save-item">
                <title>Saving New Items</title>
            

            <p>The save new item process must first access the XML file that stores the next ID
                to be used to create a unique file name. We store the next ID to be used in a small
                XML file with only one element in the root called <b>next-id</b>. Here is that file: </p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/next-id.xml</ph>: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;data&gt;
  &lt;next-id&gt;
    6
  &lt;/next-id&gt;
&lt;/data&gt;</pre>
            <p>The <ph>next-id</ph> element is updated using an XQuery "update function" when
                new items are saved to the data collection. We save the file using the number as the
                filename; in this case, the next file saved will be <ph>6.xml</ph>. After the
                file is saved, the "next-id" number is incremented to 7. (This is similar to the
                auto-increment function in many other databases. Using an arbitrary number as an ID
                is sometimes called a "surrogate key" since it is external to the actual data in the
                XML file.)</p>

            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/save-new.xq</ph>: </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";
 
let $app-collection := '/db/apps/terms'
let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'
 
(: get the form data that has been "POSTed" to this XQuery :)
let $item := request:get-data()
 
(: get the next ID from the next-id.xml file :)
let $next-id-file-path := concat($app-collection, '/edit/next-id.xml')
let $next-id := doc($next-id-file-path)/data/next-id/text() 
let $file := concat($next-id, '.xml')

(: log into the collection :)
let $login := xmldb:login($app-collection, 'admin', 'myadminpassword')

(: create the new file with a still-empty id element :)
let $store := xmldb:store($data-collection, $file, $item)
let $new-document := doc(concat($data-collection, '/', $file))

(: add the correct ID to the new document we just saved :)
let $update-id := update value $new-document/term/id with $next-id

(: update the next-id.xml file :)
let $new-next-id :=  update value $next-id with $next-id + 1

(: we need to return the original ID number in our results, 
   but the previous update expression increased $next-id by 1 :)
let $original-id := $next-id - 1

return
&lt;html&gt;
    &lt;head&gt;
        &lt;title&gt;Save Conformation&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;/head&gt;
    &lt;body&gt;
        &lt;a href="../index.xhtml"&gt;Term Home&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Term {$original-id} has been saved.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;a href="../views/list-items.xq"&gt;List all Terms&lt;/a&gt; 
    &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</pre>
        </section>

        

        <section id="update-item">
                <title>Updating Existing Items</title>
            

            <p>The update function is simpler than the save function, since it does not have to
                worry about creating a new file and incrementing a counter. It simply takes the
                incoming POST data and stores it in the file. Note that by default this means that
                the entire data file is updated and re-indexed upon the store operation. </p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/update.xq</ph>:</p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $title := 'Update Confirmation'
let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'

(: get the form data that has been "POSTed" to this XQuery :)
let $item := request:get-data()

(: log into the collection :)
let $login := xmldb:login($data-collection, 'admin', 'myadminpassword')

(: get the id out of the posted document :)
let $id := $item/term/id/text()

let $file := concat($id, '.xml')

(: save the new file, overwriting the old one :)
let $store := xmldb:store($data-collection, $file, $item)

return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;{$title}&lt;/title&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;{$title}&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;p&gt;Item {$id} has been updated.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="delete-item">
            <title>Deleting</title>
        

        <p>Deleting items is even simpler than editing items. There are only two files that we
            will need to create. Each of them takes a single REST parameter. The first file is a
            confirmation XQuery script that just asks the user "Are you sure you want to delete this
            term?" The second script actually performs the deletion.</p>

        

        <section id="confirm">
                <title>Confirming Delete</title>
            

            <p>The delete confirmation script takes the ID of the item to be deleted and selects
                the document using the <ph>doc()</ph> function. It then presents the user with
                details about the item and displays two choices. One to delete and the other to
                cancel the action. A CSS file can be used to color the links appropriately with a
                red warning indicator.</p>
            <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/delete-confirm.xq</ph>: </p>
            <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $id := request:get-parameter('id', '')
let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data/'
let $doc := concat($data-collection, $id, '.xml')

return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Delete Confirmation&lt;/title&gt;
            &lt;style&gt;
                &lt;![CDATA[
                    .warn {
                        background-color: silver; color: black; font-size: 16pt; 
                        line-height: 24pt; padding: 5pt; border: solid 2px black; 
                        }
                ]]&gt;
            &lt;/style&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;a href="../index.xhtml"&gt;Item Home&lt;/a&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;a href="../views/list-items.xq"&gt;List Items&lt;/a&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Are you sure you want to delete this term?&lt;/h1&gt;
            &lt;strong&gt;Name:&lt;/strong&gt; {doc($doc)/term/term-name/text()}&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;strong&gt;Path:&lt;/strong&gt; {$doc}&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;a class="warn" href="delete.xq?id={$id}"&gt;Yes - Delete This Term&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;a class="warn" href="../views/view-item.xq?id={$id}"&gt;Cancel (Back to View Term)&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="delete-scripts">
            <title>The Delete Script</title>
        

        <p>The delete script also takes a single REST parameter of the ID</p>
        <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/edit/delete.xq</ph>: </p>
        <pre>xquery version "1.0";

declare option exist:serialize "method=xhtml media-type=text/html indent=yes";

let $data-collection := '/db/apps/terms/data'

(: get the id parameter from the URL :)
let $id := request:get-parameter('id', '')

(: log into the collection :)
let $login := xmldb:login($data-collection, 'admin', 'myadminpassword')

(: construct the filename from the id :)
let $file := concat($id, '.xml')

(: delete the file :)
let $store := xmldb:remove($data-collection, $file)

return
    &lt;html&gt;
        &lt;head&gt;
            &lt;title&gt;Delete Term&lt;/title&gt;
            &lt;style&gt;
                &lt;![CDATA[
                    .warn {
                        background-color: silver; color: black; font-size: 16pt; 
                        line-height: 24pt; padding: 5pt; border:solid 2px black;
                    }
                ]]&gt;
            &lt;/style&gt;
        &lt;/head&gt;
        &lt;body&gt;
            &lt;a href="../index.xhtml"&gt;Terms Home&lt;/a&gt; &amp;gt; &lt;a href="../views/list-items.xq"&gt;List Terms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
            &lt;h1&gt;Term id {$id} has been removed.&lt;/h1&gt;
        &lt;/body&gt;
    &lt;/html&gt;</pre>
    </section>
        <section id="app-hp">
            <title>The Application Home Page</title>
        

        <p>A simple application home page can be a description of the application and a static
            list of links to the main entry points of the application: the item listener, the search
            form, the create new and the re-index. The index page can be a static HTML page as
            describe below.</p>
        <p> <ph>/db/apps/terms/index.html</ph>: </p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;html&gt;
  &lt;head&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;
      Terms
    &lt;/title&gt;
  &lt;/head&gt;
  &lt;body&gt;
    &lt;h1&gt;
      Terms
    &lt;/h1&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a href="views/list-items.xq"&gt;
          List Items
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a href="search/search-form.html"&gt;
          Search
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a href="edit/edit.xq?new=true"&gt;
          Create New Term
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;a href="admin/reindex.xq"&gt;
          Reindex the collection
        &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;</pre>
        <fig>
                <image href="assets/index.png"/>
            </fig>
    </section>
        <section id="next-steps">
            <title>Next Steps</title>
        

        <p>As you have now learned all of the CRUDS functions, you are ready to move on the some
            more complex examples. Here are some suggestions for next steps you can take. </p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Create an XQuery module to centralize some of the common code and reduce
                    duplication and then reference these functions in each of your queries. For
                    example, you could put the HTML boilerplate into a style module. You could also
                    explore eXist's <xref href="templating" scope="external">HTML templating module</xref>.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Change the <ph>list-items.xq</ph> to use HTML tables to view each
                    item.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Use the eXist permission system to create a group called "term-editor" and a
                    group called "term-admin". Change the group permissions on the edit and admin
                    collections to only allow users in these groups to be able to access these
                    collections.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>In the <ph>list-items.xq</ph> query, use XQuery sequences to pre-sort
                    items and then display only an initial subset of the data using the subsequence
                    function.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Add URL parameters <ph>start</ph> and <ph>per-page</ph> to the
                    list-items to indicate what record to start to display and how many records to
                    display.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Learn how to create one-to-many relationships in your forms using the
                    <ph>xf:repeat</ph> element. For example, create a form that allows you to add
                    multiple phone numbers to a contact record or multiple authors to a book
                    entry.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Learn how to use XForms binding to conditionally display elements in a
                    form.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Get fancy with how tables of data are displayed. Add sorting to table
                    columns.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Create forms that manage document work flows. Add work flow steps that flow to
                    the right as they expand.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Create advanced search forms that use multiple selection criteria such as
                    document types, authors or date ranges.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Create complex business logic in how selection lists can be controlled. Use
                    one selection list to control the values of a second selection list.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Move all of the codes in the publish-status selection list into an XML file
                    and place it in a collection called <ph>code-tables</ph>. Then add an
                    instance to the form that reads this code table into the form.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Write an XQuery function that will take a status code's value and return its
                    label.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Modify the collection configuration file for the
                    <ph>/db/apps/terms/data</ph> collection to enable versioning when items are
                    updated. See <xref href="versioning" scope="external">Versioning Extensions</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
        <section id="references">
            <title>References</title>
        

        <p>All of these topics and many more are covered in the XQuery, XForms and XRX Wikibooks.
            You can use the search tools within each Wikibook to find how specific elements are used
            within each of the examples.</p>
        <p>Wiki Books:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XForms" scope="external">XForms Wikibook</xref> </p>
                <p>Dan McCreary</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XRX" scope="external">XRX Wikibook</xref> </p>
                <p>Dan McCreary</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/XQuery" scope="external">XQuery Wikibook</xref> </p>
                <p>Chris Wallace; Dan McCreary</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
        <p>Articles:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XRX_%28web_application_architecture%29" scope="external">XRX (web application architecture)</xref> </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="http://news.oreilly.com/2008/07/xrx-xqueries-in-exist.html" scope="external">XRX: XQueries in eXist</xref> </p>
                <p>Jeni Tennison</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p> <xref href="http://www.oreillynet.com/xml/blog/2008/05/xrx_a_simple_elegant_disruptiv_1.html" scope="external">XRX: Simple, Elegant, Disruptive</xref> </p>
                <p>Dan McCreary</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
        <p>Books:</p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>XQuery</p>
                <p>Priscilla Walmsley (2007)</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>XForms Essentials</p>
                <p>Micah Dubinko (2003)</p>
            </li>
            </ul>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>