<topic id="update_ext">
    <title>XQuery Update Extension</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="xquery"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article describes eXist-db's extension to XQuery for updating nodes in the
        database.</p>
        <section id="considerations">
            <title>Important Considerations</title>
        
        <p>Two things you should take into account with respect to the updating extension.</p>
        

        <section id="w3c-rec">
                <title>Relationship to W3C Recommendation</title>
            

            <p>This extension was created well before the W3C working group created the <xref href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xquery-update-10/" scope="external">XQuery
                Update Facility 1.0</xref> recommendation and therefore differs substantially from
                it. </p>
        </section>

        

        <section id="persistence">
                <title>Persistent Document Updates</title>
            

            <p>The XQuery update extension was designed for updating
                <i>persistent</i> documents stored in the database. It does not work
                for updating temporary document fragments constructed within an query.</p>
            <p>For example: </p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">let $node := &lt;root&gt;&lt;a/&gt;&lt;/root&gt;
return 
    update insert &lt;b/&gt; into $node/a</pre>
            <p>Since <ph>$node</ph> is an in-memory constructed element (rather than a node
                stored in the database) the query has no effect and simply returns the empty
                element.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="syntax">
            <title>Update Syntax</title>
        

        <p>All update statements start with the keyword <ph>update</ph>, followed by an
            update action.</p>
        <p>Available actions are: <ph>insert</ph>, <ph>delete</ph>, <ph>replace</ph>,
            <ph>value</ph> and <ph>rename</ph>. The return type of an update expression is
            <ph>empty-sequence()</ph>. </p>
        <p>An update statement may occur at any position within the XQuery main code or a
            function body. </p>
        <note type="warning">
                <p>When using <ph>update</ph> within the return clause of a FLWOR expression, be
                cautious when deleting or replacing nodes that are still being used by the enclosing
                code. This is because a delete or replace will be processed immediately, and so the
                deleted or replaced node will no longer be available to the query. <i>Such
                actions can corrupt the database!</i> </p>
                <p>For example, the following expression will throw the database into an inconsistent
                state if <ph>//address</ph> returns more than one node:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">for $address in //address
return
    update delete //address</pre>
                <p>However, an expression like the following is safe as it only modifies the current
                iteration variable. The following example only deletes <ph>$address</ph> (the
                current iteration variable) instead of <ph>//address</ph> (all addresses in the
                database):</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">for $address in //address
return
    update delete $address</pre>
            </note>

        

        <section id="insert">
                <title>Insert</title>
            

            <pre>update insert expr ( into | following | preceding )
                exprSingle</pre>
            <p>Inserts the content sequence specified in <ph>expr</ph> into the element node
                passed via <ph>exprSingle</ph>. <ph>exprSingle</ph> and <ph>expr</ph>
                must evaluate to a node set. If <ph>exprSingle</ph> contains more than one
                element node, the modification will be applied to each of the nodes. The position of
                the insertion is determined by the keywords <ph>into</ph>,
                <ph>following</ph> or <ph>preceding</ph>:</p>
            <dl>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>into</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>The content is appended after the last child node of the specified
                            elements.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>following</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>The content is inserted immediately after the node specified in
                            <ph>exprSingle</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                    <dlentry>
                        <dt>
                            <ph>preceding</ph>
                        </dt>
                        <dd>
                        <p>The content is inserted before the node specified in
                            <ph>exprSingle</ph>.</p>
                    </dd>
                    </dlentry>
                </dl>
            <section>
                    <title>Insert Example: Element</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">update insert &lt;email type="office"&gt;andrew@gmail.com&lt;/email&gt; into //address[fname="Andrew"]</pre>
                </section>
            <section>
                    <title>Insert Example: Attribute</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">update insert attribute type {'permanent'} into //address[fname="Andrew"]</pre>
                </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="replace">
                <title>Replace</title>
            

            <pre>update replace expr with exprSingle</pre>
            <p>Replaces the nodes returned by <ph>expr</ph> with the nodes in
                <ph>exprSingle</ph>. <ph>expr</ph> must evaluate to a single element,
                attribute or text node. If it is an element, <ph>exprSingle</ph> must contain a
                single element node. If it is an attribute or text node, the value of the attribute
                or the text node is set to the concatenated string values of all nodes in
                <ph>exprSingle</ph>. <ph>expr</ph> cannot be the root element of a
                document.</p>
            <section>
                    <title>Replace Example</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">update replace //fname[. = "Andrew"] with &lt;fname&gt;Andy&lt;/fname&gt;</pre>
                </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="value">
                <title>Value</title>
            

            <pre>update value expr with exprSingle</pre>
            <p>Updates the content of all nodes in <ph>expr</ph> with the items in
                <ph>exprSingle</ph>. If <ph>expr</ph> is an attribute or text node, its
                value will be set to the concatenated string value of all items in
                <ph>exprSingle</ph>.</p>
            <section>
                    <title>Value Example</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">update value //fname[. = "Andrew"] with 'Andy'</pre>
                </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="delete">
                <title>Delete</title>
            

            <pre>update delete expr</pre>
            <p>Removes all nodes in <ph>expr</ph> from their document. <ph>expr</ph>
                cannot be the root element of a document.</p>
            <section>
                    <title>Delete Example</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">for $city in //address/city 
return
    update delete $city</pre>
                </section>
        </section>

        

        <section id="rename">
                <title>Rename</title>
            

            <pre>update rename expr as exprSingle</pre>
            <p>Renames the nodes in <ph>expr</ph> using the string value of the first item in
                <ph>exprSingle</ph> as the new name of the node. <ph>expr</ph> should
                evaluate to a set of elements or attributes. <ph>expr</ph> cannot be the root
                element of a document.</p>
            <section>
                    <title>Rename Example</title>
                    <pre outputclass="xquery">for $city in //address/city 
return
    update rename $city as 'locale'</pre>
                </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>