<topic id="kwic">
    <title>KWIC (Keywords in Context) Output</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q18"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="xquery"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>Keywords In Context (KWIC) helps users to quickly scan through search results by listing
        hits surrounded by their context. eXist provides a KWIC module that is not bound to a
        specific index or query operation. It but can be applied to query results from all indexes
        that support match highlighting. This includes the Lucene-based index and the ngram
        index.</p>
        <p>The documentation search function on eXist's home page is a good example. It queries
        documents written in DocBook format. However, the KWIC module has also been successfully
        used with different schemas (e.g. TEI) and languages (e.g. Chinese).</p>
        <section id="using">
            <title>Using the Module</title>
        

        <p>The KWIC module is entirely written in XQuery. To use the module, import its namespace
            into your query (you don't need to specify a location):</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace kwic="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic";</pre>

        <p>The easiest way to get KWIC output is to call the <ph>kwic:summarize</ph>
            function on an element node returned from a full text or ngram query:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace kwic="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic";
for $hit in doc("/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml")//SPEECH[ft:query(., "'nature'")] 
order by ft:score($hit) descending
return
    kwic:summarize($hit, &lt;config width="40"/&gt;)</pre>
        <p>Every call to <ph>kwic:summarize</ph> will return an HTML paragraph
            containing 3 <ph>span</ph> elements with the text before and after each match, as
            well as the match text itself:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;p&gt;
  &lt;span class="previous"&gt;
    ... s effect, sir; after what flourish your
  &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="hi"&gt;
    nature
  &lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="following"&gt;
    will.
  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</pre>

        <p>The <ph>config</ph> element, passed to <ph>kwic:summarize</ph> (as second
            parameter) determines the appearance of the generated HTML. It recognizes 3
            attributes:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>width</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The maximum number of characters to be printed before and after the
                        match</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>table</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>By default <ph>kwic:summarize</ph> returns an HTML paragraph
                        with spans.</p>
                    <p>If <ph>table="yes"</ph> it will return an HTML <i>table
                        row</i> <ph>tr</ph> element. The text chunks will be enclosed in a
                        table column <ph>td</ph> element.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>link</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>If present, each match will be enclosed within a link, using the URI in
                        the link attribute as target. 
                    </p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>

        <section id="call-back">
                <title>Using a callback function for more fine-grained control</title>
            

            <p>If you look at the output of query above you may notice that a space is missing
                between words if the previous or following chunk extends to a different
                <ph>LINE</ph> element. And it would also be nicer to display text from
                <ph>LINE</ph> elements only and to ignore <ph>SPEAKER</ph> or
                <ph>STAGEDIR</ph> elements. This can be achieved with the help of a callback
                function:</p>
            <pre outputclass="xquery">import module namespace kwic="http://exist-db.org/xquery/kwic";
                
declare function local:filter($node as node(), $mode as xs:string) as xs:string? {
  if ($node/parent::SPEAKER or $node/parent::STAGEDIR) then 
      ()
  else if ($mode eq 'before') then 
      concat($node, ' ')
  else 
      concat(' ', $node)
};

for $hit in doc("/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml")//SPEECH[ft:query(., "'nature'")] 
order by ft:score($hit) descending
return
kwic:summarize($hit, &lt;config width="40"/&gt;, local:filter#2)
</pre>
            <p>The third parameter to <ph>kwic:summarize</ph> here is a reference to a
                function accepting 2 arguments:</p>
            <ol>
                    <li>
                    <p>A single text node which should be appended or prepended to the current
                        text chunk</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>A string indicating the current direction in which text is appended:
                        <ph>before</ph> or <ph>after</ph>.</p>
                </li>
                </ol>


            <p>The function can return the empty sequence if the current node should be ignored
                (for instance if it belongs to a footnote which should not be displayed). Otherwise
                it must return a single string.</p>
            <p>The <ph>local:filter</ph> function above first checks if the passed node
                has a SPEAKER or STAGEDIR parent. If so, it <i>ignores</i> that node
                by returning the empty sequence. If not, the function adds a single whitespace
                before or after the string, so adjacent lines will be properly separated.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="advanced">
            <title>Advanced Use</title>
        

        <p>Using <ph>kwic:summarize</ph>, you will get one KWIC-formatted item for
            every match, even if the matches are in the same paragraph. Also, the context from which
            the text is taken is always the same: the element you queried. To get more control over
            the output, you can directly call <ph>kwic:get-summary</ph>, which is the
            module's core function. </p>
        <p>
                <ph>kwic:get-summary</ph> expects 3 or 4 parameters. </p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>The current context root</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>The match object to process</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Parameters 3 and 4 are the same as for
                    <ph>kwic:summarize</ph>
                    </p>
            </li>
            </ul>

        <p>Before passing nodes to <ph>kwic:get-summary</ph> you have to
            <i>expand</i> them, which basically means to create an in-memory copy in
            which all matches are properly marked up with <ph>exist:match</ph> tags. The main part
            of the query should look as follows:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">for $hit in doc("/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml")//SPEECH[ft:query(., "'nature'")]
let $expanded := kwic:expand($hit)
order by ft:score($hit) descending
return
    kwic:get-summary($expanded, ($expanded//exist:match)[1], &lt;config width="40"/&gt;,
        local:filter#2)
</pre>
        <p>In this example, we select the first <ph>exist:match</ph> only, thus ignoring all
            other matches within <ph>$expanded</ph>.</p>

        <p>Sometimes you may also want to change the context to restrict the KWIC display to
            certain elements within the larger query context, for instance paragraphs within
            sections. The following example still queries <ph>SPEECH</ph> but displays a KWIC
            entry for each <ph>LINE</ph> with a match, grouped by speech:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">for $hit in doc("/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml")//SPEECH[ft:query(., "nature")]
let $expanded := kwic:expand($hit)
order by ft:score($hit) descending
return
    &lt;div class="speech"&gt;{
        for $line in $expanded//LINE[.//exist:match]
        return
            kwic:get-summary($line, ($line/exist:match)[1], &lt;config width="40"/&gt;,
                local:filter#2)
    }&lt;/div&gt;
</pre>
        <p>You might wonder why we don't query <ph>LINE</ph> directly to get a different
            context, as in:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">//SPEECH[ft:query(LINE, "nature")]</pre>
        <p>This is because Lucene computes the relevance of each match with respect to the SPEECH
            context, not LINE. If we queried LINE, each single line would get a match score and the
            matches would end up in a completely different order.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="highlight">
            <title>Marking up Matches without using KWIC</title>
        

        <p>Sometimes you don't want to use the KWIC module, but still would like an indication
            where matches were found in the text. eXist's XML serializer can automatically highlight
            matches when it writes out a piece of XML. All the matches will be surrounded by an
            <ph>exist:match</ph> tag.</p>
        <p>You can achieve the same within an XQuery by calling the extension function
            <ph>util:expand</ph>:</p>

        <pre outputclass="xquery">let $expanded := util:expand($hit, "expand-xincludes=no")
return $expanded//exist:match</pre>
        <p> <ph>util:expand</ph> returns a copy of the XML fragment it received in its
            first parameter, which, unless configured otherwise, has all matches wrapped into
            <ph>exist:match</ph> tags.</p>

        <p>Please note that <ph>util:expand</ph> will not expand matches in Lucene fields. 
        Use <ph>ft:highlight-field-matches</ph> instead. For more information, see <xref href="lucene.xml#expand-fields" scope="external">lucene.xml#expand-fields</xref>.</p>    
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>