<topic id="security">
    <title>Security</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article discusses eXist-db's security features and how to manage authentication,
        users, groups, passwords, permissions and access controls. </p>
        <p>eXist-db's security infrastructure is built on a Unix permissions model (see <xref href="#unix-model" scope="local"/>), which we have extended with <xref href="#ACLs" scope="local"/>. As far as
        possible we try and adhere to the POSIX standard. The security infrastructure is very
        flexible and extensible, which enables the more advanced user, to provide custom <xref href="#authentication-realms" scope="local"/> to enable different authentication models.</p>
        <p>As well as the mechanisms described in this article, you should also note the presence of
        the <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/securitymanager" scope="external">Security Manager XQuery library module</xref>, which enables you to perform many user and
        security related tasks programmatically from XQuery.</p>
        <section id="changing-admin-password">
            <title>Changing the Administrator Password</title>
        

        <p>When the database is started for the first time, two default users are created:
            <ph>admin</ph> and <ph>guest</ph>. The <ph>admin</ph> user is a member of
            the <ph>dba</ph> group, and therefore has administrative privileges; the
            <ph>guest</ph> user is a member of the group <ph>guest</ph> and is not an
            administrator, in fact it has the least privileges.</p>
        <p> At this point, the <ph>admin</ph> password is <i>empty</i>, and so
            access to the database is <i>initially granted to everyone</i>. </p>
        <p>To set restrictions on database access, first set a password for the
            <ph>admin</ph> user in one of the following ways: </p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>The <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref> GUI has a
                    dialog box for user management. To open this dialog box, enter
                    <ph>Ctrl-U</ph> or select <ph>Tools, Edit
                    Users</ph>:</p>
                <fig>
                        <image href="assets/client-5.png" width="50%"/>
                    </fig>
                <ol>
                        <li>
                        <p>At the top, select the <ph>admin</ph> user in the table of
                            users</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Type in your password into the corresponding fields</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Click the <ph>Modify User</ph> button to apply the
                            changes</p>
                    </li>
                    </ol>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>In the Dashboard's <xref href="{dashboard}" scope="external">User
                    manager</xref>, click on the user account that you wish to edit and type its
                    password twice. Confirm by clicking <ph>save</ph>.</p>
                <fig>
                        <image href="assets/usermanager.png" width="50%"/>
                    </fig>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Set a new administrator password on the command line in the console mode of
                    the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref>. Enter the
                    following at the command prompt:</p>
                <pre>type help or ? for help.
exist:/db&gt;passwd admin
password: somepass
re-enter password: somepass
exist:/db&gt;quit</pre>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Change the password programmatically, for instance from within eXide, by using
                    the <ph>sm:passwd()</ph> function of the <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/securitymanager" scope="external">Security Manager XQuery library module</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>

        <p>The other default user, <ph>guest</ph>, has the default password
            <ph>guest</ph>. The guest identity is internally assigned to all clients that have
            not authenticated themselves.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="creating-users">
            <title>Creating Users</title>
        

        <p>There are several ways to create new users:</p>

        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>Use the Dashboard's <xref href="{dashboard}" scope="external">User
                    manager</xref> to add a new user. Click on the big red
                    <ph>+</ph> button in the lower right-hand corner and fill in
                    the dialog.</p>
                <fig>
                        <image href="assets/usermanager2.png" width="50%"/>
                    </fig>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Use the GUI of the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin
                    Client</xref>. In the <ph>Edit users</ph> dialog box, fill in
                    the username, password, and home collection fields. Assign a group (or groups)
                    for the new user. Finally, select <ph>Create User</ph>. The
                    new user will appear in the list of users in the top panel.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>The console <ph>adduser</ph> of the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref> command also allows you to create additional users.
                    The command asks for a password and a list of groups to which the user should
                    belong. An example is shown below:</p>
                <pre>exist:/db/shakespeare&gt;adduser wolf
password: xxxxxxxx
re-enter password: xxxxxxxx
enter groups: users</pre>
                <p>You can list all the users using the <ph>users</ph> command.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Create a user programmatically, for instance from within eXide, by using the
                    <ph>sm:create-account()</ph> function of the <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/securitymanager" scope="external">Security Manager XQuery library module</xref>.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>


    </section>
        <section id="system-accounts-groups">
            <title>System Accounts and Groups</title>
        
        <p>eXist-db has several built-in accounts which ensure the correct functioning of the system. These accounts and groups cannot be removed, however the <ph>admin</ph> and <ph>guest</ph>
            accounts can be disabled if required.</p>
        <section id="system-users">
                <title>System Accounts</title>
            
            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Name</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>SYSTEM</stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                This is a DBA account under which the database executes internal privileged opertaions.
                                This account is not exported during backups.
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>admin</stentry>
                        <stentry>This is the default <ph>DBA</ph> account.</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>guest</stentry>
                        <stentry>This is the account under which operations by un-authenticated users will be executed, for example users connecting to the REST Server without authenticating.</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>nobody</stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                This is an internal account and should not be used directly.
                                This account is not exported during backups.
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
        </section>
        <section id="system-groups">
                <title>System Groups</title>
            
            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry>Name</stentry>
                        <stentry>Description</stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>DBA</stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                This is the DBA group, all DBA users should be members of this group.
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>guest</stentry>
                        <stentry>This is the <i>primary group</i> of the <ph>guest</ph>.</stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry>nogroup</stentry>
                        <stentry>
                                This is an internal group and should not be used directly. In the case that users without a
                                    <i>primary group</i> are imported from an older eXist-db backup, the users will be restored with this as their primary group.
                                This group is not exported during backups.
                            </stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="permissions">
            <title>Resource Permissions</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db supports both a Unix like permissions model and simple Access Control Lists.
            It is important to understand the Unix permission model first. Access Control Lists are
            useful if the Unix Model is insufficient for your application.</p>

        <section id="unix-model">
                <title>Unix Model</title>
            

            <p>The default that is based on the UNIX <b>read</b>,
                <b>write</b> and <b>execute</b>
                flags for <b>owner</b>, <b>group</b> and <b>world</b>.</p>
            <note type="note">
                    <p>In versions prior to eXist-db 2.0, there was no <b>execute</b> flag, rather an <b>update</b> flag
                    was present.</p>
                </note>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/owner-group-world.png" width="50%"/>
                </fig>
            <simpletable>
                    <sthead>
                        <stentry> Category </stentry>
                        <stentry> Description </stentry>
                    </sthead>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry> Owner </stentry>
                        <stentry> These permissions work for the owner of the
                                resource </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry> Group </stentry>
                        <stentry> These permissions work for the members of the group of the
                                resource </stentry>
                    </strow>
                    <strow>
                        <stentry> World </stentry>
                        <stentry> These permissions work for any user </stentry>
                    </strow>
                </simpletable>

            <note type="note">
                    <p>Be aware that permissions for collections are <i>not</i>
                    inherited by their sub-collections: write permissions can be set for
                    sub-collections, but you must also have write permissions for the parent
                    collection for these to be effective!</p>
                </note>
            <p>Using the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref> or its
                command line, you can list the permissions assigned to each resource (this assumes
                the <ph>permissions</ph> property in <ph>client.properties</ph>
                is set to <ph>true</ph>). For example:</p>
            <pre>exist:/db/shakespeare/plays&gt;ls
    -rwxr-xr--      admin   dba     hamlet.xml
    -rwxr-xr--      admin   dba     macbeth.xml
    -rwxr-xr--      wolf    users   r_and_j.xml
    -rwxr-xr--      admin   dba     shakes.xsl
    exist:/db/shakespeare/plays&gt;</pre>

            <p>The Java Admin Client displays resource permissions in a format similar to the
                output of the Unix <ph>ls -l</ph> command: a ten-character code.</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p> The first character represents the type of resource: </p>
                    <ul>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>-</ph> (hyphen) for documents</p>
                        </li>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>c</ph> for collections</p>
                        </li>
                        </ul>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>The next three characters are the permissions for the user. For normal
                        usage these are (for special usage see below):</p>
                    <ul>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>-</ph> (hyphen) for denied permissions</p>
                        </li>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>r</ph> for read</p>
                        </li>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>w</ph> for write</p>
                        </li>
                            <li>
                            <p> <ph>x</ph> for execute</p>
                        </li>
                        </ul>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>The next three characters (five through seven) set the permissions for
                        groups</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>The last three for others (i.e. anyone else who can access the database).
                    </p>
                </li>
                </ul>


            <p>The database root collection <ph>/db</ph> initially has its permissions
                set to <ph>drwxr-xr-x</ph>, so full access is granted to everyone. You
                might consider changing this.</p>
            <p> Also note that the default setting for all newly created resources is
                <ph>-rw-r--r--</ph>: the owner has read/write permissions, not execute.
                The group and others (world) have read permissions only.</p>

            <section id="change-perm">
                    <title>Changing Resource Permissions and Ownership</title>
                

                <note type="note">
                        <p>Please note that only the owner of a resource or members of the
                        <ph>dba</ph> group are allowed to change permissions. All other
                        users who attempt to change these settings will receive an error
                        message.</p>
                    </note>

                <p>To change permissions and/or ownership, use one of the following methods: </p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>Use the GUI of the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin
                            Client</xref>.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The command line of the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java
                            Admin Client</xref>:</p>
                        <pre>chmod [resource] [user|group|other]=[+|-][read|write|execute][, ...]</pre>
                        <pre>chown [user] [group] [resource]</pre>
                        <p>If you do not specify a resource in the first argument of the
                            <ph>chmod</ph> command, the permission string will be applied
                            to the <i>current collection</i>. This is an important
                            feature if you want to change permissions for the <ph>/db</ph>
                            root collection. </p>
                        <p>For example, to deny write permissions to others for the entire
                            database, change directory to the root collection (enter <ph>cd
                            /db</ph>) and enter:</p>
                        <pre>chmod other=-write</pre>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Use the GUI interface of the Dashboard's <xref href="{dashboard}" scope="external">User manager</xref> </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Do it programmatically, for instance from within eXide, by using the
                            one of the functions of the <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/securitymanager" scope="external">Security Manager XQuery library module</xref>.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </section>

            <section id="special-perm">
                    <title>Special permissions</title>
                

                <p>eXist-db also supports the setuid/setgid and sticky bit permissions:</p>

                <dl>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>setuid/setgid</dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>The setuid and setgid permissions are meant for being able to run
                                code as another user or group than what the query was started
                                with.</p>
                            <p>For example: Assume a query was started by user "Fred" in group
                                "normal-users". But the XQuery needs to do something that only the
                                admin user can do, for instance reach out to disk using the
                                <ph>file</ph> module, create a new user, change somebody else's
                                password, etc. Fred needs temporary admin rights to do so. With the
                                setuid/setgid mechanism, this can be implemented by creating a
                                module owned by admin and place the setuid bit on its permissions.
                                Now when code executes within this module, Fred is no longer Fred
                                but is temporarily disguised as admin.</p>
                            <p>In a permission string, the setuid/setgid permission replaces the
                                execute (<ph>x</ph>) marker of the user and/or group. It has two
                                possible values: </p>
                            <ul>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>s</ph> for setuid <i>and</i>
                                        execute permission. </p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>S</ph> for setuid permission only (without
                                        execute permission)</p>
                                </li>
                                </ul>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                        <dlentry>
                            <dt>Sticky bit</dt>
                            <dd>
                            <p>Sticky bits in eXist are useful on collections only. When a new
                                collection or document is created in eXist, it is allocated a
                                default permissions mode, based on the umask of the user which
                                created it. However, if the sticky bit is set on the parent
                                collection (the one in which the new document or collection is
                                created), the new document or collection inherits the permissions of
                                the Collection.</p>
                            <p>In a permission string, the sticky bit permission replaces the
                                execute (<ph>x</ph>) marker of the others. It has two possible
                                values: </p>
                            <ul>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>t</ph> for sticky bit
                                        <i>and</i> execute permission</p>
                                </li>
                                    <li>
                                    <p> <ph>T</ph> for sticky bit permission only
                                        (without execute permission)</p>
                                </li>
                                </ul>
                        </dd>
                        </dlentry>
                    </dl>

                <p>For more information:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <xref href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File_system_permissions#Traditional_Unix_permissions" scope="external">The Wikipedia entry about Unix permissions</xref>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <xref href="https://linux.die.net/man/1/chmod" scope="external">The Linux man page on the
                            <ph>chmod</ph> command</xref>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <xref href="http://permissions-calculator.org/" scope="external">A "calculator" for Unix
                            file permissions</xref>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>

            </section>

        </section>

        

        <section id="ACLs">
                <title>Access Control Lists (ACL)</title>
            

            <p>ACL's complement the <xref href="#unix-model" scope="local"/> implemented by eXist-db. When
                ACL's are employed these are evaluated first. If no match is found, the Unix
                permission model is evaluated.</p>
            <p>An ACL is a list of ACEs (Access Control Entries). When an ACL is evaluated, the
                list of ACE's are evaluated from top to bottom. Each ACE allows you to grant or deny
                additional permissions to a collection or document for a user or group. Each ACE has
                3 permission bits: <ph>r</ph> for read, <ph>w</ph> for write,
                and <ph>x</ph> for execute.</p>

            <p>ACL's are perhaps best illustrated by an example, consider the following document
                <ph>somedoc.xml</ph> which has the following permissions: </p>

            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/client-7.png" width="50%"/>
                </fig>

            <p> In this example, the document <ph>somedoc.xml</ph> is owned by
                <ph>fred</ph>. However our ACL has three ACEs which: </p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Deny the user <ph>bob</ph> read and write to the document (even
                        though he is an editor) (we won't pontificate about why
                        <ph>Bob</ph> is in disgrace with his fellow editors…).</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Allow the group <ph>editors</ph> read and write access to the
                        document.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Allow the group <ph>reviewers</ph> read only access to the
                        document.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>Because the ACL is evaluated from top-to-bottom, even though
                <ph>bob</ph> is in the <ph>editors</ph> group and editors are
                allowed read and write access to the document, there is an earlier rule which
                prohibits access for just <ph>bob</ph>. </p>
            <p>More information about ACLs is available as <xref href="http://www.adamretter.org.uk/presentations/security-in-existdb_xml-prague_existdb_20120210.pdf" scope="external">slides</xref> (PDF) and a presentation on <xref href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z_Dryy9DtVo" scope="external">YouTube</xref>.</p>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="permission-checks">
            <title>Permission Checks</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db enforces permission checks on each operation. The details of the permissions
            required for a specific operation are detailed below.</p>
        <p>
                <b>Document Permissions Matrix</b>
            </p>
            <simpletable>
                <sthead>
                    <stentry> Operation </stentry>
                    <stentry> Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry> Document </stentry>
                </sthead>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Open Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>--x</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> List Collection Contents </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>r-x</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Add Document </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Remove Document </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Overwrite Existing Document </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>--x</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-w-</ph> (or owner)  </stentry>
                </strow>
            </simpletable>
        <p>
                <b>Document Copy/Move Permissions Matrix</b>
            </p>
            <simpletable>
                <sthead>
                    <stentry> Operation </stentry>
                    <stentry> Source Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry> Source Document </stentry>
                    <stentry> Destination Collection (if exists) </stentry>
                    <stentry> Destination Document (if exists) </stentry>
                </sthead>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Copy Document </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>--x</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>r--</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph> (<ph>w</ph> only if destination document
                            does not exist) </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-w-</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Move/Rename Document </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>--x</ph> (or owner)  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-w-</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
            </simpletable>
        <p>
                <b>Collection Permissions Matrix</b>
            </p>
            <simpletable>
                <sthead>
                    <stentry> Operation </stentry>
                    <stentry> Parent of Source Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry> Source Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry> Parent of Destination Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry> Destination Collection (if exists) </stentry>
                </sthead>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Add Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Remove Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>rwx</ph> (and on all sub-collections)  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Copy Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>r-x</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Move/Rename Collection </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-w-</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>---</ph>  </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <ph>-wx</ph> (When replacing an existing collection,
                            permissions for removing that collection must be met first).
                        </stentry>
                </strow>
            </simpletable>
        <p>When copying a collection, permissions are checked for each sub-collection and
            resource.</p>
        <p>Copying a sub-collection requires <i>r-x</i> on the sub-collection and
            <i>rwx</i> on the destination collection. If the sub-collection already
            exists in the destination <i>r-x</i> is required on that.</p>
        <p>Copying resources from a collection requires <i>r--</i> on the resource,
            and <i>-w-</i> on the destination resource if it exists, otherwise
            <i>-w-</i> on the destination collection.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="security-manager">
            <title>The Security Manager</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db has a central Security Manager which is configured in the file
            <ph>/db/system/security/config.xml</ph>. This document, which is generated
            during database start-up, defines what authentication <i>realms</i> are
            available to the Security Manager.</p>
        <p>For example, this Security Manager configuration file defines a URL for
            authentication:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;security-manager xmlns="http://exist-db.org/Configuration" last-account-id="11" last-group-id="10" version="2.0"&gt;
  &lt;Authentication-Entry-Point&gt;
    /authentication/login
  &lt;/Authentication-Entry-Point&gt;
&lt;/security-manager&gt;</pre>

        <p>The Security Manager also features an authentication event listener that you can
            configure to call a custom XQuery module on each authentication event. For example, this
            configuration file would pass authentication events to module
            <ph>/db/security-events.xq</ph>:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;security-manager ... version="2.0"&gt;
    ...
    &lt;events script-uri="/db/security-events.xq"/&gt;
    ...
&lt;/security-manager&gt;</pre>

        <p>The XQuery module that receives the authentication events must be a library module in
            the <ph>http://exist-db.org/security/events</ph> namespace. It must have a
            function <ph>authentication()</ph>. This example sends a log message to the
            console:</p>
        <pre outputclass="xquery">xquery version "3.0";
 
module namespace sec-ev="http://exist-db.org/security/events";
 
declare function sec-ev:authentication() {
    util:log-system-out(concat("An authentication event has occurred for ", xmldb:get-current-user())))
};</pre>


        <section id="authentication-realms">
                <title>Authentication Realms</title>
            

            <p>eXist-db always has an internal authentication realm. It also supports multiple
                external authentication realms. This allows you to add one or more external realms
                which provide user and group authentication.</p>

            <section id="default-internal-realm">
                    <title>Default Internal Realm</title>
                

                <p>The "eXist-db realm" is the default internal realm. By default this realm
                    handles the <ph>SYSTEM</ph>, <ph>admin</ph> and <ph>guest</ph> users
                    and the <ph>DBA</ph> and <ph>guest</ph> groups. Any additional users or
                    groups created in eXist-db are added to this realm.</p>
                <p>Every eXist-db realm user has an account with a username, password and other
                    metadata, stored in the database. This user information for the eXist-db realm
                    is maintained in the collection
                    <ph>/db/system/security/exist</ph>.</p>

                <note type="notice">
                        <p>The security collections in <ph>/db/system/security</ph> should
                        <i>not</i> be manipulated or accessed directly . Only access
                        this information through the <ph>SecurityManager</ph> class or the
                        <ph>SecurityManager</ph> XQuery library module. Direct manipulation may
                        lead to inconsistent state and security issues.</p>
                    </note>

                <p>The following is a sample user account document for <ph>aretter</ph>
                    in the eXist-db realm:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;account xmlns="http://exist-db.org/Configuration" id="11"&gt;
  &lt;name&gt;
    aretter
  &lt;/name&gt;
  &lt;password&gt;
    {RIPEMD160}Vi7e971INiGmyWGT1bm63bHj1gf=
  &lt;/password&gt;
  &lt;group name="dba"/&gt;
  &lt;enabled&gt;
    true
  &lt;/enabled&gt;
  &lt;expired&gt;
    false
  &lt;/expired&gt;
  &lt;metadata/&gt;
&lt;/account&gt;</pre>

                <p>As you can see, eXist-db does not store passwords in the clear. It stores
                    hashed values of the passwords (in Base64 encoding), using the
                        <i>RIPEMD-160</i> cryptographic hashing algorithm. </p>
                <p>Whenever a user supplies account credentials for authentication, the database
                    applies RIPEMD-160 hash to the password and compares it to the hash stored in
                    the user's account document. Storing hashes of passwords is a best practice in
                    security that provides a strong layer of security compared to storing passwords
                    in the clear. The notion is that even if the hashed password is exposed to an
                    attacker, it is too difficult to derive the original password from the
                    hash.</p>
                <note type="note">
                        <p>RIPEMD-160 is a legacy algorithm. For new deployments or when upgrading
                        security configurations, stronger algorithms such as SHA-256 are
                        recommended.</p>
                    </note>
                <p>Note that the <ph>/db/system/security</ph> collection is (by
                    default) only readable and writable by the system or users in the
                    <ph>dba</ph> group. The <ph>dba</ph> group is reserved for
                    database administrators, and only <ph>dba</ph> users are allowed to
                    create, remove or modify other users.</p>
            </section>

            <section id="ldap-realm">
                    <title>LDAP Realm</title>
                

                <p>The LDAP Realm is enabled by default in the build configuration file
                    <ph>extensions/build.properties</ph>
                    (<ph>include.feature.security.ldap</ph> property). To use the LDAP
                    realm, add an LDAP realm element to
                    <ph>/db/system/security/config.xml</ph>. For example:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;realm id="LDAP" version="1.0" principals-are-case-insensitive="true"&gt;
  &lt;context&gt;
    &lt;authentication&gt;
      simple
    &lt;/authentication&gt;
    &lt;url&gt;
      ldap://ad.server.url.here:389
    &lt;/url&gt;
    &lt;domain&gt;
      domain.here
    &lt;/domain&gt;
    &lt;search&gt;
      &lt;base&gt;
        ou=group,dc=ad,dc=organiation-or-what-ever,dc=domain
      &lt;/base&gt;
      &lt;default-username&gt;
        account@domain.here
      &lt;/default-username&gt;
      &lt;default-password&gt;
        XXXXXXX
      &lt;/default-password&gt;
      &lt;account&gt;
        &lt;search-filter-prefix&gt;
          objectClass=user
        &lt;/search-filter-prefix&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="objectSid"&gt;
          objectSid
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="primaryGroupID"&gt;
          primaryGroupID
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="name"&gt;
          sAMAccountName
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="dn"&gt;
          distinguishedName
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="memberOf"&gt;
          memberOf
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;metadata-search-attribute key="http://axschema.org/namePerson/first"&gt;
          givenName
        &lt;/metadata-search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;metadata-search-attribute key="http://axschema.org/contact/email"&gt;
          mail
        &lt;/metadata-search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;metadata-search-attribute key="http://axschema.org/namePerson/last"&gt;
          sn
        &lt;/metadata-search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;metadata-search-attribute key="http://axschema.org/namePerson"&gt;
          name
        &lt;/metadata-search-attribute&gt;
      &lt;/account&gt;
      &lt;group&gt;
        &lt;search-filter-prefix&gt;
          objectClass=group
        &lt;/search-filter-prefix&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="member"&gt;
          member
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="primaryGroupToken"&gt;
          primaryGroupToken
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="objectSid"&gt;
          objectSid
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="name"&gt;
          sAMAccountName
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;search-attribute key="dn"&gt;
          distinguishedName
        &lt;/search-attribute&gt;
        &lt;whitelist&gt;
          &lt;principal&gt;
            Domain Users
          &lt;/principal&gt;
          &lt;principal&gt;
            Users_GROUP
          &lt;/principal&gt;
        &lt;/whitelist&gt;
      &lt;/group&gt;
    &lt;/search&gt;
    &lt;transformation&gt;
      &lt;add-group&gt;
        group.users
      &lt;/add-group&gt;
    &lt;/transformation&gt;
  &lt;/context&gt;
&lt;/realm&gt;</pre>

                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>The <ph>default-username</ph> and <ph>default-password</ph>
                            elements are used to communicate with the LDAP server if a non-LDAP user
                            requests information from LDAP server.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The <ph>search-*</ph> elements are mapping for names.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The <ph>metadata-search-attribute</ph> elements are used for mapping
                            LDAP account metadata onto eXist-db account metadata.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The <ph>whitelist</ph> element contains the allowed groups for
                            authentication. The <ph>blacklist</ph> element contains groups that
                            are not allowed.</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The <ph>transformation</ph> element contains actions to be performed
                            after first authentication.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </section>          

        </section>

    </section>
        <section id="legacy-internal-realm">
            <title>Legacy Internal Realm</title>
        

        <p>Before eXist-db 2.0, the internal security realm was maintained in a different manner.
            The details are included here for the purpose of informing decisions on
            migration.</p>
        <p>Every eXist-db database user has an account with a username, password and other
            information that is stored in the database. Furthermore, every user belongs to one or
            more groups - and respectively, every resource in the database is owned by a user and by
            a group. By default, the owner is set to the user who created the resource, and his
            primary group, but eXist-db allows for different permissions for the owner, the owner's
            group and others. However, only the owner of the resource (or <ph>dba</ph>
            users) can change these permissions.</p>
        <p>User and group information is found in the designated XML file
            <ph>/db/system/users.xml</ph> located in collection
            <ph>/db/system</ph>. This file is generated during database start-up. The
            following is a simple example of a <ph>users.xml</ph> document: </p>

        <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;auth&gt;
  &lt;groups last-id="3"&gt;
    &lt;group name="dba" id="1"/&gt;
    &lt;group name="guest" id="2"/&gt;
    &lt;group name="mygroup" id="3"/&gt;
  &lt;/groups&gt;
  &lt;users last-id="3"&gt;
    &lt;user name="admin" uid="1"&gt;
      &lt;group&gt;
        dba
      &lt;/group&gt;
    &lt;/user&gt;
    &lt;user name="guest" uid="2" password="e55d929cdbc8d5a7ce3bda044bc69f59"&gt;
      &lt;group&gt;
        guest
      &lt;/group&gt;
    &lt;/user&gt;
    &lt;user name="user-1" uid="3" password="7f0261c14d7d1b8e51680a013daa623e" home="my-collection"&gt;
      &lt;group&gt;
        my-group
      &lt;/group&gt;
    &lt;/user&gt;
  &lt;/users&gt;
&lt;/auth&gt;</pre>
        <p>As we see from this example, passwords are encrypted using an <i>MD5</i>
            algorithm (e.g. <ph>user-1</ph> has the <i>MD5</i>-encrypted
            password "7f0261c14d7d1b8e51680a013daa623e"). Therefore, whenever a user enters his or
            her password, the database generates an MD5 encryption and compares it to the encryption
            stored in <ph>users.xml</ph>. Since it is very difficult for users to guess
            the original password from the MD5 string, passwords in eXist-db should be sufficiently
            secure.</p>
        <p>Note that the <ph>/db/system</ph> collection is (by default) only readable
            by <ph>dba</ph> users (although it is possible to make it accessible by other
            users). The <ph>dba</ph> group is specially reserved for database
            administrators, and only <ph>dba</ph> users are allowed to create or remove
            users, or change permissions for other users.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>