<topic id="scheduler">
    <title>Scheduler Module</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="2Q19"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist has a job scheduler based on <xref href="http://www.quartz-scheduler.org/" scope="external">Quartz</xref>, a full-featured, open source job scheduling system. This article will
        explain how to use the scheduler.</p>
        <section id="job-schedule">
            <title>Scheduling Jobs</title>
        

        <p>Jobs can be configured for execution by the scheduler in one of two ways:</p>

        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>System Start-up</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Jobs may be statically scheduled by configuring them in the
                        <ph>scheduler</ph> element of eXist-db's <ph>conf.xml</ph>
                        configuration file. When eXist-db starts-up this configuration is read and
                        the jobs will be scheduled with the scheduler. The configuration file
                        contains (commented out) example jobs. An example of a scheduler
                        entry:</p>

                    <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;scheduler&gt;
  &lt;job type="user" class="com.example.MyJob" period="600000" delay="300000" repeat="10" unschedule-on-exception="false"/&gt;
&lt;/scheduler&gt;</pre>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Scheduler XQuery Module</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <note type="note">
                            <p>The XQuery function module for initiating and managing scheduled jobs
                            is not activated <i>out-of-the-box</i>. It
                            has to be activated through the <ph>conf.xml</ph> file. See below
                        </p>
                        </note>
                    <p>There is an XQuery library module, <xref href="{${fundocs.pkg.abbrev}}/view.html?uri=http://exist-db.org/xquery/scheduler" scope="external">Scheduler Module</xref>, which provides functions for scheduling jobs and
                        managing jobs scheduled for execution. The scheduler XQuery library module
                        is activated by uncommenting the following in eXist-db's
                        <ph>conf.xml</ph> configuration file:</p>
                    <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;module class="org.exist.xquery.modules.scheduler.SchedulerModule" uri="http://exist-db.org/xquery/scheduler"/&gt;</pre>
                    <p>Once the scheduler XQuery library module is active, XQuery code can be
                        written to invoke and manage <i>user</i> jobs (see <xref href="#sect-job-types" scope="local"/>).</p>

                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
        <p>The scheduler keeps a log file of its actions and issues that occur when executing
            jobs in <ph>logs/scheduler.log</ph>.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="sect-job-types">
            <title>Job Types</title>
        

        <p>The scheduler supports three different types of job, each of which has a distinct
            purpose:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>Startup</ph> </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Start-up jobs are executed only once during the database start-up. This
                        execution occurs before the database becomes available for general use. Each
                        start-up job is executed in-turn to completion.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>User</ph> </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>User jobs are a general class of job, authored by a user of the system.
                        They can be scheduled for execution either periodically or as a one-off. A
                        user job can also be configured to execute concurrently with another
                        instance of itself, should schedules overlap due to execution time, or be
                        mutually exclusive.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>System</ph> </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>System jobs are similar to user jobs, but require the database to be in a
                        consistent state: no other concurrent operations are running and all
                        in-memory buffers have been flushed to disk. These are typically used for
                        internal tasks such as flushing the database Journal. In general users
                        should avoid scheduling this type of job because all other database
                        operations will be paused until the job finishes or raises an exception. Any
                        exception will be caught and a warning is written to the scheduler
                        log.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
    </section>
        <section id="job-author">
            <title>Authoring Jobs</title>
        

        <p>The scheduler supports jobs that are authored in either XQuery or Java:</p>

        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>XQuery Jobs</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Jobs coded in XQuery can be <ph>user</ph> type jobs only.</p>
                    <p>An XQuery job is a standard XQuery Main Module which is stored in the
                        database. You configure the scheduling of the job by providing the database
                        path to the XQuery, for example: <ph>/db/my-collection/my-job.xq</ph>. </p>
                    <p>XQuery job's are launched under the <i>guest</i> account. If
                        you wish to perform tasks as another user , either switch permissions by
                        calling <ph>xmldb:login()</ph> from within your job, or set the
                        <ph>SetUid</ph>/<ph>SetGid</ph> bits on the XQuery file's
                        permissions (see <xref href="security" scope="external">Security</xref> for more
                        information).</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>Java Jobs</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Jobs coded in Java can be <ph>startup</ph>, <ph>system</ph> or
                        <ph>user</ph> type jobs.</p>
                    <p>A Java job is a class (available on eXist-db's classpath) which extends
                        either <ph>org.exist.scheduler.UserJavaJob</ph> (for <ph>user</ph>
                        type jobs) or <ph>org.exist.storage.SystemTask</ph>
                        (<ph>startup</ph> or <ph>system</ph> type jobs). For example:</p>

                    <pre outputclass="java">package com.example;

import java.util.Map;
import java.util.concurrent.atomic.AtomicInteger;

import org.exist.storage.BrokerPool;

public class MyJob extends UserJavaJob {

    private static final AtomicInteger COUNTER = new AtomicInteger();
    private String jobName = "MyJob";
    
	public void execute(final BrokerPool brokerpool, final Map&lt;String, ?&gt; params) throws JobException {

		System.out.println("****** My Job count=" + COUNTER.incrementAndGet());

	}

	public String getName() {
		return jobName;
	}

    public void setName(final String name) {
        this.jobName = name;
    }
}</pre>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
    </section>
        <section id="schedule">
            <title>Job Schedule</title>
        
        <p>Job's may be scheduled using one of two mechanisms, a simple mechanism for periodic
            execution, or a more complex mechanism which uses the Cron syntax to offer greater
            flexibility.</p>
        <section id="period">
                <title>Periodic Scheduling</title>
            

            <p>For period scheduling enables you can specify for the job to run every
                <ph>n</ph> milliseconds. There are additional options to specify a delay before
                the first execution of the job, and to only repeat the execution of the job schedule
                a fixed number of times.</p>
        </section>

        <section id="cron">
                <title>Cron Scheduling</title>
            
            <p>Cron scheduling enables you to specify the execution schedule of a job using the
                more complicated but flexible <xref href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cron" scope="external">Cron</xref> syntax.</p>
            <note type="note">
                    <p>This section was copied from the <xref href="http://www.quartz-scheduler.org/documentation/quartz-2.3.0/tutorials/crontrigger.html" scope="external">Quartz Cron Trigger Tutorial</xref>.</p>
                </note>

            <section id="cron-intro">
                    <title>Cron Introduction</title>
                

                <p> <ph>cron</ph> is a UNIX tool that has been around for a long time, so its
                    scheduling capabilities are powerful and proven. The <ph>CronTrigger</ph>
                    class is based on the scheduling capabilities of <ph>cron</ph>. </p>
                <p> <ph>CronTrigger</ph> uses "<ph>cron</ph> expressions", which are able
                    to create firing schedules such as: "At 8:00am every Monday through Friday" or
                    "At 1:30am every last Friday of the month". </p>
                <p> <ph>cron</ph> expressions are powerful, but can be confusing. This
                    tutorial aims to take some of the mystery out of creating a <ph>cron</ph>
                    expression, giving users a resource which they can visit before having to ask in
                    a forum or mailing list. </p>
            </section>

            <section id="cron-format">
                    <title>Cron Format</title>
                

                <p>A <ph>cron</ph> expression is a string comprised of 6 or 7 fields
                    separated by white space. Fields can contain any of the allowed values, along
                    with various combinations of the allowed special characters for that field. The
                    fields are as follows: </p>
                <simpletable>
                        <sthead>
                            <stentry> Field Name </stentry>
                            <stentry> Mandatory? </stentry>
                            <stentry> Allowed Values </stentry>
                            <stentry> Allowed Special Characters </stentry>
                        </sthead>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Seconds </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 0-59 </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * / </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Minutes </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 0-59 </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * / </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Hours </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 0-23 </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * / </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Day of month </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 1-31 </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * ? / L W </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Month </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 1-12 or JAN-DEC </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * / </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Day of week </stentry>
                            <stentry> YES </stentry>
                            <stentry> 1-7 or SUN-SAT </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * ? / L # </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry> Year </stentry>
                            <stentry> NO </stentry>
                            <stentry> empty, 1970-2099 </stentry>
                            <stentry> , - * / </stentry>
                        </strow>
                    </simpletable>
                <p>So <ph>cron</ph> expressions can be as simple as this: <ph>* * * * ?
                    *</ph> </p>
                <p>Or more complex, like this: <ph>0 0/5 14,18,3-39,52 ? JAN,MAR,SEP MON-FRI
                    2002-201</ph>0 </p>
            </section>

            <section id="cron-characters">
                    <title>Cron special characters</title>
                

                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>*</ph> ("all values") - used to select all values within a
                            field. For example, "*" in the minute field means "every minute".
                        </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>?</ph> ("no specific value") - useful when you need to
                            specify something in one of the two fields in which the character is
                            allowed, but not the other. For example, if I want my trigger to fire on
                            a particular day of the month (say, the 10th), but don't care what day
                            of the week that happens to be, I would put "10" in the day-of-month
                            field, and "?" in the day-of-week field. See the examples below for
                            clarification. </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>-</ph> - used to specify ranges. For example, "10-12" in the
                            hour field means "the hours 10, 11 and 12". </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>,</ph> - used to specify additional values. For example,
                            "MON,WED,FRI" in the day-of-week field means "the days Monday,
                            Wednesday, and Friday". </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>/</ph> - used to specify increments. For example, "0/15" in
                            the seconds field means "the seconds 0, 15, 30, and 45". And "5/15" in
                            the seconds field means "the seconds 5, 20, 35, and 50". You can also
                            specify '/' after the '' character - in this case '' is equivalent to
                            having '0' before the '/'. '1/3' in the day-of-month field means "fire
                            every 3 days starting on the first day of the month". </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>L</ph> ("last") - has different meaning in each of the two
                            fields in which it is allowed. For example, the value "L" in the
                            day-of-month field means "the last day of the month" - day 31 for
                            January, day 28 for February on non-leap years. If used in the
                            day-of-week field by itself, it simply means "7" or "SAT". But if used
                            in the day-of-week field after another value, it means "the last xxx day
                            of the month" - for example "6L" means "the last friday of the month".
                            When using the 'L' option, it is important not to specify lists, or
                            ranges of values, as you'll get confusing results. </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>W</ph> ("weekday") - used to specify the weekday
                            (Monday-Friday) nearest the given day. As an example, if you were to
                            specify "15W" as the value for the day-of-month field, the meaning is:
                            "the nearest weekday to the 15th of the month". So if the 15th is a
                            Saturday, the trigger will fire on Friday the 14th. If the 15th is a
                            Sunday, the trigger will fire on Monday the 16th. If the 15th is a
                            Tuesday, then it will fire on Tuesday the 15th. However if you specify
                            "1W" as the value for day-of-month, and the 1st is a Saturday, the
                            trigger will fire on Monday the 3rd, as it will not 'jump' over the
                            boundary of a month's days. The 'W' character can only be specified when
                            the day-of-month is a single day, not a range or list of days. The 'L'
                            and 'W' characters can also be combined in the day-of-month field to
                            yield 'LW', which translates to "last weekday of the month". </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p> <ph>#</ph> - used to specify "the nth" XXX day of the month. For
                            example, the value of "6#3" in the day-of-week field means "the third
                            Friday of the month" (day 6 = Friday and "#3" = the 3rd one in the
                            month). Other examples: "2#1" = the first Monday of the month and "4#5"
                            = the fifth Wednesday of the month. Note that if you specify "#5" and
                            there is not 5 of the given day-of-week in the month, then no firing
                            will occur that month. The legal characters and the names of months and
                            days of the week are not case sensitive. MON is the same as mon. </p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </section>

            <section id="ex-cron">
                    <title>Cron examples</title>
                

                <p>Here are some full examples:</p>
                <simpletable>
                        <sthead>
                            <stentry> Expression </stentry>
                            <stentry> Meaning </stentry>
                        </sthead>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 0 12 * * ? </ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry>  Fire at 12pm (noon) every day  </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 * * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 * * ? *</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 * * ? 2005</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am every day during the year 2005
                                </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 * 14 * * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire every minute starting at 2pm and ending at
                                    2:59pm, every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 0/5 14 * * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire every 5 minutes starting at 2pm and ending at
                                    2:55pm, every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 0/5 14,18 * * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire every 5 minutes starting at 2pm and ending at
                                    2:55pm, AND fire every 5 minutes starting at 6pm and ending at
                                    6:55pm, every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 0-5 14 * * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire every minute starting at 2pm and ending at
                                    2:05pm, every day </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 10,44 14 ? 3 WED</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 2:10pm and at 2:44pm every Wednesday in the
                                    month of March. </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 ? * MON-FRI</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am every Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday,
                                    Thursday and Friday </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 15 * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on the 15th day of every month
                                </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 L * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on the last day of every month
                                </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 ? * 6L</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on the last Friday of every
                                    month </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 ? * 6L</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on the last Friday of every
                                    month </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 ? * 6L 2002-2005</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on every last friday of every month
                                    during the years 2002, 2003, 2004 and 2005 </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 15 10 ? * 6#3</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 10:15am on the third Friday of every
                                    month </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 0 12 1/5 * ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire at 12pm (noon) every 5 days every month, starting
                                    on the first day of the month. </stentry>
                        </strow>
                        <strow>
                            <stentry>  <ph>0 11 11 11 11 ?</ph>  </stentry>
                            <stentry> Fire every November 11th at 11:11am. </stentry>
                        </strow>
                    </simpletable>
                <p>Pay attention to the effects of '?' and '*' in the day-of-week and
                    day-of-month fields!</p>
            </section>

            <section id="cron-notes">
                    <title>Cron additional notes</title>
                

                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>Support for specifying both a day-of-week and a day-of-month value is
                            not complete (you must currently use the '?' character in one of these
                            fields). </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Be careful when setting fire times between mid-night and 1:00 AM -
                            "daylight savings" can cause a skip or a repeat depending on whether the
                            time moves back or jumps forward.</p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>