<topic id="upgrading">
    <title>Upgrade Guide</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q20"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article explains the best practices for upgrading eXist-db. It provides instructions
        for several different types of upgrades. Following these instructions will ensure your data
        is properly backed up and preserved during the upgrade process.</p>
        <section id="key-concepts">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        
        <p>The primary goal of an upgrade is to migrate your eXist application to a new version,
            while preserving the contents of your database.</p>
        <p>Before embarking on an upgrade, you should first review the new version's release
            notes (see the <xref href="https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/wiki/blogs/eXist/" scope="external">eXist Developer's
            Blog</xref> for an archive of all past release notes). The release notes introduce the
            new version's features, improvements and bug fixes. They can also outline any new
            requirements (for instance the required version of Java). </p>
        <p>For the purpose of this guide, the most important item in the release notes is whether
            the new version is <i>binary-compatible</i> with the previous version or
            not. Pay close attention to these notes, as they will tell you which upgrade route to
            follow.</p>
        <p>If a new version is binary-compatible with the previous version, it means the format
            eXist uses to store the contents of the database has not changed. The data can be used
            by new version without modification. </p>
        <p>However, if a new version is <i>not</i> binary-compatible, the new
            version of eXist has changed the way it reads data from or stores data into the
            database. Additional steps are required to migrate your data to the new version of
            eXist.</p>
        <p>Always back up your data before upgrading to any new version of eXist.</p>
        <p>Do not install the new version of eXist over the previous version. Instead, install
            the new version into a fresh new directory.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="binary-compatible-upgrades">
            <title>Binary Compatible Upgrades</title>
        

        <p>Follow these steps if the new version of eXist is binary-compatible with the your old
            version (as can be found in the release notes):</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Stop the existing installation of eXist.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Create a <xref href="backup" scope="external">backup</xref> of the data from your
                    existing installation.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Install the new version of eXist. Do <i>not</i> install one
                    eXist version over the existing one. Always install the new version into a fresh
                    new directory.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Remove the still <i>empty</i> <ph>data</ph> directory from
                    the new installation. By default the data directory is located at
                    <ph>$EXIST_HOME/data</ph>. If you are not sure where the data directory is,
                    check the main logfile <xref href="troubleshooting#logs" scope="external">
                    <ph>exist.log</ph> </xref>, searching for entries after start-up pertaining
                    to <ph>DATA_DIR</ph>. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Copy the entire existing data directory, and paste it to the location of the
                    new data directory (the directory you deleted in the previous step).</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Start the new eXist instance.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Check the <xref href="troubleshooting#logs" scope="external"> <ph>exist.log</ph>
                    </xref> for any errors during startup.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
        <section id="non-binary-compatible-upgrades">
            <title>Binary Non-compatible Upgrades</title>
        

        <p>Follow these steps if the new version of eXist is not binary-compatible with the your
            old version (as can be found in the release notes). The key difference with upgrading to
            a binary-compatible new version is that you have to perform a <i>full
            restore</i> of your backed-up data into the new installation.</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Create a <xref href="backup" scope="external">server-side backup</xref>. This can be done
                    in a number of ways: </p>
                <ol>
                        <li>
                        <p>Use Backup Central from the Dashboard</p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The Emergency Export Tool (GUI):</p>
                        <ol>
                                <li>
                                <p>Unix/Linux:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="shell">bin/export-gui.sh</pre>
                            </li>
                                <li>
                                <p>Windows:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="shell">bin\export-gui.bat</pre>
                            </li>
                            </ol>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>The Emergency Backup Tool (CLI) for headless sytems:</p>
                        <ol>
                                <li>
                                <p>Unix/Linux:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="shell">bin/export.sh</pre>
                            </li>
                                <li>
                                <p>Windows:</p>
                                <pre outputclass="shell">bin\export.bat</pre>
                            </li>
                            </ol>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>Via XQuery:</p>
                        <pre outputclass="xquery">system:trigger-system-task("org.exist.storage.ConsistencyCheckTask",
    &lt;parameters&gt;
        &lt;param name="backup" value="yes"/&gt;
        &lt;param name="output" value="export"/&gt;
    &lt;/parameters&gt;)</pre>
                    </li>
                    </ol>
                <p>Once the backup is complete, you should check the backup report in the
                    <ph>export</ph> directory within either the <ph>data</ph> directory (for
                    backups created via the Dashboard or Xquery) or <ph>$EXIST_HOME</ph> (for
                    backups created by the Emergency Backup Tool).</p>
                <p>Normally this report just contains the list of collections which were backed
                    up. If you see any warnings or errors, it is even more important to perform a
                    “full restore” of your backed-up data.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Stop the existing installation of eXist.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Install the new version of eXist. DO NOT install one eXist version over
                    another one. Always install the new version into a fresh new directory.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Perform a full <xref href="backup#restore" scope="external">restore</xref> of the backup
                    onto the new version of eXist.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
        <section id="upgrading-from-source">
            <title>Upgrading from Source</title>
        
        <p>The following steps only apply to users who wish to upgrade eXist instances that were
            built from (modified) source code, instead of from the provided installers.</p>
        <p>Before attempting to upgrade always perform a <xref href="backup" scope="external">full
            backup</xref>. Stop eXist after the backup has been generated.</p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Determine which files contain local modification and would be in conflict with
                    updated files from the new version of exist-db, by running <ph>git
                    status</ph> inside the local folder where you cloned exist. You should pay
                    special attention to Configuration files, such as:</p>
                <ul>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>etc/conf.xml</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>etc/webapp/WEB-INF/controller-config.xml</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                        <li>
                        <p>
                                <ph>etc/jetty/webapps/exist-webapp-context.xml</ph>
                            </p>
                    </li>
                    </ul>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>A typical sequence to replay the local modifications on top of the upstream
                    changes to the master branch would look like this:</p>
                <pre outputclass="shell">git fetch
git stash
git rebase origin/master
git stash pop
</pre>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Finally follow the <xref href="https://github.com/eXist-db/exist/blob/develop/BUILD.md" scope="external">build
                    instructions</xref> for eXist-db.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>
    </section>
        <section id="upgrading-docker">
            <title>Upgrading docker images</title>
        
        <p>When following eXist-db's stable release channel via the docker <ph>release</ph> tag, orchestrators will automatically check and pull newer images.
        To avoid that you accidentally pull a binary incompabtile image that will break your container, we recommend testing your app on a continous integration service on both <ph>release</ph>, and <ph>latest</ph>.
        This way your <ph>CI</ph> will inform you and prevent incompatible upgrades making it into production.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="compatibility-history">
            <title>History of Non-compatible Upgrades</title>
        

        <p>This is a list of binary non-compatible releases for quick reference.</p>
        <p>If a non-incremental upgrade across multiple non-compatible releases is necessary, for
            instance from 1.4 to 3.6, we strongly recommend to first check past release notes to
            understand how breaking changes might affect you.</p>
        <note type="notice">
                <p>Note, database backups from eXist-db 2.2 and earlier are not compatible with
                eXist-db 5.0.0+. If you wish to migrate to eXist-db version 5.0.0+ from version 2.2
                or earlier, you should first upgrade (incrementally if nessecary) to the latest
                4.x.x version.</p>
            </note>
        <p>
                <b>Notes on previous releases</b>
            </p>
            <simpletable>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> Latest </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/wiki/blogs/eXist/" scope="external">Release
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> 4.5.0 </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="incompatibilities#v4.5.0" scope="external">Special
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> 3.0 </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="incompatibilities#v3.0" scope="external">Special
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> 2.2 </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="incompatibilities#v2.2" scope="external">Special
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> 2.0 </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="incompatibilities#v2.0" scope="external">Special
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
                <strow>
                    <stentry> 1.4.0 </stentry>
                    <stentry>  <xref href="incompatibilities#v1.4" scope="external">Special
                            notes</xref>  </stentry>
                </strow>
            </simpletable>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>