<topic id="devguide_soap">
    <title>SOAP Interface Developer's Guide</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="1Q18"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="java-development"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="interfaces"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>This article explains how to add a SOAP interface to eXist-db using Java code.</p>
        <section id="intro">
            <title>Introduction</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db provides a SOAP interface as an alternative to XML-RPC. Programming with SOAP
            is slightly more convenient than XML-RPC. While you have to write XML-RPC method calls
            by hand, most SOAP tools will automatically create the low-level code from a given WSDL
            service description. Also fewer methods are needed to exploit the same functionality. On
            the other hand, SOAP toolkits tend to be complex.</p>
        <note type="notice">
                <p>SOAP is not available in the (default configuration) stand-alone server.</p>
            </note>
        <p>eXist-db uses the Axis SOAP toolkit from Apache, which runs as a servlet. The Tomcat
            webserver shipped with eXist has been configured to start Axis automatically, and will
            listen on port 8080: <ph>http://localhost:8080/exist/services</ph>. </p>

        <p>The interface has been tested using various clients, including Perl (SOAP::Lite) and
            the Microsoft .NET framework. The client stubs needed to access the SOAP interface from
            Java have been automatically generated by Axis and are included in the
            distribution.</p>

    </section>
        <section id="web-service">
            <title>Web services</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db provides two web services: one that contains methods to query the server and
            retrieve documents: </p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>A service to query the server and retrieve documents. This will listen
                    on:</p>
                <pre>http://localhost:8080/exist/services/Query</pre>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>A service for storing and removing documents and collections. This will listen
                    on:</p>
                <pre>http://localhost:8080/exist/services/Admin</pre>
            </li>
            </ul>

        <p>Both services are described in the Java docs regarding their interfaces.</p>

        

    </section>
        <section id="example">
            <title>Example</title>
        

        <p>The following example demonstrates how to retrieve a document from the database using
            SOAP:</p>

        <pre outputclass="java">package org.exist.examples.soap;

import org.exist.soap.Query;
import org.exist.soap.QueryService;
import org.exist.soap.QueryServiceLocator;

public class GetDocument {

    public static void main( String[] args ) throws Exception {
        QueryService service = new QueryServiceLocator();
        Query query = service.getQuery();
		String session = query.connect("guest", "guest");
        
		byte[] data = query.getResourceData(session, 
			"/db/shakespeare/plays/hamlet.xml",
			true, false, false);
		System.out.println(new String(data, "UTF-8"));
		query.disconnect(session);
    }
}</pre>

        <p>The <ph>Query</ph> client stub class has been automatically generated by the
            WSDL service description. It has methods for each of the operations defined in the WSDL.
            You will find the web service description file <ph>query.wsdl</ph> in
            directory <ph>src/org/exist/soap</ph>. </p>
        <p>To use the services provided, the client first has to establish a connection with the
            database. This is done by calling <ph>connect()</ph> with a valid user id and
            password. <ph>connect()</ph> returns a session id, which can then be passed to
            any subsequent method calls.</p>
        <p>To retrieve a resource simply call <ph>Query.getResource()</ph>. </p>
        <p>To release the current session, the method <ph>Query.disconnect()</ph> is
            called. Otherwise the session will remain valid for at least 60 minutes.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>