<topic id="advanced-installation">
    <title>Advanced Installation Methods</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="4Q24"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="installation"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="operations"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>The eXist-db <xref href="basic-installation" scope="external">Basic Installation</xref> article
        describes how to install and start eXist-db for basic usage. This article explains more
        advanced methods of installing and running eXist, for instance for a headless (no GUI)
        system, running it as a service, etc.</p>
        <section id="headless">
            <title>Headless Installation</title>
        
        <p>The <xref href="basic-installation" scope="external">Basic Installation</xref> of eXist-db
            requires a graphical desktop. You can also install eXist on a headless (no GUI) system.
            For this launch the installer from the command line, using the <ph>-console</ph>
            option:</p>
        <pre>java -jar eXist-{version}.jar -console</pre>
        <p>In console mode, the installer will prompt for several parameters (almost like the GUI
            version does). A dump of a sample interaction is shown below:</p>
        <pre>$ java -jar exist-installer/target/exist-installer-5.0.0-RC8-SNAPSHOT.jar
Select target path [/Users/wolf/Source/trunk/eXist] 
/Applications/eXist/
press 1 to continue, 2 to quit, 3 to redisplay
1
Set Data Directory
Please select a directory where eXist will keep its data files. On Vista and Windows 7, this should be outside the usual 'Program Files' directory:
Data dir:  [data] 

press 1 to continue, 2 to quit, 3 to redisplay
1
Set Admin Password
Enter password:  [] 
xyz
Enter password:  [xyz] 
xyz
------------------------------------------

Max memory in mb: [1024] 

Cache memory in mb: [128] 

press 1 to continue, 2 to quit, 3 to redisplay
1
[ Starting to unpack ]
[ Processing package: Core (1/13) ]
[ Processing package: Sources (2/13) ]
[ Processing package: Apps (3/13) ]
[ Processing package: bfDemos (4/13) ]
[ Processing package: bfReferences (5/13) ]
[ Processing package: dashboard (6/13) ]
[ Processing package: demo (7/13) ]
[ Processing package: doc (8/13) ]
[ Processing package: eXide (9/13) ]
[ Processing package: fundocs (10/13) ]
[ Processing package: shared (11/13) ]
[ Processing package: xsltforms (12/13) ]
[ Processing package: xsltforms-demo (13/13) ]
[ Unpacking finished ]
[ Starting processing ]
Starting process Setting admin password ... (1/1)
--- Starting embedded database instance ---
File lock last access timestamp: 30.12.2012 /Applications/eXist/data/dbx_dir.lck
Found a stale lockfile. Trying to remove it:  /Applications/eXist/data/dbx_dir.lck
File lock last access timestamp: 30.12.2012 /Applications/eXist/data/journal.lck
Found a stale lockfile. Trying to remove it:  /Applications/eXist/data/journal.lck
Dez 30, 2012 10:13:26 PM org.expath.pkg.repo.util.Logger info
INFO: Create a new repository with storage: File system storage in /Applications/eXist/data/expathrepo
Setting admin user password...
--- Initialization complete. Shutdown embedded database instance ---
[ Console installation done ]</pre>
        <section id="docker-compose">
                <title>Multi-container environments</title>
            <p>We highly recommend configuring a <ph>docker-compose.yml</ph> for local development or integration into multi-container environments.</p>
            <pre># starting eXist-db
docker-compose up -d
# stop eXist-db
docker-compose down</pre>
            <p>You can see an example configuration file below. Note that e.g.<ph>${EXIST_DATA_DIR}</ph> can be passed from an external file, and the use of the <ph>volume</ph> instructions. For all the available options please consult the <xref href="https://docs.docker.com/compose/" scope="external">docker compose</xref> documentation.</p>
            <pre>version: '3.6'
services:
  exist:
    image: existdb/existdb:release
    container_name: exist
    ports:
        - 8080:8080
        - 8443:8443
    networks:
      - www
    volumes:
      - type: volume
        source: data
        target: ${EXIST_HOME}/${EXIST_DATA_DIR}
      - type: volume
        source: config
        target: ${EXIST_HOME}/${EXIST_CONFIG_DIR}

volumes:
  data:
    driver: local
    name: exist-data
  config:
    driver: local
    name: exist-config

networks:
  www:
    name: www
    driver: bridge</pre>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="service">
            <title>Running eXist-db as a Service</title>
        
        <p>Instead of manually running the eXist-db server in a shell window, you can run it as a
            background service which is automatically launched during system start-up. This can be
            convenient, especially for servers. eXist-db continues to run even after users have
            logged off.</p>

        

        <section id="windows">
                <title>Windows</title>
            
            <p>On Windows there are three identical options:</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>Choose <ph>Install eXist-db as Service</ph> from the
                        eXist-db's system tray application.</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>Choose <ph>Install eXist-db as Service</ph> from
                        eXist-db's entry in the Windows start menu.</p>
                </li>
                </ul>
            <p>Installing eXist-db as a service on Windows requires full administrator
                rights.</p>

            <p>After installing eXist-db as a service, you'll find eXist-db in the list of
                services registered with Windows:</p>
            <fig>
                    <image href="assets/services.png"/>
                </fig>
        </section>

        

        <section id="linux">
                <title>Unix/Linux</title>
            
            <p> If your system supports <ph>systemd</ph> you can run the service wrapper as a
                non-privileged user.</p>
            <p>Begin by creating a new user in your system which is being created specifically to
                run eXist-db as a service. You can do this by typing the following command:</p>
            <pre>sudo useradd --system --shell /sbin/nologin --comment "eXist-db Service Account" existdb</pre>
            <p>To follow the examples here this user is part of an existdb user group:</p>
            <pre>sudo groupadd existdb</pre>
            <p>This command creates a new system user named "existdb" which does not need to
                login in order to run a service. In order for this new system user to be able to run
                eXist-db, we need to change the permission of eXist-db to match this new user. You
                do so by navigating to your <ph>$EXIST_HOME</ph> folder and typing the
                following two commands:</p>
            <pre>sudo chown -R existdb:existdb .
</pre>
            <p>These two commmands modify the ownership and group permissions recursively
                throughout the whole eXist-db project to your new existdb system user. Now only this
                user can run eXist-db. Next, navigate to the <ph>/etc/systemd/system</ph>
                sub-directory. Once there, create an existdb.service file which contains the
                following information at a minimum:</p>
            <pre>[Unit]
Description=eXist-db Server
Documentation=https://exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/
After=syslog.target

[Service]
Type=simple
User=existdb
Group=existdb
Environment="JAVA_HOME=/path/to/jdk8"
Environment="JAVA_OPTS=-XX:+UseG1GC -XX:+UseStringDeduplication -XX:MaxRAMPercentage=75.0"
ExecStart=/path/to/exist-5.0.0/bin/startup.sh

[Install]
WantedBy=multi-user.target
</pre>
            <p>Once this file is stored in this location, you need to update permissions. Give
                ownership of this file to the exist user by using the following commands:</p>
            <pre>sudo chown existdb:existdb existdb.service
</pre>
            <p>You can then install the existdb service, by runniung <ph>sudo systemctl daemon-reload &amp;&amp; sudo systemctl enable existdb</ph>.
                If you then want to start eXist-db as a service, run <ph>sudo systemctl start existdb</ph>.</p>
            <p>Below is a list of common commands to interact with the newly created and
                configured service:</p>
            <ul>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>sudo systemctl start existdb</ph> - Enter command to
                        start eXist-db</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>sudo systemctl stop existdb</ph> - Enter command to stop
                        eXist-db</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>sudo systemctl enable existdb</ph> - Enter command to
                        enable eXist-db to automatically start running after a reboot of your
                        system</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>sudo systemctl disable existdb</ph> - Enter commande to
                        disable eXist-db from automatically starting after a reboot of your
                        system</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>sudo systemctl restart existdb</ph> - Enter command to
                        restart eXist-db</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>systemctl status existdb</ph> - Enter command to check the status
                        of eXist-db</p>
                </li>
                    <li>
                    <p>
                            <ph>journalctl</ph> - Run the following command to check systemd
                        journal</p>
                </li>
                </ul>
        </section>
    </section>
        <section id="bin-executables">
            <title>Alternatives for scripts in the bin Directory</title>
        

        <p>Included in the distribution are a number of useful <ph>.sh</ph> (Unix
            Shell) and <ph>.bat</ph> (Windows batch) programs located in the
            <ph>bin</ph> sub-directory. Their names speak for themselves.</p>
        <p>However, if you find that programs do not launch, you can try to manually launch them
            on the command-line without the scripting wrapper. This often provides useful debugging
            information.</p>
        <p>To manually launch these scripts, give the following commands:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>startup.sh</ph> (Unix) / <ph>startup.bat</ph> (Windows)</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Starts the included Jetty web server at port 8080. eXist runs as a web
                        application, located at <xref href="http://localhost:8080/exist/" scope="external">http://localhost:8080/exist/</xref>.
                        For further options have a look at the following section about 
                        <xref href="#cli-flags" scope="external">command line flags</xref>.
                    </p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>shutdown.sh</ph> (Unix) / <ph>shutdown.bat</ph> (Windows)</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <pre>shutdown.sh -p youradminpassword</pre>
                    <p>Closes the running instance of eXist. If eXist has been started with
                        <ph>startup.sh</ph>, calling <ph>shutdown.sh</ph> will
                        also stop the Jetty web server. Otherwise, only the database is stopped by
                        this call (since eXist has no control over the environment in which it is
                        running). You should <i>always</i> call
                        <ph>shutdown</ph> before killing the server process.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>client.sh</ph> (Unix) / <ph>client.bat</ph> (Windows)</dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Use one of these scripts to launch the <xref href="java-admin-client" scope="external">Java Admin Client</xref>.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
    </section>
        <section id="cli-flags">
            <title>Command line flags to set host, ports and configuration</title>
        
        <p>There are several java tool options available to change the host, http and
            https port on which existdb will listen.
        </p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>jetty.host</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>controls on which IP jetty binds to (default is 0.0.0.0)</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>jetty.http.port</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>controls on which port jetty will listen for HTTP-requests (default is
                        8080)</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>jetty.ssl.port</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                     <p>controls on which port jetty will listen for HTTPS-requests
                          (default is 8443)</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt> <ph>JAVA_OPTS='-Djetty.host=127.0.0.1 -Djetty.http.port=9999' startup.sh</ph>
                </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Example for linux/unix:</p>
                    <p>Starts the included Jetty web server at port 9999 that will only listen
                        on the local IP 127.0.0.1. eXist runs as a web application, located at
                        <xref href="http://127.0.0.1:9999/exist/" scope="external">http://127.0.0.1:9999/exist/</xref>.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>