<topic id="development-starter">
    <title>Getting Started with Web Application Development</title>
    <prolog>
        <data name="date" value="4Q24"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="getting-started"/>
        <data name="keyword" value="application-development"/>
    </prolog>
    <body>
        <p>eXist-db is much more than just an XML database. It is also an excellent platform for the
        development of rich web applications, based on XML and related technologies (XQuery, XForms,
        XSLT, XHTML...). This article describes one of the possible approaches and demonstrates how
        to quickly prototype an application, using the following key components:</p>
        <p/>
        <ul>
            <li>
            <p>A standardized packaging format for modular applications, allowing deployment into
                any eXist-db instance.</p>
        </li>
            <li>
            <p>A set of tools to create application packages, integrated into our XQuery IDE,
                eXide.</p>
        </li>
            <li>
            <p>An <xref href="templating" scope="external">HTML templating framework</xref> for a clean
                separation of HTML page content and application logic.</p>
        </li>
            <li>
            <p>A tight integration with XForms for fast form development.</p>
        </li>
            <li>
            <p>A clean approach for the deployment of RESTful services based on XQuery code
                annotations (RESTXQ).</p>
        </li>
        </ul>
        <note type="note">
            <p> Those working on data sets in TEI may want to look at <xref href="https://teipublisher.com" scope="external">TEI Publisher</xref> also. It includes an
            application generator tailored at digital editions. The created app packages include all
            the basic functionality needed for browsing the edition, searching it or producing PDFs
            and ePUBs.</p>
        </note>
        <section id="packaging">
            <title>Packaging</title>
        

        <p>eXist-db builds on the concept of self-contained, modular applications using a
            standardized packaging format. Applications live inside the database, so application
            code, HTML views, associated services and data all reside in the same place. This allows
            packaging an application and pass it to someone else for installation in another
            database. It might even be published to eXist-db's public repository. The packaging
            format is compliant with the <xref href="http://expath.org/modules/pkg/" scope="external">EXPath packaging proposal</xref>, though it
            extends it considerably.</p>

        <p>For distribution, an application is packed into a <ph>.xar</ph> archive, which is
            basically a ZIP archive. The <ph>.xar</ph> archive contains all the application code
            and optionally data.</p>
        <p>The documentation, the dashboard, eXide and the eXist XQuery Features Demo are all
            examples of these application packages. </p>


        <p>The packaging format includes descriptor files. These describe the application and
            control the installation process. As an absolute minimum, an application package
            <i>must</i> contain two descriptor files:
            <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> and <ph>repo.xml</ph>. You can read more
            about these files in the <xref href="repo" scope="external">package repository
            documentation</xref>. Detailed knowledge about these files is not required for the
            following sections: eXide will create the proper basic descriptors for you
            automatically.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="starting">
            <title>Starting a New Application</title>
        

        <p>There are many ways to start new applications on your local environment, we provide a  <xref href="https://github.com/eXist-db/generator-exist" scope="external">yeoman generator</xref> to be run from your commandline.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="default-structure">
            <title>The Default Application Structure</title>
        

        <p>eXide has created an application skeleton for you which works out of the box. All
            resources of the application reside below the target collection
            (<ph>/db/tutorial</ph>).</p>
        <p>The generated collection hierarchy follows a certain structure, which is usually the
            same for all apps which ship with eXist-db. The most important collections and files are
            described below:</p>
        <dl>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>/modules/</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Contains XQuery modules. The actual application code should go
                        here.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>/resources/</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Resources like CSS files, images or JavaScript.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>/templates/</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Page templates containing all the repeating parts of the site's HTML
                        layout.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>collection.xconf</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>A template file for the index configuration for this application. This
                        file will be copied into the correct system collection when the application
                        is installed. This causes automatic indexing of installed data.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>controller.xq</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The URL rewriting controller, which handles the URL handling of the
                        application. You will rarely need to change this for simple
                        applications.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> and <ph>repo.xml</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>Package descriptor files for the application. These contain the
                        information you entered via the Deployment Editor. You don't need to edit
                        these files directly. Instead, open the Deployment Editor to change any of
                        the descriptor properties.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>index.html</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>The default start page of the application.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
                <dlentry>
                    <dt>
                        <ph>pre-install.xql</ph>
                    </dt>
                    <dd>
                    <p>An XQuery script run by the package manager <i>before</i>
                        installing the app. By default, the script only ensures the index
                        configurations (in <ph>collection.xconf</ph>) is properly copied to the
                        corresponding system collection.</p>
                    <p>In addition to <ph>pre-install.xql</ph>, you may also define a
                        <ph>post-install.xql</ph> script via the Deployment Editor. As the
                        name says, this script will run after the app is deployed into the database.
                        It is most often used to copy resources or run initialization tasks.</p>
                </dd>
                </dlentry>
            </dl>
        <p>You are not required to keep this structure. Feel free to restructure the app as you
            like it and remove some of its parts. However, preserve the two descriptor files
            <ph>expath-pkg.xml</ph> and <ph>repo.xml</ph>.</p>
    </section>
        <section id="html-templating">
            <title>The HTML Templating Framework </title>
        

        <p>The generated application code uses the <xref href="templating" scope="external">HTML Templating
            Framework</xref> to connect HTML views with the application logic. The goal of the HTML
            Templating Framework is a clean separation of concerns. If you look at the
            <ph>index.html</ph> page, you'll see it is just an HTML div defining the
            actual content body. The rest of the page is dragged in from the page template residing
            in <ph>templates/page.html</ph>.</p>
        <p>The <ph>controller.xq</ph> is configured to call the HTML Templating for
            every URL ending with <ph>.html</ph>. The process flow for an arbitrary
            <ph>.html</ph> file is shown below:</p>
        <fig>
                <title>Processing Flow</title>
                <image href="assets/Templating.png"/>
            </fig>
        <p>The input for the templating is always a plain HTML file. The module scans the HTML
            view for elements with class attributes, following a simple convention: It tries to
            translate the class attributes into XQuery function calls. By using <ph>class</ph>
            attributes, the HTML remains sufficiently clean and does not get messed up with
            application code. A web designer could take the HTML files and work on them without
            being bothered by this.</p>
        <p>For instance, if you look at <ph>index.html</ph>, the <ph>class</ph>
            attribute on the outer <ph>div</ph> contains a call to a templating function:</p>
        <pre outputclass="html">&lt;div class="templates:surround?with=templates/page.html&amp;amp;at=content"&gt;</pre>
        <p> <ph>templates:surround</ph> is one of the default templating functions provided
            by the module. It loads <ph>templates/page.html</ph> and inserts the current
            div from <ph>index.html</ph> into the element with the id <ph>content</ph>
            in <ph>templates/page.html</ph>. A detailed description of
            <ph>templates:surround</ph> can be found in the HTML templating module
            documentation.</p>
        <p>Add your own templating functions to the XQuery module
            <ph>modules/app.xql</ph>. Or add your own modules by importing them in
            <ph>modules/view.xql</ph>). </p>
    </section>
        <section id="ex-hello">
            <title>Example: "Hello World!"</title>
        

        <p>As an example let's implement the traditional "Hello World!": </p>
        <ol>
                <li>
                <p>Create a new HTML view, <ph>hello.html</ph>: Choose
                    <ph>File, New</ph> from the menu and set the <ph>file
                    type</ph> to HTML (drop down box at the top right in eXide). Add the
                    following contents:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xml">&lt;div class="templates:surround?with=templates/page.html&amp;amp;at=content"&gt;
    &lt;form action=""&gt;
        &lt;label for="name"&gt;Enter your name:&lt;/label&gt;
        &lt;input name="name"/&gt;
    &lt;/form&gt;
    &lt;p class="app:helloworld"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</pre>
                <p>This creates a simple form and a paragraph connected to the template function
                    <ph>app:helloworld</ph> through its class attribute.</p>
                <p>Save the HTML view to the root collection of your application as
                    <ph>/db/apps/tutorial/hello.html</ph>.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Open <ph>modules/app.xql</ph> and add an XQuery function matching
                    the <ph>app:helloworld</ph> template call:</p>
                <pre outputclass="xquery">declare function app:helloworld($node as node(), $model as map(*), $name as xs:string?) {
    if ($name) then
        &lt;p&gt;Hello {$name}!&lt;/p&gt;
    else
        ()
};</pre>

                <p>A template function is a normal XQuery function with two required parameters:
                    <ph>$node</ph> and <ph>$model</ph>. Additional parameters are allowed
                    (see below).</p>
                <p>
                        <ph>$node</ph> is the HTML element currently being processed, in our
                    example case a <ph>p</ph> element. <ph>$model</ph> is an XQuery map
                    containing application data. We can ignore both parameters for this simple
                    example, but they must be present or the function won't be recognized by the
                    templating module. Please refer to the <xref href="templating" scope="external">HTML
                    templating documentation</xref> for more information.</p>
                <p>The third parameter, <ph>$name</ph>, is injected automatically by the
                    templating framework. The templating library will try to make a best guess about
                    how to fill in any additional parameters. In this case, an HTTP request
                    parameter called <ph>name</ph> will be passed in when the form is submitted.
                    The parameter <ph>name</ph> matches the name of the variable, so the
                    templating framework will try to use it and the function parameter will be set
                    to the value of this request parameter. </p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>Open <ph>hello.html</ph> in the web browser using the base URL of
                    the app:</p>
                <pre>http://localhost:8080/exist/apps/tutorial/hello.html</pre>
                <p>Fill out the box with a name and press return.</p>
            </li>
            </ol>

    </section>
        <section id="export">
            <title>Exporting the App</title>
        

        <p>Once you have created the first pages of an application, it is a good idea to export
            it to a folder on disk. One way to do this is choose <ph>Application,
            Download</ph> from the menu to create a <ph>.xar</ph> archive of the
            application. You can however also export the app to the file system which has the
            advantage that you can continue working on the app and have eXide keep track of which
            files were modified since the last export. With a copy on the file system you can also
            add it to a version control system like GIT or SVN.</p>
        <p>To create an export to the file system, click choose <ph>Application,
            Synchronize</ph> from the menu. In the popup dialog, fill in the path to the
            desired <i>Target directory</i>: </p>
        <ul>
                <li>
                <p>If you are accessing eXist-db on a server, not the machine you are opening
                    eXide in, this must point to a directory <i>on the server</i>
                    running eXist-db, not your local file system.</p>
            </li>
                <li>
                <p>If you are running eXist from your own machine use this.</p>
            </li>
            </ul>

        <p>The <ph>Start time</ph> can be ignored for now. It will show the
            date/time of your last export when you synchronize again.</p>
        <fig>
                <title>Synchronize Dialog</title>
                <image href="assets/sync-dialog.png"/>
            </fig>
        <p>Clicking on <ph>Synchronize</ph> starts the export. The names of the
            resources written show up in the table at the bottom of the dialog.</p>
    </section>
    </body>
</topic>